<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>http://benmccormick.org</id>
    <title>benmccormick.org</title>
    <updated>2018-01-12T14:39:07Z</updated>
    <generator>Feed for Node.js</generator>
    <author>
        <name>Ben McCormick</name>
        <email>ben@benmccormick.org</email>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://benmccormick.org"/>
    <link rel="self" href="http://benmccormick.org/atom.xml"/>
    <subtitle>A blog by Ben McCormick</subtitle>
    <logo>https://benmccormick.org/logo.png</logo>
    <icon>https://benmccormick.org/favicon.ico</icon>
    <rights>All rights reserved 2016, Ben McCormick</rights>
    <contributor>
        <name>Ben McCormick</name>
        <email>ben@benmccormick.org</email>
        <uri>http://benmccormick.org</uri>
    </contributor>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Weekly Links: January 12th]]></title>
        <id>https://benmccormick.org/2018/01/12/weekly-links-01-12-18/</id>
        <link href="https://benmccormick.org/2018/01/12/weekly-links-01-12-18/">
        </link>
        <updated>2018-01-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>JavaScript And The Web</h3>
<p><a href="https://egghead.io/courses/manage-application-state-with-mobx-state-tree">Manage Application State with Mobx-state-tree| Michael Weststrate on Egghead</a>  - Mobx-state-tree is an opinionated state library built on top of the unopinionated Mobx library.  This is a free course explaining why it exists and how to use it.  I <a href="https://benmccormick.org/2017/01/09/mobx-first-impressions/">wrote about Mobx last year</a> and am still enjoying using it a year later.  I’m excited to dive into Mobx-state-tree and hopefully sharpen my Mobx skills in the process.</p>
<h3>Programming Tools And Practices</h3>
<p><a href="http://blog.atom.io/2018/01/10/the-state-of-atoms-performance.html">The State of Atom’s Performance | Atom Blog</a> - Atom continues to (slowly) become snappier.  I’m glad to see how organized they are on this.  It’s really hard to take something that was built with a slower architecture fast while it’s being used by tens of thousands of people every day.  They’re making great progress.</p>
<p><a href="http://amzn.to/2DqBeSQ">Clean Architecture | Robert C Martin</a> - I’ll probably be posting more on this soon, but I’ve been reading the new book on Architecture by “Uncle Bob” Martin, and it’s fantastic.  It breaks down big architecture and program design concepts like the Single Responsibility Principle and Dependency Inversion, and explains them well individually, but also shows how they fit together when designing a large system.  I’ll write a full review when I finish the book, but for now just wanted to share that it is worth picking up.</p>
<h3>Non-Tech</h3>
<p><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2018/01/09/us/north-carolina-gerrymander.html">North Carolina Is Ordered To Redraw Its Congressional Map | NY Times</a> - A little bit of local news here <sup id="fnref-1"><a href="#fn-1" class="footnote-ref">1</a></sup>, but it is still important for everyone in the USA.  Redistricting is the type of problem where a simple rules based algorithm could be helpful.  Nothing opaque or deep-learning-y, just have a machine apply a published set of rules and work with the results.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn-1">
<p>I’m a proud resident of Durham, North Carolina</p>
<a href="#fnref-1" class="footnote-backref">↩</a>
</li>
</ol>
</div>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Ben McCormick</name>
            <email>ben@benmccormick.org</email>
            <uri>http://benmccormick.org</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tips For Improving a Large Code Base With A Small Team]]></title>
        <id>https://benmccormick.org/2018/01/07/large-improvements-small-team/</id>
        <link href="https://benmccormick.org/2018/01/07/large-improvements-small-team/">
        </link>
        <updated>2018-01-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Over the last year I’ve been acting as the lone JavaScript resource working on a codebase with around 90k lines of JavaScript code.  That has left me spending the vast majority of my work time trying to knock out features and deal with bugs across the large code surface area.  But I’ve also wanted to do my best to continue to improve code quality with limited resources.  Here are a few things I’ve learned about trying to improve code quality across a large project with limited resources.</p>
<h4>1. You need to accept not being on the bleeding edge</h4>
<p>Let’s be real, in the JavaScript world the only way to always be on the bleeding edge is to never maintain an application for more than a few weeks.  And even in other contexts, it often is much less feasible than hype bubbles at conferences or sites like Hacker News might make it seem.  Most companies that are shipping software that users actually pay for are using quite a lot of very old technology quite extensively.  That’s not to say there’s no place for new and shiny things, but there will always be limits to how new and shiny things get.  When you’re low on people resources for the size of your project, those limits get a lot more restrictive.</p>
<h4>2. It’s important to identify your pain points.</h4>
<p>There are 3 main type of value that developers can add by changing a software system. They can write new <strong>features</strong>, which give users new capabilities.  They can improve some <strong>cross-feature attributes</strong> of the system like loading speed, accessibility, design, logging or documentation.  Or they can make <strong>architecture improvements</strong> that make it easier to make other changes.  Generally engineers don’t have to argue to add features, because the business decision makers will be calling for them constantly.  Cross-feature things like performance, design or logging sometimes come from business decision makers, but often only when things have become problematic, and then the conversations around how long it will take to achieve improvements can be tense ones.  Architecture concerns pretty much never come from business folks, because they usually don’t see the effects of a bad architecture until it is too late and shipping simple features has become a disastrously slow process<sup id="fnref-1"><a href="#fn-1" class="footnote-ref">1</a></sup>.  It’s part of a developer’s job to push for the latter 2 type of changes when they’re needed.   But with limited resources, <em>needed</em> is often hard to quantify.</p>
<p>That’s why it is important to know what is <em>actually</em> causing you pain, or will soon be causing pain.  Is your site getting slower and slower?  Is your CSS a giant tangled mess that creates bugs with every change<sup id="fnref-2"><a href="#fn-2" class="footnote-ref">2</a></sup>?  Make a list, and then prioritize it by importance and expected effort.</p>
<h4>3. Take things one at a time</h4>
<p>Once you have a list of things that you want to fix, it can be tempting to try to fit those fixes in all over the places.  You’re creating a new page, might as well write it in Vue instead of Angular.  You’re changing some styles, maybe you can use a CSS in JS library.  But the absolute worst thing you can do with limited resources is try to improve too many things at once.  You’ll end up with a codebase with many different ways to do everything, so that every change requires a full context reset, and maintenance means dealing with multiple sets of bugs and compatibility issues for each duplicated approach.  That’s why prioritization is critical.  With limited bandwidth, you need to know what <strong>one thing</strong> will be the best use of your time.</p>
<h4>4. Expand from small footholds, don’t boil the ocean</h4>
<p>A few truths to note at this point:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Changing large systems is hard.</strong>  They have a million different subtle assumptions weaved into their code, and making seemingly the same change in different places can often produce subtly different results.  </li>
<li><strong>Practice is how you learn to use a tool or technique optimally.</strong> Unless you’ve already used a technology extensively in a different context, you will never be more blind to it’s downsides than at the start of adding it to a project.  As you begin using it, you’ll learn more about it and how to use it better in your system.</li>
<li><strong>Well designed systems have good interface points</strong>.  Interface points are areas where one part of the system doesn’t need to care about the details of how other parts of the system are implemented, they just need to know the <em>interface</em> for interacting with that part of the system.  For example, when using React, parent components don’t need to know the details of how a child component work, just what props they take.  Similarly when writing HTMl, you don’t need to know the details of how CSS will work for layout, you just need to expose meaningful class names that CSS can use.  A website doesn’t need to know what language a web server is written in to make HTML requests to it.  These are examples of interface points, and while well designed systems will have more of them and fewer “breaches” of the interface lines, all systems have them to some extent.</li>
</ol>
<p>The implication of these truths is that there is value in starting small and expanding.  If we can pick a small section of the application that is cordoned off from the rest of the code in a meaningful way, we can create a foothold for the new technology.  This serves as a learning opportunity, an example, and a starting place.  If it goes badly, small changes are easy to revert or fix.  If it works well, we can look for more similar interface boundaries, or expand out to convert some of the code that uses the new code.</p>
<p>When I converted a large Backbone app to use React, I took advantage of 2 different interface boundaries.  I started by converting small “widget” components to be written in React, and came up with a method of calling these widgets from within Backbone code.  Once I had enough of these building block widgets written in React, I started writing new pages in React.  Then finally I would convert subsections of Backbone driven pages to React, starting from the bottom up and converting the top level layouts of the page last.  I was using 2 interface boundaries: components and pages.  That made sense for Backbone to React, where I was essentially converting one type of component tree to another.  But the lines may be different for other changes, and you’ll need to use your judgement.</p>
<h4>5. Automate what you can</h4>
<p>Not every change needs to be hard and slow.  Sometimes we can take advantage of automation. Tools like <a href="https://prettier.io/">Prettier</a> and <a href="https://eslint.org/">ESLint</a> make it easy to automate code style and correctness fixes.  Tools like React often provide <a href="https://github.com/reactjs/react-codemod">codemods</a> to help make it easier to update to a new version of the tool or use best practices.  Unit tests can help you prevent regression bugs and are easy to automate with a CI server or <a href="https://benmccormick.org/2017/02/26/running-jest-tests-before-each-git-commit/">pre-commit hooks</a>.  </p>
<p>If you’re dealing with problems that are more specific to your codebase, it may make sense to invest time into writing your own automation scripts, whether that means hacking together a crazy bash/python script to do a massive find and replace, or using a tool like Ansible to automate some previously manual developer processes. It made a big difference in our company when our QA developer put in the work to automate the creation of consistent local environments.</p>
<h4>6. Count the cost of maintenance</h4>
<p>With a small team, some improvements may simply not be worth it over time.  Genuinely valuable things like test coverage, JSDoc style automated documentation, old browser support, add overhead to future changes as well as any up front cost to implement. These are the type of things that advocates tend to moralize about, and say that it’s the developers job to advocate for them.  And that is true as I alluded to earlier.  But when faced with limited resources, it’s important to prioritize, and understanding the cost of maintaining certain improvements is part of that.</p>
<h4>7. Distinguish between craftsmanship and business needs</h4>
<p>Along the same lines, as developers we’re often encouraged to think of ourselves as craftsmen.  Think of <a href="https://thenextweb.com/apple/2011/10/24/steve-jobs-obsession-with-the-quality-of-the-things-unseen/">Steve Jobs talking about using good wood for the back of a cabinet</a> or the aforementioned moralizing about code and process quality.  There are great things about this, since it is a developers job to look after the quality and craftsmanship of their product.  But it also is good to align that craftsmanship with business needs and create something that is useful rather than merely theoretically beautiful.  So there is a place for making changes to improve the “purity” of code, but when investing limited resources, it’s even more important than usual to balance that with business needs.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn-1">
<p>I’ve gotten to work with plenty of non-devs who respect the need for good architecture.  They still aren’t going to be able to identify when changes need to happen.</p>
<a href="#fnref-1" class="footnote-backref">↩</a>
</li>
<li id="fn-2">
<p>Little known fact: CSS actually stands for “Giant Tangled Mess that creates bugs with every change”</p>
<a href="#fnref-2" class="footnote-backref">↩</a>
</li>
</ol>
</div>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Ben McCormick</name>
            <email>ben@benmccormick.org</email>
            <uri>http://benmccormick.org</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Weekly Links: January 5th]]></title>
        <id>https://benmccormick.org/2018/01/05/weekly-links-01-05-18/</id>
        <link href="https://benmccormick.org/2018/01/05/weekly-links-01-05-18/">
        </link>
        <updated>2018-01-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Working in The Tech Industry</h3>
<p><a href="https://blog.codinghorror.com/to-serve-man-with-software/">To Serve Man With Software | Jeff Atwood</a> - This is a great review of the ethical questions that software developer’s face in the modern world.  Is your work actually serving anyone who isn’t invested in your employer?</p>
<p><a href="https://m.signalvnoise.com/basecamp-doesnt-employ-anyone-in-san-francisco-but-now-we-pay-everyone-as-though-all-did-3ee87013cfc2">Basecamp doesn’t employ anyone in San Francisco, but now we pay everyone as though all did | Basecamp</a> - On a similar vein, this is a tech employer holding themselves to a higher standard in terms of benefiting their employees<sup id="fnref-1"><a href="#fn-1" class="footnote-ref">1</a></sup>.  Also this quote is a fantastic summary of the type of software companies I want to work for:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Especially in software, which is a profitable business when run with restraint and sold to businesses.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>There’s a glorification of the unicorn startup in the tech world, but you can go a long way with low costs and high paying customers (and it’s easier to “serve man with software” without outside pressure to grow like crazy)</p>
<h3>Non-Tech (“Less-Tech”?)</h3>
<p><a href="https://github.com/zonination/perceptions">Perceptions of Probability and Numbers | Zoni Nation</a> -  This is simply a collection of visualizations of a dataset pulled from Reddit of what probabilities people associate with common english phrases used to express uncertainty.  I found it fascinating.</p>
<p>
  <a
    class="gatsby-resp-image-link"
    href="undefined"
    style="display: block"
    target="_blank"
    rel="noopener"
  >
  
  <span
    class="gatsby-resp-image-wrapper"
    style="position: relative; z-index: -1; display: block; "
  >
    <span
      class="gatsby-resp-image-background-image"
      style="padding-bottom: 100%;position: relative; width: 100%; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url('data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAABQAAAAUCAIAAAAC64paAAAACXBIWXMAAAsSAAALEgHS3X78AAACk0lEQVQ4y5WUy0/UUBTG+UNcqEtXJiauXLky7NyKMTFiXBiNrtAFJkJiYtRgXOBrY4xGBAXD8B5hGAQyKcO08yjTdqbtbXvv7RSmw8TAxpVfpyMtEDV8SSdn7tzf/c4593Q6mjH5vp/P57PZrCRJsiyXSiVRFAVBME0zvq3hN8Kgo3lE+XW/9noy5I8G+1t1511qt2/ME5U2TCklhCA3y7Lq9bp7WJy7luNYTqU/s9uT2Xmw6olqo9Ho2G7JMAzwEYzdNovjjLLiy2Ktl9b7rM0la9PkAYzdtm0DrlQq+MRXHhNjjJhWeYWIw1bycUN4tl1NbNobFOsBHBYDc8dxwHueR2IyTTyORVhq2p8a+TX80c+kt3SN4ydcTRtG2TFnl9Ao4aLhXppYvj5ZvTXFzo3WBlGvUUNN+5zNwIUcbth6RT85O308Kd/IeHfE5nPJVRyO9TYMQ5QNGP6AGec643vwUCl/Ymmup6CPaCRvU8K4yTjlPHJGA/ZgAEtqYaEsPRRnxuW1txvSC728RswDGUVw2Cf4Ax6XV86k7nWuDtzNfX4qfx81JcOxC7aBjFqXyMuUWIxGMJbCqwY8b6zdXrx6ef5C1/T5m+lrK9X1tJnjnP/VGREmJIQLubGZqe73iYuvJk6/SXZ++9GrG8rhqYtg3JOqqigbsDTXPztwLJU4uzh3RScC91TqatyNnA1TNYzWeOJBnzRN03UdzhjE3FCX8uSUmpvhzKFOMHz7pdtEw6DDJphtHKYoSrVaBR9M6/IH91G3MXifKQJ3rIPvCLVdztppYzdOCycknDBWLOx8Hfr55ZOXXqhlBTdIx/1XzXHhztFb9M/+I8Q4PQxCYcN//gyQRaUlkGgKgnARMN4inPUbWRkMZn+diEgAAAAASUVORK5CYII='); background-size: cover; display: block;"
    >
      <img
        class="gatsby-resp-image-image"
        style="width: 100%; margin: 0; vertical-align: middle; position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; box-shadow: inset 0px 0px 0px 400px white;"
        alt="An example graph from the repo"
        title=""
        src="/static/31375424926ff146bd5d5564b41153e0-d766e.png"
        srcset="/static/31375424926ff146bd5d5564b41153e0-a6b6e.png 143w,
/static/31375424926ff146bd5d5564b41153e0-8e488.png 285w,
/static/31375424926ff146bd5d5564b41153e0-d766e.png 570w,
/static/31375424926ff146bd5d5564b41153e0-13239.png 855w,
/static/31375424926ff146bd5d5564b41153e0-4f46e.png 960w"
        sizes="(max-width: 570px) 100vw, 570px"
      />
    </span>
  </span>
  
  </a>
    </p>
<p><a href="http://mashable.com/2017/12/27/browser-bar-url-facebook-bad/">Stop Using Facebook and Start Using Your Browser | Foster Kamer</a> - This is a call for people to get out of their social media bubble and <em>internet like it’s 2005</em>.  Use bookmarks, type in URLs directly, basically go to sites directly for content instead of relying on social media algorithms to find stuff for you.  I think this is easier said than done.  Social networking sites are ingrained into our culture at this point. You don’t replace culture by condemning it, and telling everyone to go without but by creating something new or better<sup id="fnref-2"><a href="#fn-2" class="footnote-ref">2</a></sup>.  So what can we make as Internet users that provides something as easy or easier than the mindless serendipity of social media, but produces better outcomes?  </p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn-1">
<p>Feel free to be cynical about this as a marketing ploy, but I’m all for companies marketing themselves by actually improving how they compensate their employees.</p>
<a href="#fnref-1" class="footnote-backref">↩</a>
</li>
<li id="fn-2">
<p>If you’d like to read a whole book making that argument, I recommend <a href="http://amzn.to/2F9xdD6"> Culture Making by Andy Crouch</a></p>
<a href="#fnref-2" class="footnote-backref">↩</a>
</li>
</ol>
</div>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Ben McCormick</name>
            <email>ben@benmccormick.org</email>
            <uri>http://benmccormick.org</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[2017 Roundup]]></title>
        <id>https://benmccormick.org/2017/12/30/2017-roundup</id>
        <link href="https://benmccormick.org/2017/12/30/2017-roundup">
        </link>
        <updated>2017-12-30T00:00:00Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>2017 was the 5th full year of this blog, and in many ways it was the most productive.  I wrote one of the most popular things I’ve written on here, started the weekly links section (on hiatus for New Years, but will return next week), and wrote 21 full articles and 8 weekly links post, the most I’ve ever posted here in a year.  Here are some of the highlights from my blog and development this year.</p>
<h3>Most Read Posts Published in 2017</h3>
<ol>
<li>
<p><a href="https://benmccormick.org/2017/07/19/ten-things-javascript/">Ten Things A Serious JavaScript Developer Should Learn</a> - It turns out that making lists of things is a good way to get traffic.  I wonder if anybody else on the internet has figured this out?</p>
<p>
  <a
    class="gatsby-resp-image-link"
    href="undefined"
    style="display: block"
    target="_blank"
    rel="noopener"
  >
  
  <span
    class="gatsby-resp-image-wrapper"
    style="position: relative; z-index: -1; display: block; "
  >
    <span
      class="gatsby-resp-image-background-image"
      style="padding-bottom: 18.202247191011235%;position: relative; width: 100%; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url('data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAABQAAAAECAYAAACOXx+WAAAACXBIWXMAAAsSAAALEgHS3X78AAAAlklEQVQY042Puw7CMAxF8/9/xsLMytIUaCgiSdM4ji9OCgwICYYj+XlkGxHBP9RGJrBfQHYCDU+sA43uPWdeAX4Ir6kgpQxpUhWwiqrKQWUD0ulCrgLiul3xRdb6B7fgOCf4teA+BwQlaRx1L5SKSNwdpgmIBUELbbFRP17NOrgbPPaniDEQbCyYEuO2Mi6L5lo7R+rSB/qnOWb4mDEeAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC'); background-size: cover; display: block;"
    >
      <img
        class="gatsby-resp-image-image"
        style="width: 100%; margin: 0; vertical-align: middle; position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; box-shadow: inset 0px 0px 0px 400px white;"
        alt="An analytics graph with a big spike in July when I posted my list post"
        title=""
        src="/static/bf4aa20172b0ec0f0d0791d56219f6d6-d766e.png"
        srcset="/static/bf4aa20172b0ec0f0d0791d56219f6d6-a6b6e.png 143w,
/static/bf4aa20172b0ec0f0d0791d56219f6d6-8e488.png 285w,
/static/bf4aa20172b0ec0f0d0791d56219f6d6-d766e.png 570w,
/static/bf4aa20172b0ec0f0d0791d56219f6d6-13239.png 855w,
/static/bf4aa20172b0ec0f0d0791d56219f6d6-cb86a.png 890w"
        sizes="(max-width: 570px) 100vw, 570px"
      />
    </span>
  </span>
  
  </a>
    </p>
<p>In all seriousness, I think there’s a hunger out there for clearer roadmaps for folks who are early out in their front end development career.  People are telling them to learn all the frameworks, all the tools and all the compile-to-JS languages, and everyone knows they can’t learn it all.  So even an imperfect list that can serve as a starting point for figuring that out can get some traction.  This article was my attempt to answer “what should a serious mid-level JavaScript developer have learned and be learning?“.  </p>
</li>
</ol>
<ol start="2">
<li>
<p><a href="https://benmccormick.org/2017/07/10/how-to-follow-the-javascript-roadmap/">How To Follow The JavaScript Roadmap</a> - This post was aimed at a similar audience to the “Serious JavaScript Developer” post, but aimed to help folks who want to follow changes in the JavaScript language keep up with new developments.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://benmccormick.org/2017/01/03/orthogonality-and-css-in-js/">Orthogonality and CSS in JS</a> - This article was an examination of the architecture tradeoffs of CSS in JS solutions, and also an examination of how people discuss “separations of concerns” in general.  If you liked this one, keep your eyes open.  I’m planning on writing more architecture level posts in 2018.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h3>Code I wrote in 2017</h3>
<p>Most of the code I wrote this year was again for my work at Windsor Circle.  But I’ve continued to add new features to this blog, which is based on React and Gatsby, and the source code for that is available <a href="https://github.com/benmccormick/benmccormickorg">on Github</a>.</p>
<h3>Talks I gave in 2017</h3>
<p>This was a big speaking year for me.  I gave 3 different talks: <a href="https://www.slideshare.net/BenMcCormick/vim-survival-guide-71763917">The Vim Survival Guide</a> at Open Source 101, <a href="https://www.slideshare.net/BenMcCormick/gatsby-intro">Intro to Gatsby</a> at a local meetup group and <a href="https://www.slideshare.net/BenMcCormick/saving-time-by-testing-with-jest">Saving Time with Jest</a> at All Things Open.  I’d be interested in giving any of those talks again next year, so if you’re looking for a speaker, feel free to reach out.</p>
<h3>Languages, Libraries, and Technologies I started using in 2017</h3>
<ul>
<li>
<p><a href="https://mobx.js.org/">Mobx</a> is a JavaScript data modeling library that serves as an alternative to Redux or React state for state management.  I wrote about my <a href="https://benmccormick.org/2017/01/09/mobx-first-impressions/">first impressions</a> at the beginning of the year, but I’ve continued to use it and love it since then.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://yarnpkg.com/en/">Yarn</a> was a nice upgrade over npm.  My understanding is that npm has since stepped up and closed the gap here, but I’m continuing to use Yarn for now since it has taken over my projects and muscle memory.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>When I upgraded this blog to Gatsby 1.0, I had the opportunity to learn about <a href="http://graphql.org/">GraphQL</a>.  I’ve really enjoyed getting to play with it and love the GraphQL community’s dedication to providing a great developer experience.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3>Languages and Libraries I used (more or less) every day in 2017</h3>
<p>JavaScript (ES6), Python, React, PostgreSQL, Backbone (<strong>sigh</strong>), lodash, MobX, Jest</p>
<h3>Languages and Libraries I want to try in 2018</h3>
<p><a href="https://github.com/FormidableLabs/victory">Victory</a>, Rust, and Pandas/other python data analysis libraries <sup id="fnref-1"><a href="#fn-1" class="footnote-ref">1</a></sup></p>
<h3>Blogs I started following in 2017</h3>
<p><a href="http://blog.isquaredsoftware.com/">Mark Erikson’s Dev blog</a></p>
<h3>Blogs I read every post from in 2017</h3>
<p><a href="http://randsinrepose.com/">Rands In Repose</a>, <a href="https://stratechery.com/">Stratechery</a>, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/">Daring Fireball</a>, <a href="http://purposedworking.org/">purposedworking.org</a>, <a href="https://wynnnetherland.com/">wynnnetherland.com</a></p>
<h3>Podcasts I started listening to in 2017</h3>
<ul>
<li>
<p><a href="https://www.npr.org/sections/money/">Planet Money</a> - A long running NPR podcast about money, the economy, and the unexpected ways they affect our everyday lives</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://www.theallusionist.org/">The Allusionist</a> - A great podcast on the crazy history behind different words in the English language.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3>Software I started using in 2017</h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.bear-writer.com/">Bear</a> - I mentioned I was testing this out at the end of last year, but it has become my go-to notes application, and I would recommend it to anyone who wants a stylish notes app in the middle ground between Apple Notes and Evernote (and who uses Apple products).</li>
</ul>
<h3>Software I used (nearly) every day in 2017</h3>
<p>MacOS/iOS, Google Search, Chrome/Safari/Firefox, GMail/MailPlane 3, Twitter/Tweetbot, Feedbin/Reeder, Instapaper, iMessage, Slack, Trello, 1Password, Atom/Vim, iTerm, Fish Shell, Bitbucket, Fantastical, Spotify, Bear, Annotate, Dash</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn-1">
<p>Yes this is basically the same list as last year.  ¯\_(ツ)_/¯ I mostly learn tech as I have need for it, and it was a very “nose to the grindstone” year focused on improving existing codebases this year</p>
<a href="#fnref-1" class="footnote-backref">↩</a>
</li>
</ol>
</div>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Ben McCormick</name>
            <email>ben@benmccormick.org</email>
            <uri>http://benmccormick.org</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Weekly Links: December 23rd 2017]]></title>
        <id>https://benmccormick.org/2017/12/23/weekly-links-12-23-17/</id>
        <link href="https://benmccormick.org/2017/12/23/weekly-links-12-23-17/">
        </link>
        <updated>2017-12-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>JavaScript And The Web</h3>
<p><a href="http://raganwald.com/2017/12/14/73939133.html">73,939,133 / Truncatable Primes | Reg Braithwaite</a> - A nice writeup about how brute force can be useful in solving a <a href="https://projecteuler.net/">Project Euler</a> style math problem.</p>
<h3>Programming Tools and Practices</h3>
<p><a href="http://facebook.github.io/jest/blog/2017/12/18/jest-22.html">Jest 22: Refinements &#x26; Custom Runners | Jest Blog</a> - This looks like a solid refinement release for Jest.  One warning: If you’re running <code>jest -o</code> on precommit hooks as I described <a href="https://benmccormick.org/2017/02/26/running-jest-tests-before-each-git-commit/">here</a>, Jest 22 fails when run with 0 tests, so you need to specify the <code>--passWithNoTests</code> flag in order to let things go when you make a change that doesn’t affect any tests.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.gatsbyjs.org/blog/2017-12-20-introducing-the-gatsby-ux-research-program/">Introducing The Gatsby UX Research Program | Gatsby Blog</a> - An unusual case of doing real UX research for an open source developer tool.  Very cool stuff.</p>
<h3>Non-Tech</h3>
<p><a href="https://www.justinobeirne.com/google-maps-moat">Google Maps’s Moat</a> - If you have any interest in product design, maps, or computer intelligence, this is the one article you need to read this week.  Beautifully put together.  It’s an in depth examination of the difference between Google and Apple maps, but it reads as a deeper exploration of how big data combined with computer learning and automation can have a huge impact on product design.</p>
<p><a href="https://izbicki.me/blog/how-to-cheat-at-settlers-of-catan-by-loading-the-dice-and-prove-it-with-p-values.html">How to cheat at settlers by loading the dice | Mike Izbicki</a> - This is just a fun application of statistics to my favorite board game.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Ben McCormick</name>
            <email>ben@benmccormick.org</email>
            <uri>http://benmccormick.org</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Weekly Links: December 15th 2017]]></title>
        <id>https://benmccormick.org/2017/12/15/weekly-links-12-15-17/</id>
        <link href="https://benmccormick.org/2017/12/15/weekly-links-12-15-17/">
        </link>
        <updated>2017-12-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>JavaScript And The Web</h3>
<p><a href="https://stateofjs.com/">The State Of JavaScript 2017</a> - This annual survey of JavaScript developers always has lots of interesting insights.  Since it is an internet survey, I view it less as a full snapshot of the industry, but more as a place to see what is new and trending in the JS world.  This year <a href="https://code.visualstudio.com/">Visual Studio Code</a>, <a href="https://prettier.io/">Prettier</a> and <a href="https://vuejs.org/">Vue</a> caught my eye as spiking in popularity.</p>
<p><a href="https://engineering.linkedin.com/blog/2017/12/the-glimmer-binary-experience">The Glimmer Binary Experience | LinkedIn Engineering</a> - I had the privilege of seeing Yehuda Katz, one of the Ember core developers, give a talk about <a href="https://glimmerjs.com/">Glimmer</a> and bytecode at this year’s All Things Open conference.  They’re doing some pretty serious software engineering in the Ember community right now.  This write-up covers a lot of the same ground and is worth a read.</p>
<h3>Programming Tools and Practices</h3>
<p><a href="http://blog.atom.io/2017/12/12/atom-1-23.html">Atom 1.23</a> and <a href="https://code.visualstudio.com/updates/v1_19">Visual Studio Code 1.19</a> were released this week, making this a big week for Electron based text editors.  If you use either of them, you’ll get to enjoy a nice set of performance improvements when you upgrade.</p>
<p><a href="https://blog.bear-writer.com/bear-1-4-the-tags-edition-298d6fdc55dd">Bear 1.4</a> - Speaking of software that I love to use getting updates, I’ve been using Bear as my primary notes app for the last year, and it is a delight.  Getting autocomplete on tags this week solved it’s last real annoyance for me, and I would definitely recommend it to anyone interested in a simple notes app.  It’s more powerful than Apple’s notes or text files, but cleaner and more elegant than <a href="https://evernote.com/">Evernote</a>.  And even the paid level is very affordable.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Ben McCormick</name>
            <email>ben@benmccormick.org</email>
            <uri>http://benmccormick.org</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Weekly Links: December 8th 2017]]></title>
        <id>https://benmccormick.org/2017/12/08/weekly-links-12-08-17/</id>
        <link href="https://benmccormick.org/2017/12/08/weekly-links-12-08-17/">
        </link>
        <updated>2017-12-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>JavaScript And The Web</h3>
<p><a href="https://reactjs.org/blog/2017/12/07/introducing-the-react-rfc-process.html">Introducing the React RFC Process | React Blog</a> - React is now using a public process for proposing and designing new features, starting with a new context API.</p>
<p><a href="https://blog.neufund.org/why-we-have-banned-default-exports-and-you-should-do-the-same-d51fdc2cf2ad">Why we have banned default exports in Javascript and you should do the same | Krzysztof Kaczor</a> - This lines up pretty well with my own experience when it comes to native JS modules.  The named exports are pretty much always better than the default ones.</p>
<p><a href="https://egghead.io/courses/advanced-react-component-patterns">Advanced React Component Patterns | Egghead.io/Kent C. Dobbs</a> - This is a new Egghead course on React Component patterns, and is the best “advanced” React resource I’ve seen.  If you’re a React developer, you should either watch it this weekend while it is still free, or pay up to Egghead (it will be behind their subscriber wall starting Monday).  He also released a <a href="https://egghead.io/courses/the-beginner-s-guide-to-reactjs">beginner level React course</a> this week that will remain free.</p>
<h3>Non-Tech</h3>
<p><a href="https://stratechery.com/2017/the-pollyannish-assumption/">The Pollyannish Assumption | Stratechery</a> - Ben Thompson gives a pretty good breakdown here of the problems companies face moderating Internet scale content.  Human beings capable of both greater heights and darker depths than we like to think.  </p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Ben McCormick</name>
            <email>ben@benmccormick.org</email>
            <uri>http://benmccormick.org</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Weekly Links: December 1st 2017]]></title>
        <id>https://benmccormick.org/2017/12/01/weekly-links-12-01-17/</id>
        <link href="https://benmccormick.org/2017/12/01/weekly-links-12-01-17/">
        </link>
        <updated>2017-12-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>JavaScript And The Web</h3>
<p><a href="http://2ality.com/2017/04/flatmap.html">Functional pattern: flatMap | 2ality</a> - This post isn’t new, but <code>flatmap</code> and <code>flatten</code> hit stage 3 in the TC39 process for adding new features to JavaScript this week<sup id="fnref-1"><a href="#fn-1" class="footnote-ref">1</a></sup>.  So this is a great time to read up on them.</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Stage 3 for Array.prototype.flatMap and Array.prototype.flatten! Thank you so much <a href="https://twitter.com/jspedant?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@jspedant</a> for driving this!<a href="https://t.co/9kLCKJcZEv">https://t.co/9kLCKJcZEv</a></p>&mdash; Brian Terlson (@bterlson) <a href="https://twitter.com/bterlson/status/935582351999901696?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">November 28, 2017</a></blockquote>
<p><a href="http://bholley.net/blog/2017/stylo.html">Boiling the Ocean, Incrementally - How Stylo Brought Rust and Servo to Firefox | Bobby Holley </a> - This is a great review of the technical achievement that Firefox 57 represents, and also gives some insight into where Mozilla is going from here. I’ve switched back to Firefox over the past 2 weeks and am pretty happy with it so far.</p>
<h3>Programming Tools and Practices</h3>
<p><a href="https://aws.amazon.com/blogs/aws/introducing-amazon-appsync/">Introducing AWS AppSync | AWS News Blog</a> - AWS announced a bunch of new services this week, but I wanted to highlight AppSync, an Amazon GraphQL service.  <a href="http://graphql.org/">GraphQL</a> seems to be gaining more and more momentum, and if you don’t know anything about it I’d suggest checking it out.  I’ve gotten to play with it since rewriting my blog to <a href="https://www.gatsbyjs.org/">Gatsby</a> 1.0, and it is a nice way to work with data.</p>
<h3>Non-Tech</h3>
<p><a href="https://www.seattletimes.com/business/amazon/this-city-hall-brought-to-you-by-amazon/">This City Hall, brought to you by Amazon | The Seattle Times</a> - I’m amazed by the incentives cities have been willing to offer Amazon to locate a headquarters in their city.  I think the outrage in this column is a bit over the top, but it is a startling insight into the power large tech companies have over the cities where they’re located.</p>
<p><a href="http://amzn.to/2i78Knm">Doomsday Clock - #1</a> - If you have any interest in comic books DC’s <a href="http://amzn.to/2i78Knm">Watchmen</a> sequel has begun.  It’s a story that crosses over with the mainstream DC Universe, and appears to be a rebuttal of the cynical vantage point of the original work.  This is the first of 12 issues over the next year and it was a strong (but slow start).  If you’re interested in Watchmen but don’t read a lot of comics, this is the continuation of a story that began with <a href="http://amzn.to/2jD0Y5c">a big DC special</a> and continued in a special <a href="http://amzn.to/2i5zSDn">Batman/Flash crossover</a></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn-1">
<p>See <a href="https://benmccormick.org/2017/07/10/how-to-follow-the-javascript-roadmap/">this post</a> for more info about staying informed about features that are being added to JavaScript.</p>
<a href="#fnref-1" class="footnote-backref">↩</a>
</li>
</ol>
</div>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Ben McCormick</name>
            <email>ben@benmccormick.org</email>
            <uri>http://benmccormick.org</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Implementing The Sieve Of Eratosthenes in JavaScript]]></title>
        <id>https://benmccormick.org/2017/11/28/sieveoferatosthenes/</id>
        <link href="https://benmccormick.org/2017/11/28/sieveoferatosthenes/">
        </link>
        <updated>2017-11-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As a way of keeping my math skills sharp, I’ve recently started to work through the <a href="https://projecteuler.net/">Project Euler</a> set of computational math problems.  They ask you not to post your work publicly, so I won’t be posting about any of my specific solutions, but I did think it would be fun to share about a helper method I’ve been using.</p>
<p>For several of the Project Euler problems I’ve worked on, I needed to be able to generate a list of prime numbers.  To do that, I borrowed a Python implementation of the Sieve Of Erathosthenes from <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/a/568618/1424361">this StackOverflow answer</a>.  Since I haven’t had much reason to use generators in JavaScript yet, I thought it would be fun to translate that algorithm to JavaScript and share that here.</p>
<h3>Sieve of Eratosthenes</h3>
<p>The Sieve of Erathosthenes is a very old<sup id="fnref-1"><a href="#fn-1" class="footnote-ref">1</a></sup> simple algorithm for identifying prime numbers.  In its normal implementation it is a useful way of finding small primes up to a certain number.  Beginning at 2, the algorithm iterates upward.  For the current number, if the number has not been marked, we identify it as a prime, and then mark all multiples of that number up to our target number.  So to find all primes up to 12, we would</p>
<ul>
<li>start at 2, note <strong>2</strong> as prime, and mark 4, 6, 8, 10 and 12 as non-prime</li>
<li>move to 3, note <strong>3</strong> as prime, and mark 6, 9, 12 as non-prime</li>
<li>move to 4, see that it is marked, and skip it</li>
<li>move to 5, note <strong>5</strong> as prime and mark 10 as non-prime</li>
<li>move to 6, see that it is marked and skip it</li>
<li>move to 7 , note <strong>7</strong> as prime</li>
<li>see that 8-10 are marked and skip them</li>
<li>move to 11, note <strong>11</strong> as prime</li>
<li>move to 12, see that it is marked and skip it</li>
</ul>
<p>You can see it graphically with this visualization from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sieve_of_Eratosthenes">Wikipedia</a>:</p>
<p><img src="/6420e3488e509dce176a1e957ea07ff5.gif" alt="sieve animation, shows the numbers being marked visually"></p>
<h3>Python Implementation</h3>
<p>The Python implementation that I used makes some modifications to the classic version of the algorithm that lets it generate an indefinite number of primes while being memory efficient</p>
<div class="gatsby-highlight">
      <pre class="language-python"><code><span class="token keyword">def</span> <span class="token function">gen_primes</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">:</span>
    <span class="token triple-quoted-string string">""" Generate an infinite sequence of prime numbers."""</span>
    marked_not_prime <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span><span class="token punctuation">}</span>
    value_to_check <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token number">2</span>
    <span class="token keyword">while</span> <span class="token boolean">True</span><span class="token punctuation">:</span>
        <span class="token keyword">if</span> value_to_check <span class="token operator">not</span> <span class="token keyword">in</span> marked_not_prime<span class="token punctuation">:</span>
            <span class="token keyword">yield</span> value_to_check
            marked_not_prime<span class="token punctuation">[</span>value_to_check <span class="token operator">*</span> value_to_check<span class="token punctuation">]</span> <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token punctuation">[</span>value_to_check<span class="token punctuation">]</span>
        <span class="token keyword">else</span><span class="token punctuation">:</span>
            <span class="token keyword">for</span> prime <span class="token keyword">in</span> marked_not_prime<span class="token punctuation">[</span>value_to_check<span class="token punctuation">]</span><span class="token punctuation">:</span>
                marked_not_prime<span class="token punctuation">.</span>setdefault<span class="token punctuation">(</span>prime <span class="token operator">+</span> value_to_check<span class="token punctuation">,</span> <span class="token punctuation">[</span><span class="token punctuation">]</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">.</span>append<span class="token punctuation">(</span>prime<span class="token punctuation">)</span>
            <span class="token keyword">del</span> marked_not_prime<span class="token punctuation">[</span>value_to_check<span class="token punctuation">]</span>
        value_to_check <span class="token operator">+=</span> <span class="token number">1</span>
</code></pre>
      </div>
<p>This version of the algorithm keeps a running set of the relevant matches, and keeps only the ones it needs.  We can translate it more or less directly to JavaScript like this:</p>
<div class="gatsby-highlight">
      <pre class="language-javascript"><code><span class="token keyword">function</span><span class="token operator">*</span> <span class="token function">generatePrimes</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
    <span class="token keyword">const</span> markedNotPrime <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span><span class="token punctuation">}</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
    <span class="token keyword">let</span> valueToCheck <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token number">2</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
    <span class="token keyword">while</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token boolean">true</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
        <span class="token keyword">if</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token operator">!</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>valueToCheck <span class="token keyword">in</span> markedNotPrime<span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
            <span class="token keyword">yield</span> valueToCheck
            markedNotPrime<span class="token punctuation">[</span>valueToCheck<span class="token operator">**</span><span class="token number">2</span><span class="token punctuation">]</span> <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token punctuation">[</span>valueToCheck<span class="token punctuation">]</span>
        <span class="token punctuation">}</span> <span class="token keyword">else</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
            <span class="token keyword">let</span> primes <span class="token operator">=</span>markedNotPrime<span class="token punctuation">[</span>valueToCheck<span class="token punctuation">]</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
            primes<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">forEach</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>prime<span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token operator">></span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
                <span class="token keyword">let</span> nextMultipleOfPrime <span class="token operator">=</span> prime <span class="token operator">+</span> valueToCheck<span class="token punctuation">;</span>
                <span class="token keyword">if</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span>nextMultipleOfPrime <span class="token keyword">in</span> markedNotPrime<span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
                    markedNotPrime<span class="token punctuation">[</span>nextMultipleOfPrime<span class="token punctuation">]</span><span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">push</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>prime<span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
                <span class="token punctuation">}</span> <span class="token keyword">else</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
                    markedNotPrime<span class="token punctuation">[</span>nextMultipleOfPrime<span class="token punctuation">]</span> <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token punctuation">[</span>prime<span class="token punctuation">]</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
                <span class="token punctuation">}</span>
            <span class="token punctuation">}</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span>
            <span class="token keyword">delete</span> markedNotPrime<span class="token punctuation">[</span>valueToCheck<span class="token punctuation">]</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
        <span class="token punctuation">}</span>
        valueToCheck <span class="token operator">+</span><span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token number">1</span>
    <span class="token punctuation">}</span>
<span class="token punctuation">}</span>
</code></pre>
      </div>
<p>Let’s break down what this is doing.</p>
<div class="gatsby-highlight">
      <pre class="language-javascript"><code><span class="token keyword">function</span><span class="token operator">*</span> <span class="token function">generatePrimes</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
  <span class="token comment" spellcheck="true">//...</span>
<span class="token punctuation">}</span>
</code></pre>
      </div>
<p><code>generatePrimes</code> is a JavaScript <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/JavaScript/Reference/Global_Objects/Generator">generator</a>.  Generators “generate” a series of values in a “just in time” fashion; they only calculate the next value when it is needed, making them an efficient solution for working with large or infinite series.  You specify a generator function by adding the <code>*</code> to the function declaration.  Generators then use the <code>yield</code> keyword rather than <code>return</code> to return their values, and can <code>yield</code> multiple times. After a generator yields, it pauses execution until it is asked for another value.  For our <code>generatePrimes</code> function, we are operating inside an infinite loop and will yield continuously without stopping<sup id="fnref-2"><a href="#fn-2" class="footnote-ref">2</a></sup>.</p>
<div class="gatsby-highlight">
      <pre class="language-javascript"><code><span class="token keyword">const</span> markedNotPrime <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span><span class="token punctuation">}</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
<span class="token keyword">let</span> valueToCheck <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token number">2</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
<span class="token keyword">while</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token boolean">true</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
    <span class="token comment" spellcheck="true">//...</span>
    valueToCheck <span class="token operator">+</span><span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token number">1</span>
<span class="token punctuation">}</span>
</code></pre>
      </div>
<p>We’re using a plain object to keep track of our marked numbers, and using <code>valueToCheck</code> to keep track of where we are in iterating through numbers. As noted, we will iterate it forever if the generator continues to be called.</p>
<div class="gatsby-highlight">
      <pre class="language-javascript"><code><span class="token keyword">if</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token operator">!</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>valueToCheck <span class="token keyword">in</span> markedNotPrime<span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
    <span class="token keyword">yield</span> valueToCheck
    markedNotPrime<span class="token punctuation">[</span>valueToCheck<span class="token operator">**</span><span class="token number">2</span><span class="token punctuation">]</span> <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token punctuation">[</span>valueToCheck<span class="token punctuation">]</span>
<span class="token punctuation">}</span> <span class="token keyword">else</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
  <span class="token comment" spellcheck="true">//...</span>
<span class="token punctuation">}</span>
</code></pre>
      </div>
<p>As in the original algorithm, if we get to a number that isn’t marked, we know that it is a prime.  So we <code>yield</code> it, which pauses execution.  If the generator is queried again, when we resume execution we mark the prime squared as not-prime, and we do that by assigning it an array with the current prime value in it.  Using arrays for markers will make more sense in a moment. For now its worth noting that we only need to mark prime-squared as non-prime since every multiple below that is the current prime multiplied by a number less than it, which means it will already be covered, as we will see below.</p>
<div class="gatsby-highlight">
      <pre class="language-javascript"><code><span class="token keyword">if</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token operator">!</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>valueToCheck <span class="token keyword">in</span> markedNotPrime<span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
  <span class="token comment" spellcheck="true">//...</span>
<span class="token punctuation">}</span> <span class="token keyword">else</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
    <span class="token keyword">let</span> primes <span class="token operator">=</span> markedNotPrime<span class="token punctuation">[</span>valueToCheck<span class="token punctuation">]</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
    primes<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">forEach</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>prime <span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token operator">></span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
        <span class="token keyword">let</span> nextMultipleOfPrime <span class="token operator">=</span> prime <span class="token operator">+</span> valueToCheck<span class="token punctuation">;</span>
        <span class="token keyword">if</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span>nextMultipleOfPrime <span class="token keyword">in</span> markedNotPrime<span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
            markedNotPrime<span class="token punctuation">[</span>nextMultipleOfPrime<span class="token punctuation">]</span><span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">push</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>prime<span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
        <span class="token punctuation">}</span> <span class="token keyword">else</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
            markedNotPrime<span class="token punctuation">[</span>nextMultipleOfPrime<span class="token punctuation">]</span> <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token punctuation">[</span>prime<span class="token punctuation">]</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
        <span class="token punctuation">}</span>
    <span class="token punctuation">}</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span>
    <span class="token keyword">delete</span> markedNotPrime<span class="token punctuation">[</span>valueToCheck<span class="token punctuation">]</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
<span class="token punctuation">}</span>
</code></pre>
      </div>
<p>Here’s the clever part of this implementation.  When we hit a number that is marked as not-prime, instead of just skipping it and moving on, we use some logic to keep our list of marked values small and memory efficient. This is also what allows us to get an infinite list of primes instead of settling for those under a particular value.  What we want to do is keep a list of all the primes that are factors of each marked number.  Then when we hit a number that is marked, we mark the next multiple for each prime (<code>valueToCheck + prime</code>), and remove the current value from the object.  That keeps checks fairly cheap by eliminating the number of marked numbers, and allows us to only add values to the marked list as we need them.</p>
<p>We can then use this code to get the 1,000,001st prime like this:</p>
<div class="gatsby-highlight">
      <pre class="language-javascript"><code><span class="token keyword">let</span> gen <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token function">generatePrimes</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
<span class="token keyword">for</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token keyword">var</span> i<span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token number">0</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span> i<span class="token operator">&lt;</span> <span class="token number">1000000</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span> i <span class="token operator">++</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
    gen<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">next</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span>
<span class="token punctuation">}</span>
console<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">log</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>gen<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">next</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">.</span>value<span class="token punctuation">)</span>
</code></pre>
      </div>
<p>That executed on my laptop in ~20seconds, approximately the same as the python implementation in python2, a little slower than running it under python3.  I was curious whether using a <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/JavaScript/Reference/Global_Objects/Map">Map</a> for our marked prime list would speed things up:</p>
<div class="gatsby-highlight">
      <pre class="language-javascript"><code><span class="token keyword">function</span><span class="token operator">*</span> <span class="token function">generatePrimes</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
    <span class="token keyword">const</span> markedNotPrimeMap <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token keyword">new</span> <span class="token class-name">Map</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
    <span class="token keyword">let</span> valueToCheck <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token number">2</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
    <span class="token keyword">while</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token boolean">true</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
        <span class="token keyword">if</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token operator">!</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>markedNotPrimeMap<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">has</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>valueToCheck<span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
            <span class="token keyword">yield</span> valueToCheck
            markedNotPrimeMap<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token keyword">set</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>valueToCheck<span class="token operator">**</span><span class="token number">2</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span> <span class="token punctuation">[</span>valueToCheck<span class="token punctuation">]</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span>
        <span class="token punctuation">}</span> <span class="token keyword">else</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
            <span class="token keyword">let</span> primes <span class="token operator">=</span>markedNotPrimeMap<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token keyword">get</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>valueToCheck<span class="token punctuation">)</span>
            primes<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">forEach</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>prime<span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token operator">></span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
                <span class="token keyword">let</span> nextMultipleOfPrime <span class="token operator">=</span> prime <span class="token operator">+</span> valueToCheck<span class="token punctuation">;</span>
                <span class="token keyword">if</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span>markedNotPrimeMap<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">has</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>nextMultipleOfPrime<span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
                    markedNotPrimeMap<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token keyword">get</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>nextMultipleOfPrime<span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">push</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>prime<span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
                <span class="token punctuation">}</span> <span class="token keyword">else</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
                    markedNotPrimeMap<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token keyword">set</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>nextMultipleOfPrime<span class="token punctuation">,</span> <span class="token punctuation">[</span>prime<span class="token punctuation">]</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
                <span class="token punctuation">}</span>
            <span class="token punctuation">}</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span>
            markedNotPrimeMap<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token keyword">delete</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>valueToCheck<span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
        <span class="token punctuation">}</span>
        valueToCheck <span class="token operator">+</span><span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token number">1</span>
    <span class="token punctuation">}</span>
<span class="token punctuation">}</span>
</code></pre>
      </div>
<p>This version of the code runs about 25% faster, in 15 seconds on my machine. Not bad.</p>
<h3>More Resources</h3>
<ul>
<li>You can dig in more on the Sieve of Erosthenes on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sieve_of_Eratosthenes">Wikipedia</a></li>
<li>Check out <a href="https://projecteuler.net/">Project Euler</a> for some fun computational math problems.</li>
</ul>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn-1">
<p>There are references as old as ~100 AD</p>
<a href="#fnref-1" class="footnote-backref">↩</a>
</li>
<li id="fn-2">
<p>At least until we hit system boundaries for memory/number size/etc.</p>
<a href="#fnref-2" class="footnote-backref">↩</a>
</li>
</ol>
</div>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Ben McCormick</name>
            <email>ben@benmccormick.org</email>
            <uri>http://benmccormick.org</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Weekly Links: Thanksgiving 2017 edition]]></title>
        <id>https://benmccormick.org/2017/11/26/weekly-links-11-26-17/</id>
        <link href="https://benmccormick.org/2017/11/26/weekly-links-11-26-17/">
        </link>
        <updated>2017-11-26T00:00:00Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In honor of Thanksgiving this week, instead of a list of writing from around the web, this week I’ll be linking to some of my favorite lesser known software tools, apps and gear.  These are things that let me get things done, and I’m thankful for that.</p>
<h3>JavaScript Libraries</h3>
<p><a href="https://www.gatsbyjs.org/">Gatsby</a> - I’ve written and spoken about Gatsby before, but it keeps getting better as a tool for building React-based web sites and applications.  This blog is written using it.</p>
<p><a href="https://date-fns.org/">date-fns</a> - date-fns is a nice modular lightweight alternative to <a href="https://momentjs.com/">moment.js</a> for date management in JavaScript.  Because JavaScript’s built in dates are weird and hard to work with, and not everybody needs all of the goodness moment provides.</p>
<p><a href="https://mobx.js.org/">MobX</a> - It’s been overshadowed by Redux, but MobX is a fantastic state management library for JavaScript libraries.  Since its an object oriented model that can be used in a variety of ways, it is easier to pull in incrementally</p>
<p><a href="https://glamorous.rocks/">glamorous</a> - My favorite CSS-in-JS library for React, it lets you write styles in a few different ways, which allows you to manage things in a very React-y way, without ever getting stuck with things you can’t do.</p>
<h3>Apps</h3>
<p><a href="https://flexibits.com/fantastical">Fantastical</a> - The best app I’ve ever used for OSX and iPhone</p>
<p><a href="https://mailplaneapp.com/">Mailplane</a> - If you like GMail’s web app (obviously not to everyone’s taste) Mailplane is a great way to use it as a native app on OSX.  I like it because it allows me to use both of my Gmail accounts side by side with their own notification settings and no risk of being lost in a sea of browser tabs.</p>
<h3>Gear</h3>
<p><a href="http://www.rickshawbags.com/commuter-laptop-bag">Rickshaw Bagworks Commuter Bag</a> - I’ve had the 2.0 version of this bag for the past 4 years, and it has been an amazingly versatile and durable tool for transporting my laptops, notebooks and more.  Highly recommended.</p>
<p><a href="https://store.google.com/product/chromecast_2015">Chromecast</a> - I have a Chromecast and a Chromecast audio, and they’re an amazing cheap way to turn TVs and speakers into “Smart devices” that you can control from your phone without having to pay for “smart devices” that probably won’t be kept up to date the way you’d want.</p>
<p><a href="http://amzn.to/2zpBZcm">Backbeat Fit</a> - I’ve now ended up buying 4 pairs of these headphones for myself and others.  They’re fantastic versatile headphones that work great for exercise headphones but are good enough quality to use for other purposes.  I personally have trouble with ear-buds (they don’t stay in my ears), so the over-ear style of the fit is perfect for me.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Ben McCormick</name>
            <email>ben@benmccormick.org</email>
            <uri>http://benmccormick.org</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
</feed>