<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>http://benmccormick.org</id>
    <title>benmccormick.org</title>
    <updated>2019-12-19T01:25:43Z</updated>
    <generator>Feed for Node.js</generator>
    <author>
        <name>Ben McCormick</name>
        <email>ben@benmccormick.org</email>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://benmccormick.org"/>
    <link rel="self" href="http://benmccormick.org/atom.xml"/>
    <subtitle>A blog by Ben McCormick</subtitle>
    <logo>https://benmccormick.org/logo.png</logo>
    <icon>https://benmccormick.org/favicon.ico</icon>
    <rights>All rights reserved 2016, Ben McCormick</rights>
    <contributor>
        <name>Ben McCormick</name>
        <email>ben@benmccormick.org</email>
        <uri>http://benmccormick.org</uri>
    </contributor>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[How Software Engineers Produce Value]]></title>
        <id>https://benmccormick.orghow-se-add-value</id>
        <link href="https://benmccormick.orghow-se-add-value">
        </link>
        <updated>2019-12-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I had the opportunity this week to walk a software engineer who is new to the field through some lessons I’ve learned over the years about how software engineers add value to the business.  It seemed generally applicable, so here’s a cleaned up version of what I shared.</p>
<hr>
<h2>What Is Value?</h2>
<p>It can be easy to think of software engineering work as a series of task where you’re given instructions and you make the computer do what the designer / PM / CEO asked.  Or as a series of fun problem solving challenges that you’re somehow getting paid to complete.  Both of those views will eventually lead you to make suboptimal decisions when it comes to helping your business and growing in your role though.  Instead consider the following definition:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Software Developers create value through shipping working code that solves important user problems in a predictable manner.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This captures a number of important things.</p>
<h3>Shipping</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>Real Artists Ship - <em>Steve Jobs</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Software Engineer’s super power compared to other roles is that we get to build.  We create new things, add new behaviors, and ultimately (for a product company) control the shape of the product our company is built around.  This only has value when software actually ships though.  When we’re not shipping, it’s actually worse than just being slow to deliver value, because of a few non-obvious factors.</p>
<p>First, <strong>unshipped code rots.</strong>  When we leave code in a branch 90% done, it doesn’t just stay the same.  It’s quite common for our situation to get worse.  Our teammates check in code that may cause merge conflicts, or worse just doesn’t take into account the unshipped code and sets us up for subtle bugs.  And when we do get back to the work we’ve often lost valuable mental context that makes any remaining work or testing harder and more error-prone.</p>
<p>Second, <strong>we learn from shipping!</strong>  It’s quite common in software development for a developer or team to complete 90% of their feature according to the spec, only to find that they have another 90% of the work to go.  Doing the work to push things through to production inherently de-risks things, because we learn what the challenges are, and we know how long the work took.  Up until then, we will always have unknowns.  And when software goes out to users, we get to hear their feedback as well.  Shipped software lets us learn from our users (and from the performance of our system) and make adjustments that we wouldn’t have known about if we sat on the code.  </p>
<p>So how do we get to shipping?  First, it’s important to push things through to completion rather than allowing ourselves to jump from project to project, making progress without finishing, and incurring a lot of cost from context switching.  Soemtimes this may mean imposing kanban style <a href="https://lethain.com/limiting-wip/">work in progress limits</a> on ourselves.  Second, its often helpful to break things into smaller chunks.  Small code reviews are easier to complete, test, <a href="https://benmccormick.org/2019/04/22/better-code-feedback">review</a> and verify.  So multiple small changes will often go through faster than the same changes bundled together into a big chunk.  This can go too far, but as long as your changes work in isolation and provide value, I’d encourage erring on this side when in doubt.</p>
<h3>Working Code</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>[We Prefer] working software over comprehensive documentation - <em>The Agile Manifesto</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Software engineers are responsible for their code working.  At the simplest level that means delivering code that doesn’t crash when run in the intended way.  As we grow and mature as developers however, we should aspire to  learn to write code that will scale to any reasonable load the system might see (and maybe even to unreasonable loads), code that handles odd input or context gracefully, and code that is easy to modify and maintain.  We should also take responsibility for proving that it works; writing tests, making the code easy to monitor in production, and providing good logging for debugging all fall under a software engineer’s domain. We also should make sure that our definition of working matches what the business needs, not just a pedantic reading of whatever spec we’re working off of.  More on that in a moment.</p>
<h3>Solving Important User Problems</h3>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Just really funny- What the Customer Wanted expanded <a href="https://t.co/kdr7HKTSDy">pic.twitter.com/kdr7HKTSDy</a></p>&mdash; Frank Spillers (@farreaching) <a href="https://twitter.com/farreaching/status/764256002053025792?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">August 13, 2016</a></blockquote>
<p>Software Engineers can be quite inventive in the ways they write code without solving important user problems.  Some common routes:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Working on their own pet projects over the prioritized business problems</strong> - Tech improvement work and engineer-driven projects are part of a healthy organization, but if they consistently replace work that was scoped based on user requests / feedback, they can cause problems</li>
<li><strong>Matching the spec without solving the original problem</strong> - This is partially a design/product problem, but its often possible to meet all the stated requirements for a project without solving the original user pain point.  Great engineers understand exactly what problem they’re trying to solve with a feature and will always step back to evaluate whether they’re succeeding throughout the development process.</li>
<li><strong>Matching the spec and causing new problems</strong> - Oftentimes our efforts to fix cause or expose new problems.  When we dodge responsibility by ignoring or hiding those problems instead of openly evaluating tradeoffs or working to improve the solution, we’re not providing all the value we’re capable of. </li>
</ol>
<p>These are ultimately issues of ownership. When we’re invested in our work, we will want to work on useful problems and make sure they produce real value.  If you’re consistently not feeling that way, it may be time to find something else to work on.</p>
<h3>In a predictable manner</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>The challenge and the mission are to find real solutions to real problems on actual schedules with available resources - <em>Fred Brooks</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Ok, now we come to the section that is the <em>boring part</em> for many software engineers.  But as somebody who has recently converted to the management side of the fence, the ability to ship predictably is incredibly important.  </p>
<p>It’s important for software engineers to ship predictably in 2 senses:</p>
<ol>
<li>There is ongoing understanding of when something is likely to ship among the people who need to know</li>
<li>There is ongoing understanding of how something will work when it will ship among the people who need to know.  </li>
</ol>
<p>Estimating software engineering projects is not an exact science. Nobody reasonable expects estimation perfection from software engineers, especially those new to the field.  Instead we aim to be as accurate as possible, and especially to be transparent as those estimates change over time.  </p>
<p>When we encounter obstacles, it’s important to be realistic about what they mean to schedules and update the important people in a timely manner. </p>
<p>For those working on a product team that may be a manager and a PM, for those building something solo, that may be the customers or internal users of the software directly.  It’s never fun to say something is going to be late, but its always better to say that we’ll miss a date that is 2 weeks away than to tell somebody for the first time that you’ve missed the date that was 2 days ago.</p>
<p>Communicating about the scope of work is just as important as schedule.  If we find out a piece of a feature is unfeasable or we dropped it due to time pressure, its important to communicate that.  Depending on your team/product, that may mean sharing with people directly, updating documentation, or just making the new behavior clear in an interface.   </p>
<h3>It’s a process</h3>
<p>Nobody starts out their first software engineering job with a fully evolved sense of how to estimate, scope and document their work.  Most have no clue how to think about building a system to be scalable or when to escalate problems to other members of the team.  These are skills learned through hard experience.  Make sure to <a href="https://benmccormick.org/2019/05/18/obvious-things">always be reflecting</a> on what you’re experiencing though.  Experience combined with reflection is a powerful mixture, and eventually will lead to growth.  Good luck!</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Ben McCormick</name>
            <email>ben@benmccormick.org</email>
            <uri>http://benmccormick.org</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Review: Resilient Management]]></title>
        <id>https://benmccormick.org/2019/07/22/book-review-resilient-management</id>
        <link href="https://benmccormick.org/2019/07/22/book-review-resilient-management">
        </link>
        <updated>2019-07-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://abookapart.com/products/resilient-management">Resilient Management</a> by Lara Hogan is a short and useful read for engineering managers who want to think more systematically about how they support their team.  Lara covers concepts like how to connect with a new team, how to encourage growth in your teammates, and how to communicate difficult news.  This is a <em>blog+</em> book: most of the material here has appeared previously in Lara’s blog or newsletter, but for the book it has been cleaned up and organized together in a coherent fashion that makes it greater than the sum of its parts.</p>
<p>If you’ve followed my <a href="https://benmccormick.org/subscribe">newsletter</a> for a while, you’ll have seen me link to Lara’s work on a regular basis.  Lara’s strength as a teacher is building meaningful exercises for thinking through abstract topics, and that plays out here.  Almost every piece of advice and insight comes with a suggestion on how to start implementing it, or an exercise to help you think deeper about yourself or your situation.  I’ve found her <a href="https://larahogan.me/blog/leadership-style-colors/">leadership colors</a> and her <a href="https://larahogan.me/blog/team-introspection/">MadLibs worksheet for leadership philosophy</a> particularly helpful for me.</p>
<p>In addition to the helpful exercises, the highlights of the book for me were Lara’s look at the BICEPS model for understanding people’s needs at work, the way she structured her book around a groups evolution over time, and the chapter on communication plans.  I’ve made notes to reference each of those areas the next time I hit a relevant situation.</p>
<p>Overall I’d recommend this book to pretty much any early-career engineering manager.  If you’re not already familiar with Lara’s work, there should be some fantastic new ideas for you in here.  If you have followed it, I recommend buying out of appreciation, and to get the concepts bundled in a nice cleanly organized packages.  These are ideas worth paying for.</p>
<p>Resilient Management is available from <a href="https://abookapart.com/products/resilient-management">A Book Apart</a></p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Ben McCormick</name>
            <email>ben@benmccormick.org</email>
            <uri>http://benmccormick.org</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Avoiding Derived State In React]]></title>
        <id>https://benmccormick.org/2019/06/24/derived-state</id>
        <link href="https://benmccormick.org/2019/06/24/derived-state">
        </link>
        <updated>2019-06-24T00:00:00Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A lot of advice in the React community is focused around avoiding explicitly storing “derived state” of some type or another.  Some examples of this type of “derived state” that the community warns against:</p>
<h4>Storing data that is directly derived from another piece of data in redux</h4>
<div class="gatsby-highlight" data-language="javascript"><pre class="language-javascript"><code class="language-javascript"><span class="token keyword">const</span> reducer <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token function">createReducer</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>initialState<span class="token punctuation">,</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
  <span class="token function-variable function">ADD_USER</span><span class="token punctuation">:</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token parameter">state<span class="token punctuation">,</span> action</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token operator">=></span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
    state<span class="token punctuation">.</span>users <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token punctuation">[</span><span class="token operator">...</span>state<span class="token punctuation">.</span>users<span class="token punctuation">,</span> action<span class="token punctuation">.</span>user<span class="token punctuation">]</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
    <span class="token comment">// numUsers is derived state: it will always be tied to users</span>
    state<span class="token punctuation">.</span>numUsers <span class="token operator">=</span> state<span class="token punctuation">.</span>users<span class="token punctuation">.</span>length<span class="token punctuation">;</span>
  <span class="token punctuation">}</span>
<span class="token punctuation">}</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span></code></pre></div>
<h4>Storing state that is directly derived from a prop in a component</h4>
<div class="gatsby-highlight" data-language="javascript"><pre class="language-javascript"><code class="language-javascript"><span class="token keyword">const</span> <span class="token function-variable function">Widget</span> <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token parameter">props</span> <span class="token operator">=></span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
    <span class="token comment">// the hasError state is derived from the error prop</span>
    <span class="token keyword">let</span> <span class="token punctuation">[</span>hasError<span class="token punctuation">]</span> <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token function">useState</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token operator">!</span><span class="token operator">!</span>props<span class="token punctuation">.</span>error<span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
    <span class="token comment">//... continued ...</span>
<span class="token punctuation">}</span></code></pre></div>
<h4>Storing state that is directly derived from another piece of state</h4>
<div class="gatsby-highlight" data-language="javascript"><pre class="language-javascript"><code class="language-javascript"><span class="token keyword">class</span> <span class="token class-name">NameForm</span> <span class="token keyword">extends</span> <span class="token class-name">React<span class="token punctuation">.</span>Component</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
    <span class="token function">constructor</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token parameter">props</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
        <span class="token keyword">super</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>props<span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
        <span class="token keyword">this</span><span class="token punctuation">.</span>state <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
            firstName<span class="token punctuation">:</span> <span class="token string">''</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span>
            lastName<span class="token punctuation">:</span> <span class="token string">''</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span>
            fullName<span class="token punctuation">:</span> <span class="token string">''</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span>
        <span class="token punctuation">}</span>
    <span class="token punctuation">}</span>
    <span class="token comment">// because fullName is directly associated with firstName and lastName, we have to update it</span>
    <span class="token comment">// any time they are updated</span>
    <span class="token function">updateFirstName</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token parameter">newFirstName</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
        <span class="token keyword">this</span><span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">setState</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token parameter">state</span> <span class="token operator">=></span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">{</span>
            <span class="token operator">...</span>state<span class="token punctuation">,</span>
            firstName<span class="token punctuation">:</span> newFirstName<span class="token punctuation">,</span>
            fullName<span class="token punctuation">:</span> newFirstName <span class="token operator">+</span> <span class="token string">' '</span> <span class="token operator">+</span> state<span class="token punctuation">.</span>lastName<span class="token punctuation">,</span>
        <span class="token punctuation">}</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span>
    <span class="token punctuation">}</span>
    <span class="token function">updateLastName</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token parameter">newLastName</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
        <span class="token keyword">this</span><span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">setState</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token parameter">state</span> <span class="token operator">=></span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">{</span>
            <span class="token operator">...</span>state<span class="token punctuation">,</span>
            lastName<span class="token punctuation">:</span> newLastName<span class="token punctuation">,</span>
            fullName<span class="token punctuation">:</span> state<span class="token punctuation">.</span>firstName <span class="token operator">+</span> <span class="token string">' '</span> <span class="token operator">+</span> newLastName<span class="token punctuation">,</span>
        <span class="token punctuation">}</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span>
    <span class="token punctuation">}</span>
    <span class="token comment">// ... continued ....</span>
<span class="token punctuation">}</span></code></pre></div>
<p>These examples are all based on real-world code I’ve seen.  And they all were in code that <em>worked</em>, the program executed as expected.  But they’re still problematic.  This type of derived state is error-prone; when new code is written to update the state, each new programmer touching the code has to understand the relationship, or the whole thing can get out of sync.  When state is coming from props, like the error example above, you have to make sure that the state gets updated properly when the props change. And when the state gets out of sync, it is possible to end up in strange states where a programmer’s expectations are violated.  A program shows a blank state saying no users have been added, even though one has already been created. A form is expecting to have an error, but the error text is empty or set to a default value.  Or a site has 2 different names for an individual that show up differently in separate parts of the interface.</p>
<p>This type of problem isn’t a new thing in Computer Science.  When programmers do it by accident they usually call it a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Don%27t_repeat_yourself">DRY violation</a>.  When they do it intentionally they call it caching.  And when they do it intentionally but screw things up, they <a href="https://twitter.com/secretGeek/status/7269997868">make jokes about off by one errors</a>.  Fortunately, that means that the tradeoffs are pretty well understood here.  So how do we handle situations where it looks like derived state may be necessary?</p>
<h4>Just Derive State At Render Time</h4>
<p>For many many things, including the 3 examples above, if you need information at render time that can be derived from other pieces of state, it’s totally fine to just calculate it at render time.  For the first name example above, you can just include a <code class="language-text">let fullName = this.state.firstName + &#39; &#39; + this.state.lastName;</code> line at the top of your render function and move on<sup id="fnref-1"><a href="#fn-1" class="footnote-ref">1</a></sup>. Storing derived information is unnecessary and harmful when calculating it at runtime adds minimal performance overhead or repetition.</p>
<h4>Memoization</h4>
<p>But Ben, my component is slow now!</p>
<p>…are you sure it’s actually slow?  Have you tested it?  Have you proven that the derived state calculation is actually a meaningful part of this?</p>
<p>Deriving state can be slow when you have to do complicated calculations or reformatting of data.  This is still not usually a problem, but if you’re in a performance sensitive area of code and have proven it to be a problem, you can start considering caching solutions. You still don’t want to store your cached values in state or your redux stores though.  Instead, you want to use a computed value that is recalculated when its inputs change.  The exact code will depend on your state management strategy, but some examples out there include</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/reduxjs/reselect">Reselect for Redux</a></li>
<li><a href="https://mobx.js.org/refguide/computed-decorator.html">Computeds in MobX</a></li>
<li><a href="https://reactjs.org/docs/hooks-reference.html#usememo">useMemo in React Components</a></li>
</ul>
<p>All of these methods use <em>memoization</em>, a type of caching where arguments are passed to a function, and if the function has been called with those arguments before, it returns the previous result rather than recomputing.  If for instance we had a component and wanted to get the names of all <code class="language-text">users</code> with the current <code class="language-text">type</code> based on props, and we knew that <code class="language-text">users</code> was sometimes quite large, making the calculations slow, and we expected the component to re-render often for some reason or another we might write code like this:</p>
<div class="gatsby-highlight" data-language="javascript"><pre class="language-javascript"><code class="language-javascript"><span class="token keyword">const</span> <span class="token function-variable function">UsersList</span> <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token parameter"><span class="token punctuation">{</span>users<span class="token punctuation">,</span> type<span class="token punctuation">,</span><span class="token punctuation">}</span></span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token operator">=></span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>

    <span class="token keyword">let</span> userNames <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token function">useMemo</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token operator">=></span> users<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">map</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token parameter">user</span> <span class="token operator">=></span> user<span class="token punctuation">.</span>type <span class="token operator">===</span> type<span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span> <span class="token punctuation">[</span>users<span class="token punctuation">,</span> type<span class="token punctuation">]</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
    <span class="token comment">// ... continued ...</span>
<span class="token punctuation">}</span></code></pre></div>
<p>Now userNames will automatically be recalculated only when users or type changes<sup id="fnref-2"><a href="#fn-2" class="footnote-ref">2</a></sup>.  The MobX and Redux solutions work similarly.  Memoization isn’t a performance silver bullet: at some point, you might have to look at how you can make your calculations less expensive or take them off of the rendering path completely.  But for most simple data transformation tasks, deriving state at render time and using memoization to keep it performant where needed should help you tame any derived state problems you encounter.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn-1">
<p>But you should probably read about all the ways that <a href="https://www.kalzumeus.com/2010/06/17/falsehoods-programmers-believe-about-names/">names can be more complicated than you think</a></p>
<a href="#fnref-1" class="footnote-backref">↩</a>
</li>
<li id="fn-2">
<p>Note that useMemo (and most memoization solutions generally) doesn’t guarantee the function will never run more than once.  Most solutions have a limited number of results they will store, so if the inputs change often, the result might get recalculated.</p>
<a href="#fnref-2" class="footnote-backref">↩</a>
</li>
</ol>
</div>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Ben McCormick</name>
            <email>ben@benmccormick.org</email>
            <uri>http://benmccormick.org</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lessons From Managing A Distributed Team]]></title>
        <id>https://benmccormick.org/2019/06/24/managing-a-distributed-team</id>
        <link href="https://benmccormick.org/2019/06/24/managing-a-distributed-team">
        </link>
        <updated>2019-06-17T00:00:00Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Working with people over the internet is different from meeting in an office five days a week.  This isn’t a moral statement.  I’ve done and enjoyed both.  Working with a distributed team requires a different set of skills, especially when you’re a leader.  Today I want to share the most helpful lessons I’ve learned over the last year managing a distributed team.</p>
<h4>Evaluate process and outcomes, not inputs</h4>
<p>Focusing on output` is great advice for any team, but it’s easier and more important when managing remote teams.  When you’re not in the office with people, you won’t see when they start in the morning or finish at night.  You won’t be able to tell if they’re taking long coffee breaks or checking Amazon between tasks.  You’ll have to evaluate them on their output and on the methods they use to get work done.</p>
<p>Evaluating on outputs is tricky for tech work in the short term.  It’s often hard to tell how hard a specific task should have been.  But over the long run, you’ll need to find ways to see if developers are meeting their goals, and focus on that over the exact times they did work.  And this is good, because that is actually what matters.</p>
<p>Output is a lagging indicator though.  In the short term, what you can evaluate if “butts in seats” isn’t an option.  I recommend process: is work being documented, are tests being written and are code reviews being done in a timely manner?  The nice thing about this is that you can check these things in low touch ways; by reviewing your issue tracking and version control systems rather than having status meetings or sending distracting slack messages.  This idea comes up in <a href="https://amzn.to/2XBg1iv">Camille Fournier’s book The Manager’s Path</a>, where she argues persuasively for always doing your information gathering in ways that don’t disrupt your team first.</p>
<h4>1-1s are extra important</h4>
<p>Let’s say Sarah has some lingering concerns about her current project that she’s not yet ready to raise to the full group.  When I work in the same office with Sarah, she can drop by my desk anytime to talk through a small issue.  When we’re working remotely, that may not feel as comfortable for a variety of reasons.  Good 1-1s provide space for the little things to come out.</p>
<h4>When you get in-person time, focus on the relationship</h4>
<p>Currently I get together with my team (and my manager) about once a quarter.  Initially my instinct was to save the “big work stuff” for that time.  And I still try to get a few big conversations in each time, mostly around career development.  But the most value from these visits has come in the gaps, when I go out to lunch with my team and chat, or we get together with a larger group after work.  Time spent together builds trust, and that trust lingers and pays off when you’re back on the other side of the internet the next week.</p>
<h4>Async communication is great.  Don’t neglect “face to face” time.</h4>
<p>“Embrace async communication” is common remote work advice.  When you get stuff done through email/slack/Github/Invision/etc you have fewer meetings and more flow time for your team.  Which is great!  My team takes advantage of “async” tools every day.  But I also try to be intentional about working in “face to face” time through Zoom.  For my team that’s a daily standup and weekly 1-1s, but it could be different for another team’s process.  The key is to not <em>only</em> rely on writing.  Writing is an amazing way to communicate, but it will always lack the context of the human face.  For now I’m aiming for a mix of mostly async with regular “internet face to face”, and occasional “in person”.</p>
<p>Make sure to personalize your communication as well.  If Jerry tends to miss all nuance when you communicate in text, try to spend more time talking over zoom to make sure you’re communicating.  On the other hand if Jennifer has a tendency to lose track of what you’re asking her to do, you may want to give instructions through a text medium, where you can use it for accountability later.</p>
<h4>Hire for remote success</h4>
<p>Not everyone is going to thrive in a remote role.  Most companies hiring remote recognize this and try to filter for it in some form. A lot of companies’ response here is to “only hire senior”.  Which is probably a workable heuristic in some ways.  Developers that have a proven track record of success probably have built up some habits that will help them succeed in remote work even if they aren’t naturally inclined to it.  But hiring only senior folks is expensive, and makes things like diversity and career growth paths harder.</p>
<p>I haven’t done this enough to draw any hard conclusions on remote hiring yet.  But the qualities I want to evaluate for are independence, technological comfort, writing skills, and a history of taking the initiative to seize opportunities (in whatever domain).  Obviously that’s in addition to normal hiring criteria.</p>
<h4>Tools and Process matter</h4>
<p>The worst way to work remote is to not commit to it.  Commitment means aligning your process toward remote work.  Some lessons here.</p>
<p><strong>First, Hybrid meetings are harmful to your team</strong>.  There are 3 ways to do meetings: in person, remote, or hybrid.  An in person meeting involves putting a number of humans in a small room for an hour and letting them talk through an issue.  A remote meeting connects various people from the comforts of whatever work venue they’ve chosen, and discussion ensues over the internet.  In a hybrid meeting, some people are in the room, and some are connecting remotely.  Hybrid meetings are hell for the remote folks.  Usually they can’t hear at least one person well.  They can’t match faces to voices, lose context of what is happening in the room, and are sometimes just plain ignored by the folks in the room.</p>
<p>I really didn’t understand how bad this was until I did it myself a few times.  If you’re a leader who uses or tolerates hybrid meetings, I highly recommend trying to call into them remotely a few times.  As the boss you’ll get a slightly different experience, but ask yourself: are you a first class meeting participant when you’re calling in remote?  If not, is it acceptable to you to treat your remote workers as second class participants?</p>
<p><strong>Second, Use good tools</strong>.  Bad collaboration software is a drag if you’re working with people in person.  It’s a killer for remote teams.  Use software that lets you communicate in timely and useful ways, keep your project critical information organized, and lets your team focus on getting stuff done.  There are hundreds of good tools out there these days, so there’s no excuse for using bad ones.  My recommendations, which are not particularly controversial and also not the only good options: use Zoom for video chat, Slack for messaging, Bitbucket, GitHub, or Gitlab for Version Control, Trello or Jira<sup id="fnref-2"><a href="#fn-2" class="footnote-ref">2</a></sup> for task tracking depending on the size of your team, and Google Drive for keeping documents and documentation together<sup id="fnref-3"><a href="#fn-3" class="footnote-ref">3</a></sup>.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn-2">
<p>I… don’t love Jira.  But Trello doesn’t scale forever, and I haven’t seen anything significantly better than Jira for large teams.</p>
<a href="#fnref-2" class="footnote-backref">↩</a>
</li>
<li id="fn-3">
<p>My team doesn’t actually use Google Docs for documentation, we use Confluence.  Which is… worse than Jira.  So this is more of a “don’t be miserable like me” recommendation than one based on experience.  I’d be curious to hear if anyone has a documentation/wiki tool that they love.</p>
<a href="#fnref-3" class="footnote-backref">↩</a>
</li>
</ol>
</div>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Ben McCormick</name>
            <email>ben@benmccormick.org</email>
            <uri>http://benmccormick.org</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Review: The Manager's Path]]></title>
        <id>https://benmccormick.org/2019/06/12/book-review-the-managers-path</id>
        <link href="https://benmccormick.org/2019/06/12/book-review-the-managers-path">
        </link>
        <updated>2019-06-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Titles in the software engineering world are strange.  Without much work, it’s easy to find <em>Senior Engineers</em> with 2 years of professional experience, <em>junior developer</em> job descriptions requesting 5 years of experience, <em>tech lead</em> roles focused purely on technology, <em>tech lead</em> roles where the lead is managing a team, and who can tell the difference between a <em>CTO</em> and a <em>VP of Engineering</em> anyway?  This results in weird title shifts when developers switch jobs, odd or unfair salary distributions, and a world where it is very difficult to understand what a career path looks like in this industry.</p>
<p>Camille Fournier’s book <a href="https://amzn.to/2F2jG1p">The Manager’s Path</a> steps into this breach by laying out a clear look at an engineering management-focused career path. The book runs through a series of roles: <em>Mentor</em> to <em>Tech Lead</em> to <em>Manager</em> to <em>Manager of Managers</em> all the way up to <em>Executive</em>. For each role she describes what the job is,  walks through what type of challenges you might face in the role after a promotion, and offers practical advice on overcoming those challenges.</p>
<p>I found it to be an extremely engaging read, and the best description of what it actually looks like to advance in technical leadership roles I’ve ever read.  Because she focuses on skills and responsibilities more than titles, it’s possible to apply her advice across large and small companies, even those with wonky title structures.  It helped me think about what skills I need to be building in my career, and gave me a glimpse of what next steps look like.</p>
<p>The focus on common challenges and how to face them was also helpful, though whole books could (and have) been written on those challenges and how to face them at each level.  The Manager’s Path serves as a good starting point here, identifying the challenges and giving good solid general advice for facing them.  For those new to a role it could help them identify where they’re weak or uncomfortable, and serve as a starting point to a deeper dive into those areas.</p>
<p>As I read the book, I immediately thought of 4 or 5 people at various points in their career I knew who could benefit greatly from reading this book.  If you’re working in the software world and think that you long term are interested in advancing in your career beyond your current role, there will probably be interesting tidbits in here for you.  Even those who are sure they <strong>don’t</strong> want to be in management could benefit from understanding the perspectives of what engineering managers actually <em>do</em>.  The book is also structured so that the first few chapters are highly relevant for both technical and manager track developers; tech lead is an important role on both tracks.  If you fall into one of those buckets, I highly recommend <a href="https://amzn.to/2F2jG1p">The Manager’s Path</a>.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Ben McCormick</name>
            <email>ben@benmccormick.org</email>
            <uri>http://benmccormick.org</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Thinking About Values]]></title>
        <id>https://benmccormick.org/2019/06/03/thinking-values</id>
        <link href="https://benmccormick.org/2019/06/03/thinking-values">
        </link>
        <updated>2019-06-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As a way to help myself grow in my first year as a manager, I’ve been working through <a href="https://rework.withgoogle.com/guides/managers-develop-and-support-managers/steps/review-googles-new-manager-training/">Google’s New Manager Training</a> which they have generously published online.  One exercise that stood out to me was a “values selection” process, where they encourage managers to select a ranked list of 5-10 words that resonate with them as values from a list of around 400 “values words”.</p>
<p><a
    class="gatsby-resp-image-link"
    href="/static/f585fe7fa02d9e97dc89883f7e623db6/67e88/values-list.png"
    style="display: block"
    target="_blank"
    rel="noopener"
  >
    <span
    class="gatsby-resp-image-wrapper"
    style="position: relative; display: block;  max-width: 570px; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"
  >
    <span
      class="gatsby-resp-image-background-image"
      style="padding-bottom: 96.14093959731544%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url('data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAABQAAAATCAYAAACQjC21AAAACXBIWXMAAAsSAAALEgHS3X78AAAB10lEQVQ4y2WUh47DMAxD8/8/2JnupnvvqcMzQJ3iBggCEzIlUVSK7/dr1+vVjsej3e934wE7nU52uVxMD9j5fLbP5/OD8dVTEFBVlU0mE3s8HgkEG41Gtlwua5en06mt12t7v98eNx6Pbbfb2e12S+dECBnB+/0+gVwmcLFYOKHieNWJsMFgkDpMFXK53+/bbDbzzGC9Xs+Gw+FP1a1Wy1arlWOQdbtdez6f/y2XZZkqQksRttttm8/nfublIslfr5cTkhgZFOeElB4rJDOYBCcOWQ6HQ00G4sB1t5BeqkaEtIeGIuTLmanmg4pxRRQ7XuacJ8ENDC5WSDG0LDt5hbSNTTRlWmEoEltJqBBMLXJPbnANIURwGVnaMPloESVFR03/h1B6YQe1A0Z12+3WTSt7yTLRXrUpSxuCMSeZsQVJOMsy0poE0UpgUZpESGuQQsAOQwoWd1mE4LFCBkeVSuQVooMmJYvI6CKMU1aFYOgtO7mGgHEDwMgejQ1GhfHvAoZcGpLvcr5mYPlWoFWz2azpiEMajUaq1I1Nlk6nY5vNprZ6bEG+ZsRCiA/lhlrLEhthpY8w7CAdIaAacAanTvL9LrT0+e+LFjBx/JkShzT6SyuOBLr3BwgCtgPfjUqrAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC'); background-size: cover; display: block;"
    ></span>
    <img
        class="gatsby-resp-image-image"
        style="width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;box-shadow:inset 0px 0px 0px 400px white;"
        alt="A list of 400 values words like accountability, accuracy, achievement, altruism and more"
        title=""
        src="/static/f585fe7fa02d9e97dc89883f7e623db6/a9e6e/values-list.png"
        srcset="/static/f585fe7fa02d9e97dc89883f7e623db6/40f08/values-list.png 143w,
/static/f585fe7fa02d9e97dc89883f7e623db6/d4502/values-list.png 285w,
/static/f585fe7fa02d9e97dc89883f7e623db6/a9e6e/values-list.png 570w,
/static/f585fe7fa02d9e97dc89883f7e623db6/67e88/values-list.png 596w"
        sizes="(max-width: 570px) 100vw, 570px"
      />
  </span>
  </a></p>
<p>Choosing values is an odd process, because you’re choosing between “goods”.  When I first went through this sheet, I circled over 40 words as values that “resonated” with me.  They’re things that I value and strive for, or wish that I was more like.  Deciding between adventurousness and cowardice is not a “values decision”. A real values decision means that you’re trying to decide whether good traits like adventurousness, belonging, or clear-mindedness are more important to you.</p>
<p>Management often forces you to choose between goods: Will we ship quicker? Aim for higher quality? How do those choices impact work/life balance for our teams?. It’s hard to know if we’re making good choices, because the results routinely lack clarity.  Indicators lag, causation is fuzzy, and we don’t get to compare to a control group.  Values can be guideposts through ambiguity.  I’ve seen the power of this at a company level in my current gig, where having a set of values that are kept in the spotlight often allows us to weaponize them as decision making tools <sup id="fnref-1"><a href="#fn-1" class="footnote-ref">1</a></sup>.</p>
<p>Going through the list, I eventually cut things down to 20, 12, 10 and then 8.  That still feels like a lot to me, but for each of the 8 I can easily cite work situations I’ve faced in the past month where my response came directly out that value.  In the end I ended up with <em>Integrity</em>, <em>Thankfulness</em>, <em>Community</em>, <em>Prudence</em> (in the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prudence">classical sense</a>), <em>Generosity</em>, <em>Continual Improvement</em>, <em>Accountability</em>, <em>Justice</em>.  I find that these are easy to connect to my everyday work when I write them out as more detailed sentences though.</p>
<ol>
<li>Act with <em>integrity</em>.</li>
<li>Live with <em>thankfulness</em> for what I’ve been blessed with.</li>
<li>I want to work and live life in <em>community</em>.</li>
<li>Make decisions based on a rational analysis of reality, not feelings and first impressions (<em>Prudence</em>).</li>
<li>Don’t save it all for myself. Leave margin and be <em>generous</em>.</li>
<li><em>Continual Improvement</em> + Goodism are a powerful combo<sup id="fnref-2"><a href="#fn-2" class="footnote-ref">2</a></sup>.</li>
<li>Be <em>accountable</em> for my responsibilities and hold others to the same.</li>
<li>Actively work for <em>justice</em></li>
</ol>
<p>I’ve published them <a href="/my-values">here</a> with a bit more detail.</p>
<p>Those are “guideposts” that I can easily quote to myself or post up somewhere, but they still have enough substance to say something meaningful when I’m considering how to handle a low-performing employee, organizational changes, or personal career decisions. I’ve already seen these values bring a clarity to my thinking about tough things in a short period of time.  If you’re interested, I highly recommend checking out <a href="https://rework.withgoogle.com/guides/managers-develop-and-support-managers/steps/review-googles-new-manager-training/">Google’s training</a>.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn-1">
<p>I’ve also seen how quickly this becomes useless when those values are not universally embraced or enforced.</p>
<a href="#fnref-1" class="footnote-backref">↩</a>
</li>
<li id="fn-2">
<p>Probably a separate post, but <em>goodism</em> has always been my response when asked if I’m a perfectionist: “I’m a goodist.  I care about doing work that is good and meets the needed standards, but tend to move to the next challenge when I pass that bar and hit diminishing returns”.</p>
<a href="#fnref-2" class="footnote-backref">↩</a>
</li>
</ol>
</div>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Ben McCormick</name>
            <email>ben@benmccormick.org</email>
            <uri>http://benmccormick.org</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Herding Lions]]></title>
        <id>https://benmccormick.org/2019/05/27/herding-lions</id>
        <link href="https://benmccormick.org/2019/05/27/herding-lions">
        </link>
        <updated>2019-05-27T00:00:00Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I used to find myself using the term “herding cats” a lot when confronting inertia, disorganization or ambiguity in work situations.  <a href="https://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=herding%20cats">Urban Dictionary</a> actually endorses this:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The phrase herding cats comes from the common saying that something involving coordination of many different groups or people is as difficult as herding cats. One of the commonly encountered uses of the term in technical fields is the phrase “Managing programmers is like herding cats” or “Managing engineers is like herding cats”. In education it would be “Managing students is like herding cats”.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The phrase correctly captures the difficulty of getting a group of programmers (or even worse <em>teams of programmers</em>) on the same page.  But there’s an inherent arrogance to it.  The implication is that the herder is the adult in the room and everyone else’s pointless individualism is getting in the way.</p>
<p>There are days that I think I could fix everything if I could just get the *&#x26;$% cats to move in the right direction.  In those situations  I’ve started telling myself that what I’m actually doing is herding <strong>lions</strong>.  How do you herd a group of lions?  I have no idea.  But I know that if you don’t start with a healthy respect for the lion’s capabilities and agenda, it won’t end well for you.</p>
<p>When you treat people like lions, it’s an opportunity to stop and figure out <em>why</em> they’re not just getting on board with your <em>obvious</em> plan.  It’s an opportunity to learn, to find new ways to motivate people, and maybe even to empower somebody who had been viewing themselves as more of a kitten.  Ultimately the best teams flourish where people can <a href="https://rework.withgoogle.com/blog/five-keys-to-a-successful-google-team/">be strong contributors, take risks and do work they find meaningful</a>.  They’re teams of lions.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Ben McCormick</name>
            <email>ben@benmccormick.org</email>
            <uri>http://benmccormick.org</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Obvious Things]]></title>
        <id>https://benmccormick.org/2019/05/18/obvious-things</id>
        <link href="https://benmccormick.org/2019/05/18/obvious-things">
        </link>
        <updated>2019-05-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I saw a tweet thread a few weeks ago that made me think:</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">There’s a bit of a meme in some parts that there is value in saying, out loud, “I realize that I am surprised.” For similar reasons, I often subvocalize “I believe I now understand the type of situation the ‘trivial’ advice was preparing me for.” <a href="https://t.co/JzdYmSvJWH">https://t.co/JzdYmSvJWH</a></p>&mdash; Patrick McKenzie (@patio11) <a href="https://twitter.com/patio11/status/1115751939210223616?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">April 9, 2019</a></blockquote>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">And then you repeat it to someone and they say “lol that is obvious” and you wonder if you know the advice well enough yet to correct them on how not obvious it is going to be for their next 10 years.</p>&mdash; Patrick McKenzie (@patio11) <a href="https://twitter.com/patio11/status/1115752453910061056?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">April 9, 2019</a></blockquote>
<p>I realized that I’ve encountered plenty of pieces of wisdom in my software career that have this property; I see them as clear and obvious when put in the abstract, but only learn to actually apply them by repeatedly failing to do so.  This is what people talk about when they say something is “hard earned experience” I guess.</p>
<p>Here are some examples from my career:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>In the long run, rate of improvement (or regression) matters more than current level</strong> - This has applications in hiring, code quality, and finding/staying in a job.  But it’s often easier to observe how good something is now than to see how its changing, and I often fail to properly estimate what a trend means for a situation 1-3 years down the road.  It’s also easy to mis-apply this principle when you for get about the “long run” part.  A new employee with tons of potential won’t help you when you need an experienced hand <em>now</em> and fixing technical debt can easily cost you your ability to hit a quarterly objective.  Knowing how to balance these long and short term goals is something I still struggle with all the time.</li>
<li><strong>Rewriting from scratch is (almost) never worth it</strong> - <a href="https://www.joelonsoftware.com/2000/04/06/things-you-should-never-do-part-i/">Joel Spoelsky</a> wrote about this way back in 2000 and I remember reading that article nearly a decade ago and nodding along.  I seem to have infinite capacity to convince myself that my current situation fits in those parentheses though.  In my career this has mostly been a problem where I’m able to more accurately forecast the pain that would ensue from fixing what exists (because that code exists and is easier to work with), while I appear to systematically underestimate the pain of building the new thing (because the internet told me it would be great, and the code doesn’t exist for me to nitpick yet).</li>
<li><strong>Always consider multiple options</strong> - Pretty much any decision (technical or otherwise) benefits from having multiple contenders.  This seems obvious.  But I have often let myself fall into situations where I’m choosing between just 2 options, or really just choosing whether or not to do 1 thing.  This has applications in technology choices, job choices, responding to another person’s provocations, and more.  I intuitively know that more options are good, and I constantly miss opportunities to add options.</li>
</ol>
<p>So how do we improve on these situations where we fail to apply <em>obvious</em> wisdom?  I’ve been learning a few things lately.</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Always review what you’ve done on a regular basis</strong> - Do weekly reviews about how your week went.  Do quarterly reviews with yourself about how your job is going.  When you make big decisions, make sure to find a time to check back in later and evaluate how it went.  We make better decisions when we take the time to measure our results</li>
<li><strong>Note Missed Opportunities</strong> - When you do those reviews, make sure to pay attention to when you missed an opportunity to apply something you <em>knew</em>.  Sometimes we make mistakes because we just didn’t know something.  It’s more common though that we didn’t properly apply our own principles and knowledge.</li>
<li><strong>Identify Cues</strong> - Identify the thing that you know you’re going to have to handle different next time.  Maybe you say “if I’m looking for a job, I should consider at least 4 or 5 different companies and not focus in on just one”, or if I’m asked to fix a legacy codebase, I will spend at least 3 months trying to improve it before considering a re-write,and I’ll look for real world comparisons to base a rewrite estimate on”.  Whatever it is for you, when you can identify situations where a specific action should take place, it can help you be better the next time instead of repeating the same old mistakes.</li>
</ol>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Ben McCormick</name>
            <email>ben@benmccormick.org</email>
            <uri>http://benmccormick.org</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[How To Get Better Feedback On Your Code]]></title>
        <id>https://benmccormick.org/2019/04/22/better-code-feedback</id>
        <link href="https://benmccormick.org/2019/04/22/better-code-feedback">
        </link>
        <updated>2019-04-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>Deliberate practice [is when] (1) your attention is focused tightly on a specific skill you’re trying to improve […] (2) <strong>you receive feedback so you can correct your approach to keep your attention exactly where it is most productive.</strong></p>
<p><em>- Cal Newport, Deep Work</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>In <a href="https://amzn.to/2TqwDeR">Deep Work</a>, Cal Newport explains that research has shown the primary difference between experts and amateurs in a typical field is not innate talent; instead it is the amount of time they’ve spent in <em>Deliberate Practice</em> within their field of study that sets them apart.  Deliberate practice is not merely time spent working on the craft, but includes a <a href="https://benmccormick.org/2018/08/02/feedback-loops/">feedback loop</a> aspect. To get better at something, we need to receive meaningful feedback on whether what we’re doing is working.</p>
<p>When working with a team, one of the best ways to get this type of feedback is <a href="https://benmccormick.org/2019/01/14/value-from-code-reviews">quality code reviews</a>.  When you’re reviewing, you get to see other developers approaches to code, and when you’ve written code, you hopefully get high quality feedback from a different point of view.</p>
<p>In reality, code reviews don’t always provide the value they could.  Many developers don’t give much feedback at all on code reviews, give unhelpful aesthetic feedback, or may even use it abusively to try to show off their “superiority”. I can’t solve all of those problems, but here are a few tips I’ve found that help me get better feedback when my code is being reviewed.</p>
<h4>1. Annotate Pull Requests</h4>
<p>Most people assume that the inline commenting features in Github and Bitbucket code reviews are for use by the people reviewing the code.  But I’ve found that it can be helpful to preemptively add comments to my PRs to give reviewers context.
This is especially useful for information that may be relevant during a code review but isn’t long term relevant, like the original reason for extracting some reusable code and where it came from.  Below is an example of a comment I left demoing how React hooks could be used to pull out shared logic in my work project.</p>
<p><a
    class="gatsby-resp-image-link"
    href="/static/a883e2a63572b0df0719ee97fac65e95/df1a7/comment-example.png"
    style="display: block"
    target="_blank"
    rel="noopener"
  >
    <span
    class="gatsby-resp-image-wrapper"
    style="position: relative; display: block;  max-width: 570px; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"
  >
    <span
      class="gatsby-resp-image-background-image"
      style="padding-bottom: 32.14285714285714%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url('data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAABQAAAAGCAYAAADDl76dAAAACXBIWXMAAAsSAAALEgHS3X78AAABD0lEQVQY04WQWW/CMBCE8/9/WA/1ECpSaShFUHI5duz4inNApxtD1T6Vh0+z1o7Xs058FyCaFqo1ETmjLlDNtMDsCWGI+K4H4wq1UPFeIzWpRkN+5wMSax01W+xqhp0osRcFMlVFmBNggaPpJaGiiiBR2hqV5agcJ8+vci+R8LLAZrPH+tBim3Hs8gpctpSOXlaUXFNyY2C8h73gug6282fmc+giYeiRTNMR2jgw1oDTKhVpHZVSyfPqWjsM/YhxmDDM9H/0Uv/0kvlfjPVYsQ+8sBWW9RsW5StW8h2f4wHFV4H8lCM7Zv9yIPKxOA9U2uK5WuKGPeCWPeKOuK+fsDBLpFOK9Wl9lfSUYnvc4hs/scSv4Qbq/QAAAABJRU5ErkJggg=='); background-size: cover; display: block;"
    ></span>
    <img
        class="gatsby-resp-image-image"
        style="width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;box-shadow:inset 0px 0px 0px 400px white;"
        alt="hooks comment example"
        title=""
        src="/static/a883e2a63572b0df0719ee97fac65e95/a9e6e/comment-example.png"
        srcset="/static/a883e2a63572b0df0719ee97fac65e95/40f08/comment-example.png 143w,
/static/a883e2a63572b0df0719ee97fac65e95/d4502/comment-example.png 285w,
/static/a883e2a63572b0df0719ee97fac65e95/a9e6e/comment-example.png 570w,
/static/a883e2a63572b0df0719ee97fac65e95/c2e96/comment-example.png 855w,
/static/a883e2a63572b0df0719ee97fac65e95/df1a7/comment-example.png 1036w"
        sizes="(max-width: 570px) 100vw, 570px"
      />
  </span>
  </a></p>
<p>These types of comments are also good ways to point a reviewer to the important parts of a review. This matters for reviews where there are many small changes across a large number of files, with a few high impact changes.  It’s always better to make atomic changes (see <a href="https://benmccormick.org/2019/01/14/value-from-code-reviews">more here</a>), but when you must make a large change, this technique can help a lot.  I have received noticeably better feedback on my large pull requests since I began annotating</p>
<h4>2. Encourage Questions</h4>
<p>If you’re receiving feedback from more junior members of a team, they may not always be comfortable giving direct feedback on code.  One way to get better feedback in those situations is to encourage them to ask questions about things they don’t understand.  This gives them opportunities to learn, but also let’s you see which parts of your code are unintuitive or unfamiliar to the rest of the team.  In some cases the questions will expose bugs that a more confident reviewer may have pointed out straight out, and that experience can help grow a reviewers confidence and lead to even better feedback next time.</p>
<p>Of course asking questions rather than assuming understanding can be a good tactic when giving feedback in general, and is worth considering when doing your own reviews regardless of whether a reviewer has encouraged it.</p>
<h4>3. Find More Than One Reviewer</h4>
<p>This applies to more than just code, but if you’re not getting the feedback you need right now, ask somebody else.  In a work setting, this might be finding different team members to review your code.  If that isn’t possible at work, finding other ways to write code and get feedback on it can make a big difference in your career.  Not everyone has time or capacity for this, but contributing to open source, project nights at local meetups and hackathons can all be great ways to learn and get feedback from others.  If you can find a mentor to talk through code challenges with, that can be beneficial even if they aren’t on your team and going through your code line by line.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Ben McCormick</name>
            <email>ben@benmccormick.org</email>
            <uri>http://benmccormick.org</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ten Soft Skills That Will Shape Your Career]]></title>
        <id>https://benmccormick.org/2019/04/15/soft-skills</id>
        <link href="https://benmccormick.org/2019/04/15/soft-skills">
        </link>
        <updated>2019-04-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the most popular posts in the history of my blog was a list with the click-baity name <a href="https://benmccormick.org/2017/07/19/ten-things-javascript/">Ten Things A Serious JavaScript Developer Should Learn</a>.  It explicitly focused on the set of technical skills that you need to become a “senior” JavaScript developer.  While I’m happy with that post, I’ve always wanted to revisit the idea, because it is my strong belief that <em>once you’ve hit a minimum level of technical capability, only about 20% of career success is determined by your technical skills</em>.  The other 80% is composed of skills that can be loosely bundled under “soft skills”.</p>
<p>You may quibble with my choice of percentage, but I don’t think the underlying idea that things other than technical ability is particularly controversial.  Even if they bitterly dismiss such things as “politics” most developers are aware that their careers are impacted by things that go beyond their ability to write algorithms.  What I haven’t seen much of however, are attempts to catalogue what these soft skills are, and how somebody might get better at them.  The second part is outside of the scope of a single post, though I will attempt to list resources here.  But the first is achievable, and that is what I will attempt to do here.</p>
<p>The following is not an exhaustive list, but it covers 10 “soft skills” that I’ve seen have a clear impact on my career in software and those of others.  The best part? These are things you can grow in that will have an impact in your life outside of work, and in any career you might transition into in the future.</p>
<h3>The Skills</h3>
<h4>1. Clear Communication</h4>
<p>While I’m making bold statements: A developer’s ability to communicate clearly is the single most important skill in determining the trajectory of their career.  Poor communicators are forced to rely on others to interpret their work, even when it is brilliant.  They will often create problems for others through miscommunications or lead teams to make suboptimal decisions because they were not able to explain the technical considerations involved in a situation.</p>
<p>Great communicators on the other hand, enlighten.  They help teams understand what is really going on so that non-technical team members can make good decisions, and technical folk can work with confidence.  Great communicators cut through misunderstandings, expose ambiguity and poor assumptions, and can translate for team members who are having trouble making themselves heard.</p>
<p>Communication skills are important for those on a management track, but they are just as important for those on a technical trajectory. Architects, Principal Engineers and Tech Leads must coordinate with many teams, teach less experienced developers, explain technical tradeoffs and document decisions and code.  Those are core parts of a senior technical employee’s job, and all of them come down to communication.</p>
<p><strong>Resources</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://benmccormick.org/2019/03/02/the-importance-of-writing">The Importance Of Writing For Software Developers</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.codingame.com/blog/10-tips-to-improve-your-communication-skills-as-a-software-developer/">10 Tips to Improve your Communication Skills as a Software Developer</a></li>
</ul>
<h4>2. Attention Management</h4>
<p>This one is more commonly referred to as “time management”, but I agree with <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/03/28/smarter-living/productivity-isnt-about-time-management-its-about-attention-management.html">this recent NYT Op-Ed</a>: the mechanics of how we organize our time is less important than whether we end up spending it on the most important things.  This broadly encompasses the ability to prioritize, to prevent distractions from wreaking havoc on productivity, and the ability to find ways to get back on track when things go wrong or priorities change.</p>
<p>This was a weakness for me early in my career: I got things done but often did them haphazardly or inefficiently.  One of my biggest sources of growth in the last few years has been finding ways to structure and prioritize my time better, while cutting out distractions.  This has been necessary due to life changes: I’m now a parent and have people reporting to me at work.  I wouldn’t be able to meet my current responsibilities with the habits I had as a 25 year old.  For me this has been largely about focusing in on a small amount of essential things and actively removing less important things from my life.  For others it may be more about establishing patterns and limits.  Either way, this requires planning and introspection first to be effective.</p>
<p><strong>Resources</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://amzn.to/2TqwDeR">Deep Work - Cal Newport</a></li>
<li><a href="http://bradfrost.com/blog/post/scheduling-every-minute-of-my-day/">Scheduling Every Minute of My Day - Brad Frost</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/03/28/smarter-living/productivity-isnt-about-time-management-its-about-attention-management.html">Productivity Isn’t About Time Management, It’s about Attention Management - Adam Grant</a></li>
</ul>
<h4>3. Initiative</h4>
<p>If you see an opportunity or a problem, do you do something about it?  I’ve been reading a good amount of “manager books” recently, and in many of them a surprising amount of focus is dedicated to the question of how we create conditions when people are “empowered” to act.  And there certainly is an environmental factor here.  People are more likely to take initiative and risks when they’re not afraid of being punished for it.  But the individual also controls a lot here.  Developers who are willing to step up and take initiative in a situation can make an outsize impact.</p>
<p>Do you have a piece of code or process on your team that everybody acknowledges is a bit wonky, but nobody has ever taken the time to fix even though it is slowly taking a toll on the team over time?  Are there simple things that you know could make your product better, but nobody has quite taken the time to get to them?  Those are the opportunities that initiative can turn into value.</p>
<p><strong>Resources</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://overreacted.io/fix-like-no-ones-watching/">Fix Like No One’s Watching</a></li>
</ul>
<h4>4. Empathy</h4>
<p>There is no meaningful software product that has been created in isolation.  One person may have written the code (though that is quite rare for software with any scale of impact), and maybe even didn’t collaborate with anyone to handle distribution / hosting etc, but if that software is used by others there is always support, training and marketing to consider.  You can create a todo app for yourself without talking to anyone.  But nobody makes a career in this business without talking to other humans.</p>
<p>The thing about us humans; we work well with people who we trust, and who we perceive as caring about us.  We also are for the most part exceptionally good at discerning when somebody is faking it.  So if we can’t get away from humans, and we can’t be fake, what can we do?  We are left with, in the words of Dale Carnegie “becoming genuinely interested in other people”.  If you’re currently filled with red-faced frustration at your annoying co-worker or manipulative boss, this may seem like asking for a miracle. And arguably any time we look outside ourselves it is a miracle. But regardless of your philosophical outlook on such things, there are definitely ways we can improve in how we work with and care for the people around us.  And it starts with trying to empathize and seeing the people around us as human beings and not obstacles or tools.</p>
<p><strong>Resources</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://amzn.to/2Iiooe4">How To Win Friends And Influence People - Dale Carnegie</a></li>
<li><a href="https://amzn.to/2YSZasy">Radical Candor - Kimball Scott</a></li>
<li><a href="https://amzn.to/2WVkqfv">I Hear You - Michael Sorenson</a></li>
</ul>
<h4>5. Negotiation &#x26; Persuasion</h4>
<p>You may not think that Software Engineering involves much negotiation.  But that is only true if you use a shallow definition of negotiation.  Every time a team debates implementation strategies for a feature, which tickets should end up in a sprint, and how much time to spend chasing a difficult to reproduce bug, they are engaging in negotiation, and team members are attempting to persuade.  And there is a wealth of knowledge out there describing how to improve on these skills.</p>
<p>A word of caution here; unlike some of the other things on this list, these skills can often be dangerous when they’re improved in isolation.  When developers complain about politics trumping technical ability, they’re often experiencing decisions being made based on the ability of some employees to persuade and negotiate.  When those employees are not actually providing the best ideas this is suboptimal.  For the technically skilled employees, the answer is to learn to persuade better.  But for those who can negotiate we always need to make sure that we’re <strong>persuading for good</strong>.  Just like the loudest voices shouldn’t always win, when you can communicate well, make sure to stay humble and  boost other’s good ideas when you see them.</p>
<p><strong>Resources</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://amzn.to/2OUBnnl">Negotiation Genius - Deepak Malhotra and Max Bazerman</a></li>
</ul>
<h4>6. Continual Learning</h4>
<p>Were you paying attention in high school physics when they taught about the difference between distance, velocity, and acceleration?  Distance is the amount an object has traveled.  Velocity is the speed at which it is currently moving in a given direction.  Acceleration is the rate at which the object’s velocity is changing.  If you want to know where an object is <em>right now</em>, distance is the only thing that matters.  But as time progresses, velocity starts to matter more, and in the very long term any difference in acceleration will be the only thing that matters.</p>
<p>The same ideas play out when acquiring skills.  If you need to evaluate your career potential for the next few months, the skills and accomplishments you’ve acquired so far (distance) are the only things that matter.  But if you want to think about your career potential over the next 30 years, the new skills you’re acquiring (velocity) and even more importantly your ability to get better at learning new things (acceleration) will matter much much more. Learning is a skill unto itself, and the earlier you invest in it the more dividends it will pay over time.</p>
<p><strong>Resources</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://css-tricks.com/learning-to-learn/">Learning To Learn - Sarah Drasner</a></li>
<li><a href="http://benmccormick.org/2019/02/18/how-to-keep-learning-js">How To Keep Learning JavaScript</a></li>
</ul>
<h4>7. Self Care</h4>
<p>Another lesson that I’ve learned the hard way in my career is the reality of my own mortality.  None of us are indestructible, and our bodies are not perpetual energy machines.  They require care and maintenance.  Our souls too are not meant to run on work alone, and we can burn out hard without sufficient rest.  This is all aside from deeper issues of disease and mental health that can change our lives in even more profound and difficult ways.</p>
<p>Self care is a career skill because frankly we are great at deluding ourselves into thinking we’re functioning normally while we’ve compromised ourselves.  <a href="https://www.thecut.com/2014/07/you-might-not-know-if-youre-sleep-deprived.html">Research</a> shows that we are horrible judges of whether our judgement and creativity are compromised by lack of sleep.  Because we can’t run controlled studies on ourselves, we don’t really know whether our lack of exercise or 60 hour workweek induced burnout are hurting our creativity.  But research suggests it is for pretty much everybody.</p>
<p>Healthy socialization, sleeping, eating and exercise ultimately lead to better emotional stability, ability to focus, and creativity.  But even aside from the career benefits, when we’re devouring our bodies and minds for work, it leads to a question of what we’re doing this for in the first place.</p>
<p><strong>Resources</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://amzn.to/2OVBpvx">Why We Sleep - Matthew Walker</a></li>
<li><a href="https://benmccormick.org/2019/03/09/book-review-deep-work-common-rule">Deep Work &#x26; The Common Rule</a></li>
</ul>
<h4>8. Business Awareness</h4>
<p>Do you know what your company actually does?  Do you understand why the features you’re building are important, and the relative priority of them?  Can you explain the business tradeoffs involved when you’re making an software architecture decision between performance and security?</p>
<p>In companies larger than a few people it’s not ultimately developers’ jobs to make business decisions.  But understanding the context for those decisions helps us better prioritize our time, make good tradeoffs, and call attention to inefficiencies or counterproductive behavior in our products. In addition, nobody wants to spend time working on things that don’t matter. But when we try to innovate without understanding the broader business, we often end up doing just that.</p>
<p><strong>Resources</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://mcfunley.com/choose-boring-technology">Choose Boring Technology - Dan McKinley</a></li>
</ul>
<h4>9. Marketing and Branding</h4>
<p>Marketing is a dirty word in engineering circles.  Many take the attitude of the Dilbert comics that <a href="https://dilbert.com/strip/1997-05-02">marketing is a synonym for exaggeration lying, and fraud</a>.  But at it’s core marketing is just making sure that the people who could benefit from your services are aware of those services.  This has several applications to developers.  In the job market, finding ways to let employers know who you are and what you’re capable of is important.  But in medium to large companies it also is important to do some level of internal marketing; to make sure you’re credited for the work you’ve done and that people understand it’s values.  Developers who consider themselves above this or dismiss it as politics do so at their own peril.</p>
<p><strong>Resources</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.stephaniemorillo.co/single-post/2019/02/17/7-Common-Content-Marketing-Mistakes-Developers-Make-and-How-to-Avoid-Them">7 Common Content Marketing Mistakes Developers Make and How to Avoid Them - Stephanie Morillo</a></li>
</ul>
<h4>10. Character</h4>
<p>The final item here is in some ways an oddball.  While the other 9 things on this list are skills that you can work on, character is something deeper.  Questions of what good character is and how you develop it are way outside the scope of this post.  And I would personally consider any attempt to improve your character for solely utilitarian career reasons to be ultimately hollow.  But character is undeniably important in your career.</p>
<p>Do the people around you trust you?  Do they believe that you’re trying to do the right thing?  If the answers are no, you may find obstacles in the most unexpected places.  If the answers are yes, you will eventually find help from people you would never have looked to.</p>
<p>In addition, as an industry, technology has the power to shape the world, and as practitioners we all get the chance to impact our little corners of the world.  It’s worth considering not just whether we’re “succeeding in our career”, but what impact we’re having on the world around us.</p>
<p><strong>Resources</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://amzn.to/2I5jP7K">Future Ethics - Cennydd Bowles</a></li>
</ul>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Ben McCormick</name>
            <email>ben@benmccormick.org</email>
            <uri>http://benmccormick.org</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
</feed>