<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>http://benmccormick.org</id>
    <title>benmccormick.org</title>
    <updated>2017-02-14T03:28:08Z</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Ben McCormick</name>
        <email>ben@benmccormick.org</email>
        <uri>http://benmccormick.org</uri>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://benmccormick.org"/>
    <subtitle>A blog by Ben McCormick</subtitle>
    <rights>All rights reserved 2016, Ben McCormick</rights>
    <generator>Feed for Node.js</generator>
    <contributor>
        <name>Ben McCormick</name>
        <email>ben@benmccormick.org</email>
    </contributor>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Evaluating Web Apps With Lighthouse]]></title>
        <id>https://benmccormick.org/2017/02/13/improving-site-performance-with-lighthouse/</id>
        <link href="https://benmccormick.org/2017/02/13/improving-site-performance-with-lighthouse/">
        </link>
        <updated>2017-02-13T22:30:00Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last year Google coined the term “Progressive Web App” as a way of describing the type of sites and applications that they think are the future of the web.  Progressive Web Apps are sites that load quickly, are always responsive to user input, work as well as possible offline, and integrate with native platforms like native apps.  While this site is not an “app” per say, I do want it to be as fast and responsive as possible, and I also wanted to better understand what Google is pulling under the PWA umbrella.  Fortunately, Google has built a tool <a href="https://developers.google.com/web/tools/lighthouse/">Lighthouse</a> to help developers profile and improve their web applications, comparing them to a set of PWA benchmarks.  So I took this site through Lighthouse, and worked against their suggestions with the goal of learning more about PWAs and improving the experience of using <a href="http://benmccormick.org">benmccormick.org</a>.  I’m passing along my experience here.</p>
<h3>Getting Started</h3>
<p>I began by downloading the Lighthouse extension in the <a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/lighthouse/blipmdconlkpinefehnmjammfjpmpbjk">Chrome Web Store</a>.  Lighthouse can be installed either as a chrome extension or a node command line tool.  Both produce the same HTML report, but I chose the chrome extension for the convenience of keeping everything in the browser.  When I ran the initial report, I got the following result:</p>
<img alt="first score: 48/100" src="http://benmccormick.org/posts/images/lighthouse/first_report_summary.png" class="full-width bordered-img">
<p>48 out of 100 didn’t seem like a bad starting place.  Scrolling down it looked like I was mainly dinged on a few main areas:</p>
<ol>
<li>I had no offline support</li>
<li>I did’t have any special setup for being included on a users homescreen. (I did have platform appropriate icons, but no app configuration)</li>
<li>I had some possible inefficiencies in the assets I loaded.</li>
</ol>
<img alt="offline issues" src="http://benmccormick.org/posts/images/lighthouse/first_report_offline.png" class="full-width bordered-img">
<img alt="native issues" src="http://benmccormick.org/posts/images/lighthouse/first_report_native.png" class="full-width bordered-img">
<img alt="asset issues" src="http://benmccormick.org/posts/images/lighthouse/first_report_assets.png" class="full-width bordered-img">
<p>Native app support isn’t a huge priority for me, and the assets issue seemed small, so I decided to investigate the offline support issue first.</p>
<h3>Offline</h3>
<p>I based my service worker implementation off of <a href="https://github.com/chriscoyier/Simple-Offline-Site">Simple Offline Site</a> a demo Service Worker repo created by Chris Coyier for an article on <a href="https://css-tricks.com/serviceworker-for-offline/">CSS Tricks</a>.  This was perfect since it’s default behavior was what I wanted: cache everything, and check for updates from the server everytime we return from cache so we’re never out of date for long.  You can see what I did specifically in my <a href="https://github.com/benmccormick/benmccormickorg/blob/master/pages/sw.es6">github repo for this site</a>. After adding the service worker, my score moved up to 63/100.</p>
<p>Finally, Service Workers only work on HTTPS connections, but most links to my site are not https currently. So to take full advantage (and to address another metric I was flagged on), I used a <a href="https://support.cloudflare.com/hc/en-us/articles/200170536-How-do-I-redirect-all-visitors-to-HTTPS-SSL-">CloudFlare page rule</a> to redirect all visting traffic to use https.  That bumped me up to 69/100.</p>
<img alt="asset issues" src="http://benmccormick.org/posts/images/lighthouse/second_report_offline.png" class="full-width bordered-img">
<h3>Native Support</h3>
<p>As I said previously, native platform support isn’t a major priority for this blog, but I was curious about the process.  Getting native support turned out to be very straightforward.  I had already collected icons for the various platforms, and created a simple manifest when I originally created a favicon for my site.  But the manifest file didn’t have everything and it wasn’t being deployed properly to my site.  Fixing that and making it available at <code>/manifest.json</code>, fixed all of the problems related to native platform support.</p>
<p>My manifest file now looks like this:</p>
<pre><code class="language-json">{
	&quot;name&quot;: &quot;benmccormick.org&quot;,
  &quot;short_name&quot;: &quot;benmccormick&quot;,
	&quot;icons&quot;: [
		{
			&quot;src&quot;: &quot;\/android-chrome-192x192.png?v=yyxgnp97qG&quot;,
			&quot;sizes&quot;: &quot;192x192&quot;,
			&quot;type&quot;: &quot;image\/png&quot;
		},
		{
			&quot;src&quot;: &quot;\/android-chrome-384x384.png?v=yyxgnp97qG&quot;,
			&quot;sizes&quot;: &quot;384x384&quot;,
			&quot;type&quot;: &quot;image\/png&quot;
		}
	],
	&quot;theme_color&quot;: &quot;#ffffff&quot;,
	&quot;background_color&quot;: &quot;#57a3e8&quot;,
	&quot;display&quot;: &quot;browser&quot;
}
</code></pre>
<p>After correctly deploying that manifest file, my score moved all the way up to 100/100!</p>
<img alt="asset issues" src="http://benmccormick.org/posts/images/lighthouse/third_report_native.png" class="full-width bordered-img">
<p>I clearly benefited from starting in a good spot.  <a href="https://github.com/gatsbyjs/gatsby">Gatsby</a> is “fast by default” as a platform for building blogs, and I’ve done my best to avoid making it slow.  But it was fun seeing what I could do to make the site a better experience for users with bad connectivity, and to learn more about what Google is trying to do with PWAs.</p>
<h3>More Resources</h3>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Google has a bunch of resources around creating Progressive Web Apps.  You can find them on <a href="https://developers.google.com/web/progressive-web-apps/">their PWA landing page</a>.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>It was so easy to make my blog a PWA mostly because it is built on <a href="https://github.com/gatsbyjs/gatsby">Gatsby</a>. Worth looking at if you’re a web developer who blogs.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3>Subscribe</h3>
<p>Thanks for taking the time to read this post!  Web development is one of the main topics of this blog, so if you enjoyed the post, please consider subscribing by using the <a href="http://feedpress.me/benmccormick">feed</a>, <a href="http://twitter.com/benmccormickorg">Twitter</a> or my <a href="http://eepurl.com/WFYon">mailing list</a>. If you liked this post you also might want to check out my article from 2015 on <a href="https://benmccormick.org/2015/11/25/productive-javascript-development/">Productive JavaScript Development</a>.</p>
]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Ben McCormick</name>
            <email>ben@benmccormick.org</email>
            <uri>http://benmccormick.org</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[MobX: First Impressions]]></title>
        <id>https://benmccormick.org/2017/01/09/mobx-first-impressions/</id>
        <link href="https://benmccormick.org/2017/01/09/mobx-first-impressions/">
        </link>
        <updated>2017-01-09T13:30:00Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I spent some time around the holidays this year playing with <a href="https://mobx.js.org/">MobX</a>, a state management library for JavaScript.  MobX is an unopinionated library that provides a layer over normal JavaScript data structures that allow other code to efficiently observe data changes and update based on what has changed.  It’s an interesting tool for handling state in web applications, especially in existing projects that might need to update state handling iteratively.  Here are some first impressions.</p>
<h3>What is MobX?</h3>
<p>MobX has 3 core concepts developers need to understand:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Observable state</strong> - MobX provides functions to make data <em>observable</em>.  Observable data can be watched by other pieces of code which may efficiently update when the state changes.  Observable data is primarily created in MobX using the <code>observable</code> function.</li>
<li><strong>Derivations</strong> - Functions that <em>watch</em> observable data are called derivations.  MobX has 2 primary types of derivations: <em>computed values</em> and <em>reactions</em>.  Computed values update a value based on other data, while reactions produce side effects: updates to a UI, a network call, or a logging statement for example. MobX provides a <code>computed</code> function for defining computed values; in most cases reactions will likely be mostly defined using a framework specific helper library like <a href="https://github.com/mobxjs/mobx-react">mobx-react</a> or <a href="https://github.com/500tech/ng2-mobx">ng2-mobx</a>.  MobX does provide some lower level libraries for reactions though, including <code>autorun</code> and <code>when</code>.</li>
<li><strong>Actions</strong> - Code that updates observable state is known as an action.  MobX has a formalized version of actions which can be defined using the <code>action</code> function, but it is also possible to modify state directly using any normal JavaScript code and maintain observable behavior.</li>
</ol>
<p>In practice this looks something like this:</p>
<pre><code class="language-javascript">import React from 'react';
import ReactDOM from 'react-dom';
import {observable} from 'mobx';
import {observer} from 'mobx-react';

let digits = observable([1, 2]);

const DigitPrinter = observer(({digits}) =&gt; {
  return (&lt;div&gt;
    {digits.join(', ')}
  &lt;/div&gt;);
});

ReactDOM.render( &lt;DigitPrinter digits = {digits} /&gt;, document.getElementById('root'));

/* prints 1, 2 */


digits.push(3);

/* DOM re-renders to print 1, 2, 3 */

digits[2] = 4;

/* DOM re-renders to print 1, 2, 4 */

</code></pre>
<p>The component is able to passively <em>observe</em> changes in the data, and re-render when it changes.  But MobX is actually even smarter than this example shows.  Let’s look at another example, this time using a more complex data structure (a class).</p>
<pre><code class="language-javascript">import React from 'react';
import ReactDOM from 'react-dom';
import {extendObservable} from 'mobx';
import {observer} from 'mobx-react';
import moment from 'moment';

class Appointment {

  constructor() {
    extendObservable(this, {
      dueDate: '01-01-2017',
      title: 'Dinner with Joe'
      location: 'Chik-Fil-A',
      isToday: computed(function() {
        return moment(dueDate, 'MM-DD-YYYY').diff(moment.now(), 'days') === 0;
      }),
    });
  }

  toString() {
    return `${this.title} @ ${this.location}`;
  }
}


const TodayBox = observer(class TodayBox extends React.Component {
  render () {
    let {appointments} = this.props;
    return (&lt;div&gt;
      {appointments.filter(a =&gt; a.isToday).map(a =&gt; &lt;span&gt;a.toString()&lt;/span&gt;)}     
    &lt;/div&gt;);
  }
});

let appointment = new Appointment();

ReactDOM.render( &lt;TodayBox appointments = {[appointment]} /&gt;, document.getElementById('root'));

/* prints an empty div */

appointment.title = 'Dinner with Bob';

/* Nothing relevant has changed. The component does not re-render */

appointment.dueDate = '01-09-2017';  

/*  assume that 01-09-2017 is &quot;today&quot; */
</code></pre>
<p>MobX has the “magical” ability to determine what changes actually affect the observer and not make unnecessary calls of reaction functions.  In practice, that magic allows you to write less, more efficient code for updating your UI based on data.</p>
<h3>How Does MobX work?</h3>
<p>I have a learned skepticism of magical solutions like this.  Generally I find that time-saving magic like this ends up costing time when it comes to maintenance, and explicit relationships between code saves time over less-boilerplate heavy code. Fortunately, while the libraries code itself is fairly complex, it isn’t too hard to understand the logic behind how MobX works.</p>
<p>On the Observer side, MobX uses <a href="http://benmccormick.org/2015/09/14/es5-es6-es2016-es-next-whats-going-on-with-javascript-versioning/">ES5</a> setters and getters to proxy updates to observable data structure and listen in when data is updated.  This allows the type of event listening that <a href="http://backbonejs.org/">Backbone</a> and other libraries provide, without requiring the user to go through special <code>set</code> or <code>get</code> methods to update an object’s properties.  Most of the time you should be able to just be able to write code as you normally would, and MobX will make it work.  There are some exceptions though that mean its important to actually understand how the library work.  Getters and Setters only work when looking up an existing property on an object, so when using primitive values or adding new values to an existing object, some special syntax (the return of <code>get</code> and <code>set</code> methods) may be required.  In Mobx primitive observables are referred to as <em>boxed</em> values, and objects that require new values over time can be handled by using observable Maps, which use the API of <a href="http://benmccormick.org/2015/09/14/es5-es6-es2016-es-next-whats-going-on-with-javascript-versioning/">ES6</a> Maps.</p>
<p>On the derivative side, reactions and computed values are always defined as functions.  MobX wraps these functions and is able to determine (through the method described above) what properties were accessed during each function run.  It then only listens for changes to these properties.  Thus it doesn’t matter if you theoretically could access thousands of observable properties in a function, if you wrap those references in an if statement to a single property, and that property returns false on first run, the derivative function will only listen for changes on that property before running again. When an observable is updated, all derivative code is run synchronously and atomically so there is no concern of getting into bad intermediate states.</p>
<p>Most of the “magic” is covered by the 2 paragraphs above, and once you understand the ideas behind them (see the resources at the bottom of this post for more in-depth explanations), it is fairly easy to understand the reasoning behind the cases where the magic fails.</p>
<h3>Decorators</h3>
<p>Developers who actually use MobX are probably questioning my examples by now, because I’ve been using a different syntax than the primary MobX documentation for showing my examples.  So let’s talk about decorators.  The preferred way (according to the documentation) to write MobX code is to use decorators to define observers and observables.  Decorators are a <a href="http://tc39.github.io/proposal-decorators/">proposed new JavaScript feature</a> for declaratively adding extra behavior to classes, class properties and class methods.  Using them with MobX, my above example would look like this [^1]:</p>
<pre><code class="language-javascript">
class Appointment {

  @observable dueDate = '01-01-2017'
  @observable title = 'Dinner with Joe'
  @observable location = 'Chik-Fil-A'

  @computed get isToday() {
    return moment(dueDate, 'MM-DD-YYYY').diff(moment.now(), 'days') === 0;
  }

  toString() {
    return `${this.title} @ ${this.location}`;
  }
}


@observer class TodayBox extends React.Component {
  render () {
    let {appointments} = this.props;
    return (&lt;div&gt;
      {appointments.filter(a =&gt; a.isToday).map(a =&gt; &lt;span&gt;a.toString()&lt;/span&gt;)}     
    &lt;/div&gt;);
  }
}
</code></pre>
<p>That obviously looks a lot cleaner than my example.  So what’s the problem?  Again, decorators are a <em>proposed</em> JavaScript feature.  Currently they’re in Stage 2, which means roughly that they are very likely to eventually make it into the language, but may change in non-trivial ways before that happens.  Currently decorators are implemented in <a href="https://www.typescriptlang.org/docs/handbook/decorators.html">TypeScript</a>, as well as a <a href="https://github.com/loganfsmyth/babel-plugin-transform-decorators-legacy">3rd party babel plugin</a>, but as of January 2017 <a href="http://kangax.github.io/compat-table/esnext/#test-class_decorators">are not implemented in any browser engines</a>, and are not implemented in any first party babel plugins <a href="https://github.com/babel/babel/issues/2645">due to spec instability</a>.  Decorators are a key part of Angular2, and are used by other frameworks including <a href="http://aurelia.io/">Aurelia</a> and <a href="https://github.com/rwjblue/ember-computed-decorators">Ember</a>, so I don’t think they’re going away.  But I also don’t see them as ready for production use for teams that don’t have the capacity to dedicate the time to update existing code if/when the spec changes[^2].  If for one reason or other you’re comfortable with the risks however, decorators are a great way to clean up the MobX API, and I’m excited for the spec to get to the point where I can use them.</p>
<h3>Comparison to Redux and setState</h3>
<p>As a state management library that was built to be used with React, the obvious questions to ask about MobX are how it improves over React’s built in state handling, and how it compares to <a href="http://redux.js.org/">Redux</a>, the current most popular state management solution for React. MobX takes a different approach to each.</p>
<p>It’s important to say at the start that MobX isn’t mutually exclusive with using setState.  It’s possible to use them together, with MobX managing application data and setState handling individual component/UI state.  But there is some advantages to using MobX for UI state as well.  The biggest reason is that MobX is smarter than setState about when re-rendering is required.  By default React Components re-render on any call to setState, regardless of whether the state change actually affects what is rendered or not. MobX’s creator <a href="https://medium.com/@mweststrate/3-reasons-why-i-stopped-using-react-setstate-ab73fc67a42e#.x0o6y4rxv">wrote more about this on Medium</a>.</p>
<p>Comparing MobX and Redux could be a whole article on its own, so I’m not going to go too deep here, but suffice it to say that MobX is more flexible than Redux, but as a result loses some of the benefits of Redux’s structured approach.  Specifically, it is easy to convert a single object to become a MobX observable and use it in an existing React component.  It can be easily inlined in an existing file and used for one component even.  You also don’t have to deal with the ceremony of using <a href="http://benmccormick.org/2016/06/04/what-are-mutable-and-immutable-data-structures-2/">immutable data</a>.  Redux is intended as a solution that will take over all your state, and doesn’t scale down nearly as well or mix with other solutions [^3].  However, Redux’s structure also has benefits.  It allows easy testings of each component of an app individually, the creation of powerful tooling that will work with any Redux app, and reliable guarantees of how state will be updated.  These things are mostly possible with MobX [^4], but require more developer discipline, and/or can’t be written as easily as universal tools. Overgeneralizing, I would prefer Redux in a new application, but would look to MobX for improving data management in an existing application.  MobX also has advantages in applications where you’re displaying a large amount of UI elements based on a relatively small amount of data, or have a lot of derived data (something like a spreadsheet), whereas Redux has benefits for applications that need to be extremely reliable and well tested.</p>
<h3>Stray Thoughts</h3>
<ul>
<li>If you do want more discipline in MobX, make sure to use <code>useStrict</code> to require updates to use Actions</li>
<li>MobX has a nice set of <a href="https://github.com/mobxjs/mobx-react-devtools">devtools</a> that are useful if you’re opting in to using actions, and using React with MobX.</li>
<li>If this isn’t clear yet, I definitely recommend hacking around with Mobx’s low level APIs to learn more about how it works before integrating it straight into a framework</li>
<li><s>Also note that MobX 3.0 is imminent, there is a release candidate that you can play with now.</s> <strong>Update:</strong> That didn’t take long.  <a href="https://medium.com/@mweststrate/mobx-3-released-unpeeling-the-onion-ca877382f443#.mk6mdypt2">MobX 3.0 is out</a>.</li>
</ul>
<h3>More Resources</h3>
<ul>
<li>
<p>The two most helpful resources I found for conceptually understanding MobX were in-depth articles by the library’s author <a href="">Michael Westrate</a>: <a href="https://medium.com/@mweststrate/becoming-fully-reactive-an-in-depth-explanation-of-mobservable-55995262a254#.jd4hgh2zi">Becoming fully reactive: an in-depth explanation of MobX</a> on Medium and <a href="https://mobx.js.org/intro/concepts.html">Concepts &amp; Principles</a> from the MobX documentation</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>This <a href="https://twitter.com/AdamRackis/status/775706291259908096">tweet thread</a> and the linked article, are a good breakdown of the tradeoffs between MobX and Redux</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3>Subscribe</h3>
<p>Thanks for taking the time to read this post!  JavaScript development is one of the main topics of this blog, so if you enjoyed the post, please consider subscribing by using the <a href="http://feedpress.me/benmccormick">feed</a>, <a href="http://twitter.com/benmccormickorg">Twitter</a> or my <a href="http://eepurl.com/WFYon">mailing list</a>. You also might want to check out my <a href="http://benmccormick.org/2017/01/03/orthogonality-and-css-in-js/">post on Orthogonality and CSS in JS</a>.</p>
<p>[^1]: Technically this also uses class properties as well, another proposal that works well with decorators
[^2]: It’s possible any spec changes will be trivially fixable with a code mod script, but right now there is more uncertainty than I am personally comfortable with.  I’m grateful to people who are willing to take more risks here than me, they push the language forward.
[^3]: I’m talking here about what is encouraged and easy, not what is possible.  It is of course possible to mix in Redux with other solutions.
[^4]: MobX has some nice <a href="https://github.com/mobxjs/mobx-react-devtools">devtools!</a></p>
]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Ben McCormick</name>
            <email>ben@benmccormick.org</email>
            <uri>http://benmccormick.org</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Orthogonality and CSS in JS]]></title>
        <id>https://benmccormick.org/2017/01/03/orthogonality-and-css-in-js/</id>
        <link href="https://benmccormick.org/2017/01/03/orthogonality-and-css-in-js/">
        </link>
        <updated>2017-01-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the realities of the constant change in the web development world is that “best practices” are often hotly contested.  One issue that the front end community doesn’t seem to have come to a consensus on yet is how tightly to bundle JavaScript, HTML and CSS in code.  Should they be bundled and managed completely separately?  Kept in different files and imported together into JavaScript component files?  Or can we remove HTML and CSS files entirely and generate everything in JavaScript? This is a discussion that still comes up all the time in my <a href="https://twitter.com/thomasfuchs/status/810885087214637057">twitter</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/TheLarkInn/status/812089065210335232">feed</a>.</p>
<p>Many new frameworks that encourage a component based architecture (including React, Vue, and Angular2 [^1]) provide affordances for including HTML and CSS directly in JavaScript, but those solutions are not yet used universally.  Many people are still very happy keeping CSS bundled separately.  I have no idea what the <em>best</em> solution is.  But I am interested in how people talk about the problem.  One major argument I have seen from people advocating both sides is that their preferred approach encourages good “separation of concerns”.</p>
<div>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">I&#39;m moving from storing my CSS, JS and HTML in different files, to physically putting them on different drives. Keep those concerns separate</p>&mdash; Ben Lesh (@BenLesh) <a href="https://twitter.com/BenLesh/status/812092408519413761">December 23, 2016</a></blockquote>
</div>
<p>I’d like to take a deeper look at this and give some vocabulary that can hopefully help anyone working through discussions on how to manage CSS for components.  I’ll focus specifically on CSS since frameworks tend to be more agnostic to how it is blended with JS than they are about HTML, and on components since that is the main context in which people are arguing for blending of css. For this piece, I’ll consider a component to be a set of HTML, CSS, and JavaScript that combine to form a reusable piece of UI [^2].</p>
<h3>Orthogonality, Cohesion, and Coupling</h3>
<p><a href="http://amzn.to/2hNzQ0t">The Pragmatic Programmer</a>, one of the best books ever written on Software Engineering, uses the following three terms when talking about “Separation of Concerns”: orthogonality, cohesion, and coupling.</p>
<p>Orthogonality is the idea that modules should be written in a way that a change in one module should not require changes in any other module.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Two or more things are orthogonal if changes in one do not affect any of the others. In a well-designed system, the database code will be orthogonal to the user interface: you can change the interface without affecting the database, and swap databases without changing the interface.</p>
<p><strong>— The Pragmatic Programmer</strong></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Cohesion is a measure of how well the internal contents of a module relate to each other. A cohesive module is one with a single well defined purpose, where all code in the module is related to that purpose.  A less cohesive module might have multiple purposes, with pieces of code that are completely unrelated to each other.  <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/unclebobconsultingllc/">Robert C. Martin</a> describes this as each module having “a single reason to change”.</p>
<p>Coupling is a measure of how dependent different modules are on the internal workings of other modules. In a loosely coupled system, any module can be completely rewritten as long as it exposes the same public interface, without any other modules needing to change.  In a tightly coupled system, changing the internal details of one module may require changes in many other modules.</p>
<p>In the real world most systems are not purely orthogonal, and their modules are likely not 100% cohesive and uncoupled.  But striving for these goals is a good approximation of what many people mean when they talk about <em>separation of concerns</em>.</p>
<h3>Conways Law</h3>
<p><a href="http://amzn.to/2hNzQ0t">The Pragmatic Programmer</a> does touch on another application of orthogonality to software engineering:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Have you noticed how some project teams are efficient, with everyone knowing what to do and contributing fully, while the members of other teams are constantly bickering and don’t seem able to get out of each other’s way?</p>
<p>Often this is an orthogonality issue. When teams are organized with lots of overlap, members are confused about responsibilities. Every change needs a meeting of the entire team, because any one of them might be affected.</p>
<p>How do you organize teams into groups with well-defined responsibilities and minimal overlap? There’s no simple answer. It depends partly on the project and your analysis of the areas of potential change. It also depends on the people you have available. Our preference is to start by separating infrastructure from application. Each major infrastructure component (database, communications interface, middleware layer, and so on) gets its own subteam. Each obvious division of application functionality is similarly divided. Then we look at the people we have (or plan to have) and adjust the groupings accordingly.</p>
<p>You can get an informal measure of the orthogonality of a project team’s structure. Simply see how many people need to be involved in discussing each change that is requested. The larger the number, the less orthogonal the group. Clearly, an orthogonal team is more efficient.</p>
<p><strong>— The Pragmatic Programmer</strong></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The idea is that teams work more efficiently when each can work in its own areas without having to be bogged down by using another group (or individuals) code, and only interacting with those modules through a well communicated interface.  This is also known as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conway's_law">Conway’s Law</a>, which is often used disparagingly but still stands as a true observation about real life code.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>organizations which design systems … are constrained to produce designs which are copies of the communication structures of these organizations</p>
<p><strong>— Conway’s Law</strong></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Although it usually isn’t phrased quite so explicitly, I believe Conway’s law is often related to what people mean when they discuss separation of concerns in front end development.</p>
<h3>Boundaries and Interfaces between CSS and JavaScript</h3>
<p>Let’s look at 2 examples of how CSS can be structured.  We’ll use a “page view counter” as our example. The element will show the number of users who have viewed the page, and respond to click events by showing a modal with the most popular pages on the site.
First, for a more traditional example, I’ll show a <a href="http://marionettejs.com/">Marionette</a> View, with separate CSS. For a more integrated example, I’ll use a React component.</p>
<h4>Marionette</h4>
<pre><code class="language-javascript">//view-counter.js

import Mn from 'backbone.marionette';
import template from './view-counter.hbs'
import { getPageViews, showModal } from '../util/page-views';

var ViewCounter = Mn.View.extend({

  template,

  className: 'page-view-counter',

  ui:  {
    'showPageViewsModal': '.show-modal-js',
  },

  events: {
    'click @ui.showPageViewsModal': 'showPageViewsModal',
  }

  templateContext() {
      return {
        pageViews: getPageViews(),
      };
  },

  showPageViewsModal() {
    showModal();
  }

});
</code></pre>
<pre><code class="language-hbs">{{!view-counter.hbs}}

&lt;span class=&quot;page-view-counter__title&quot;&gt; Page Views: &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;page-view-counter__counter show-modal-js&quot;&gt; {{pageViews}} &lt;/span&gt;
</code></pre>
<pre><code class="language-css">//view-counter.css

.page-view-counter {
  display: flex;
}

.page-view-counter__title {
  font-weight: 700;
  padding: 3px;
}

.page-view-counter__counter {
  padding: 3px;
}
</code></pre>
<h4>React</h4>
<pre><code class="language-javascript">//view-counter.jsx
import React from 'react';
import { showModal } from '../util/page-views';

export const PageViewCounter = (props) =&gt; {
    return &lt;div style = {{display: 'flex'}}&gt;
      &lt;span style = {{
        fontWeight: 700,
        padding: '3px',
      }}&gt;
        Page Views:
      &lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span style = {{padding: '3px'}}&gt;{this.props.pageViews}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
}

</code></pre>
<p>The React and Marionette examples have set different module boundaries. In the Marionette example, we have defined 3 modules, split by code type.  Ignoring the leaky abstractions in the Marionette boundaries [^3], we can say we have 3 modules with clear singular purpose (styling, behavior,  structure) that use class names and  <code>templateContext</code> as interfaces.  The handlebars file exposes classes, which the CSS uses to style elements and the JavaScript code uses as attachment points for event handling.  The JavaScript view passes data to the template through templateContext.  In the React code we have defined a single module that exports a component as its only external interface. The module’s single purpose could be defined as “rendering a PageViewCounter”.</p>
<h3>How do we define module boundaries?</h3>
<p>If you’re excited to read which of the above examples is the <em>correct</em> module boundary definition, I’m sorry to disappoint you.  It turns out that module boundaries are more of an art than a science.  Let’s consider each of these examples by the criteria we laid out above.</p>
<p>The Marionette modules are <strong>cohesive</strong>.  Each module is single purpose, with a clear reason why it might change.  The React module is also cohesive, as it describes a single atomic component. However, it has more reasons it might change.  We might change that module because of a change in the look and feel of the site, because of a change in the expected behavior of the click event, or because we’re changing the text inside the component.</p>
<p>The Marionette modules are not quite <strong>decoupled</strong>.  While this CSS doesn’t nest selectors and we don’t have any explicit dependencies on the HTML structure, it is still written in a way that assumes <code>.page-view-counter__title</code> and <code>.page-view-counter__counter</code> will be direct children of <code>.page-view-counter</code>.  So changing the “internal details” of the Handlebars file by adding an extra element around those children would break the CSS. While the modules are not completely decoupled from each other, they don’t rely on any private details of other modules or global styles and can be used together as a reusable component.  The React module is similarly decoupled from the rest of the system, and as a single module faces no internal coupling issues.</p>
<p>Both components should be <strong>orthogonal</strong> from the rest of the system, even though the Marionette modules may be less orthogonal internally.  The question of how they meet a Conway’s law style of orthogonality depends on a team.  If your team has designers, and developers separately working on style/structure and behavior, the Marionette version may allow for more efficient division of labor, with communication centering on class based communication.  If you instead have a group of polyglot front end developers who implement mocks from designers across all 3 areas, the React version will instead present a simpler implementation that maps better to your team, with the focus on interfaces across different components.</p>
<p>In the end decisions like this are an exercise in understanding context and preferences.  What will make your team productive? You can accept the coupling of the first example in order to gain the benefits of small focused modules.  Or you can take the larger scope of the React component in exchange for keeping all information relevant to a component in one place.  Are you making single developers responsible for a set of components?  Or are they responsible for behavior generally, with design handled by someone else? Make the decisions that work for your project.</p>
<h3>More Resources</h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://amzn.to/2hNzQ0t">The Pragmatic Programmer</a> is a great book. Much of the vocabulary in this post comes from its Chapter 8, but the whole book is worth a read and is highly recommended.</li>
<li>CSS Tricks has a good look at the <a href="https://css-tricks.com/the-debate-around-do-we-even-need-css-anymore/">pros and cons of CSS in JS</a>.  I focused on theory here, but this is much more hands on about the practical concerns around this debate.</li>
</ul>
<h3>Subscribe</h3>
<p>Thanks for taking the time to read this post!  JavaScript development is one of the main topics of this blog, so if you enjoyed the post, please consider subscribing by using the <a href="http://feedpress.me/benmccormick">feed</a>, <a href="http://twitter.com/benmccormickorg">Twitter</a> or my <a href="http://eepurl.com/WFYon">mailing list</a>. You also might want to check out my <a href="http://benmccormick.org/2016/05/02/digging-into-react-choosing-component-styles/">post on choosing which component styles to use in React</a>.</p>
<p>[^1]: This is a bit of a generalization.  React provides an abstraction over HTML that replaces hand-written HTML, but doesn’t specify anything for CSS, CSS in JS solutions are simply popular in that community.  Vue and Angular both allow  CSS and HTML to share a file with JS, but CSS can still be handled separately.
[^2]: There are some distinctions about CSS in JS vs importing CSS into JS using webpack that I’m not really dealing with here.  This is a post about how to think about these decisions moreso than the specific options for bundling CSS and JS
[^3]: The root HTML element in any Marionette component is always defined implicitly in JavaScript, and Handlebars is an expressive templating language that can handle more than structure.</p>
]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Ben McCormick</name>
            <email>ben@benmccormick.org</email>
            <uri>http://benmccormick.org</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[2016 Roundup]]></title>
        <id>https://benmccormick.org/2016/12/31/2016-roundup/</id>
        <link href="https://benmccormick.org/2016/12/31/2016-roundup/">
        </link>
        <updated>2016-12-30T02:15:00Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thanks to all of you who have followed my blog this year! It was a busy year and I didn’t get as many posts out as years past, but you all have been as supportive as ever.  I’m excited about the things I’ve been able to do with the new site this month, and am looking forward to a great 2017.  But first, a look back.</p>
<h3>Most Read Posts of 2016</h3>
<p>I wrote 15 posts in 2016, down from my pace of 19 in 2015 and 25 in 2014.  Some of that was an unusually busy work year, and some of the time I normally put into the site went to the redesdign. I also sat on a few articles that didn’t turn out that great when actually written out.  But I made a good run at the end and hopefully will be writing more in 2017.  The most read posts from this site in 2016 were:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p><a href="http://benmccormick.org/2016/01/11/the-most-interesting-atom-packages-ive-found-so-far/">The Most Interesting Atom Packages I’ve found so far</a> - I started using <a href="https://atom.io/">Atom</a> as my primary text editor late in 2015.  This was my roundup of the coolest and most unique plugins I had found for Atom at that point.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="http://benmccormick.org/2016/09/19/testing-with-jest-snapshots-first-impressions/">Testing with Jest Snapshots</a> - This was my review of <a href="https://facebook.github.io/jest/">Jest</a>’s snapshot testing feature.  I found it extremely useful for testing UI components.  I also wrote about Jest again <a href="http://benmccormick.org/2016/12/10/saving-time-with-jest/">this month</a>, transcribing a talk I gave at a local meetup on <a href="http://benmccormick.org/2016/12/10/saving-time-with-jest/">How Jest can save you time</a>.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="http://benmccormick.org/2016/01/08/reusable-code-patterns/">Reusable Code Patterns</a> - This article was a high level look at the ways you can approach sharing code for 2 different use cases.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h4>Honorable Mention</h4>
<p><a href="http://benmccormick.org/2015/12/30/es6-patterns-converting-callbacks-to-promises/">ES6 Patterns: Converting Callbacks to Promises</a> - This article was technically written in 2015, but it was published during the last week of the year and thus wasn’t eligible to be included last year. However it has proven quite popular.  This was my attempt at a straightforward explanation of how to convert a callback based API to a Promise based one.</p>
<h3>Code I wrote in 2016</h3>
<p>Most of the code I wrote this year was for my work at Windsor Circle.  But I have spent some time getting this blog up and running, and anyone interested in what it takes to get a fully functioning blog running on <a href="https://github.com/gatsbyjs/gatsby">Gatsby</a> is welcome to take a look at the <a href="https://github.com/benmccormick/benmccormickorg">github repo</a>.</p>
<h3>Languages, Libraries, and Technologies I started using in 2016</h3>
<ul>
<li>
<p><a href="https://facebook.github.io/jest/">Jest</a> is a JavaScript testing library that I started using this year. It’s fantastic, and I’ve had the opportunity to <a href="http://benmccormick.org/2016/09/19/testing-with-jest-snapshots-first-impressions/">write</a> and <a href="http://benmccormick.org/2016/12/10/saving-time-with-jest/">speak</a> about it a few times already.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://github.com/gatsbyjs/gatsby">Gatsbyjs</a> now powers this blog. Gatsby is a ReactJS based static site generator, and it has been a pleasure to work with.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>My team started using <a href="https://www.docker.com/">Docker</a> this year.  It’s been a mixed bag for me personally, but I love the idea of what it provides</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3>Languages, Libraries, and Technologies I stopped using in 2016</h3>
<ul>
<li>Despite my affection for <a href="http://marionettejs.com/">Marionette</a>, I’m no longer actively using it other than in some legacy code for my work application</li>
</ul>
<h3>Languages and Libraries I used (more or less) every day in 2016</h3>
<p>JavaScript (ES6), Python, React, PostgreSQL, Backbone, lodash</p>
<h3>Languages and Libraries I want to try in 2017</h3>
<p>RxJS, Flow, VueJS, <a href="https://github.com/FormidableLabs/victory">Victory</a>, Pandas and other python data analysis libraries, Rust</p>
<h3>Blogs I started following in 2016</h3>
<p>Nothing new this year,</p>
<h3>Blogs I read every post from in 2016</h3>
<p>Rands In Repose, Stratechery, Daring Fireball,  <a href="http://Marco.org">Marco.org</a>, <a href="http://rauchg.com">rauchg.com</a>, <a href="http://purposedworking.com">purposedworking.com</a></p>
<h3>Podcasts I started listening to in 2016</h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.npr.org/podcasts/510310/npr-politics-podcast">NPR Politics</a> - Approachable and fun while still being informative, one of the best ways to follow this years election.</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="http://www.npr.org/podcasts/510313/how-i-built-this">How I Built This</a> - This has been a great new podcast on entrepreneurship</p>
<h3>Software I started using in 2016</h3>
<ul>
<li>
<p><a href="http://inbox.google.com">Google Inbox</a> + <a href="http://airmailapp.com/">Airmail</a> for email: I’m not sure I’m ever going to be happy with an email client, but I’m currently using the combo of Google Inbox on iOS and Airmail on MacOS.  Post <a href="https://www.mailboxapp.com/">Mailbox</a>, Inbox is my favorite iOS mail app.  On desktop though I like to have universal inbox and tight integration with the rest of the operating system, so I use Airmail, which is less bad than the rest of the MacOS mail clients I’ve tried</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="http://copiedapp.com/">Copied</a>: Copied is a clipboard manager for MacOS (and sort of iOS).  It’s been great to be able to keep multiple things in the clipboard at once, and be able to go back and get something if I blow it away.  I’m not a power user.  I haven’t really figured out a reason to use their lists features, or their iOS client, but it has been great for the limited things I use it for.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://caskroom.github.io/">Homebrew Cask</a>: I’ve used homebrew for a while.  But being able to install GUI apps as easily as command line apps has been pretty amazing.  If you are on OSX and don’t use homebrew to install pretty much everything, you’re missing out.  Of course the real effect is that it makes me dread and hate the Mac App Store even more.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/services/mobile/">The New York Times App</a>: Ok this is a bit of a cheat since this is more about content than software, but if you’re out of touch on what is going on in the world, there’s never been a better time to support a good source of news and reporting, whichever outlet is your preference.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3>Software I stopped using in 2016</h3>
<p>Nothing I’m aware of, though I am currently checking out <a href="http://www.bear-writer.com/">Bear</a> and <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/annotate-capture-and-share/id918207447?mt=12">Annotate</a> as potential replacements for Evernote and Skitch.</p>
<h3>Software I used (nearly) every day in 2016</h3>
<p>MacOS/iOS, Google Search, Chrome/Safari, Google Inbox/Airmail, Twitter/Tweetbot, Feedbin/Reeder, Instapaper, iMessage, Slack, Trello, 1Password, Atom/Vim, iTerm, Fish Shell, tmux, Bitbucket, Fantastical, Spotify, Evernote, Skitch, Dash</p>
]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Ben McCormick</name>
            <email>ben@benmccormick.org</email>
            <uri>http://benmccormick.org</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[What are Higher Order Components?]]></title>
        <id>https://benmccormick.org/2016/12/14/what-are-higher-order-components/</id>
        <link href="https://benmccormick.org/2016/12/14/what-are-higher-order-components/">
        </link>
        <updated>2016-12-14T14:30:00Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you spend much time at all reading through articles and documentation around React, you’re likely to run into the term “Higher Order component”, often abbreviated HoC.  Since it is often used without context in React discussions, and is not a particularly intuitive term for many (most?) developers, I thought it was worth publishing a quick and simple explanation of what Higher Order Components are.</p>
<p>Higher Order Components are functions that take a React Component, and return a React Component.  The “higher order” phrasing is borrowed from the term “higher order function”, a more widely used term in Mathematics and Computer Science that refers to a function that either takes one or more functions as an argument, returns a function, or does both.  Since React Components can be thought of as functions that take data and return ui elements, the naming and usage make sense.  Let’s look at an example of a higher order component.</p>
<pre><code class="language-javascript">const ExtraPropsComponent = (WrappedComponent, componentType) =&gt; {
  return class ExtraPropsChild extends React.Component {
    render() {
      let props = Object.assign({}, this.props, {
        importantFunction: () =&gt; 'foo',
        componentType,
      });
      return &lt;WrappedComponent {...props}/&gt;
    }
  }
}
</code></pre>
<p>This is a pretty basic HoC that takes a component and returns a new version of that component that will always be passed 2 extra props <code>importantFunction</code> and <code>componentType</code>. One is statically generated in this case, but the other is dynamically passed in when the component is generated.  The ability to pass dynamic content in when defining the component is one of the key wins of HoCs in the real world.  For instance, this is how Redux’s <a href="https://github.com/reactjs/react-redux/blob/master/docs/api.md#connectmapstatetoprops-mapdispatchtoprops-mergeprops-options">connect</a> function works.</p>
<p>Note that this is different from a normal React Component that renders a subcomponent passed as an argument like this:</p>
<pre><code class="language-javascript">let componentType = '???';
class ExtraPropsComponent extends React.Component
  render() {
      let { ChildComponent } = this.props;
      let props = Object.assign({}, this.props, {
        importantFunction: () =&gt; 'foo',
        componentType,
      });
      delete props.ChildComponent;

      return &lt;ChildComponent {...props} /&gt;;
  }
}
</code></pre>
<p>These 2 examples are roughly equivalent for this case, but accomplish things in different ways.  The HoC is a function that takes a component and data when it is created and generates another component.  The normal component example is a component that takes a component as a property and accesses a variable that is in its scope at creation time to generate the element tree that it renders.  The HoC is more flexible as you could theoretically create multiple versions of a component using the single HoC.</p>
<pre><code class="language-javascript">
const FancyButton = ExtraPropsComponent(Button, 'fancy');
const CrazyButton = ExtraPropsComponent(Button, 'crazy');
const BoringButton = ExtraPropsComponent(Button, 'boring');
</code></pre>
<p>For the equivalent functionality without using an HoC, you would have to define the whole component for each case.</p>
<h3>Higher Order Components in the real world</h3>
<p>I’ve already mentioned connect from <a href="https://github.com/reactjs/react-redux">react-redux</a> as an example of a higher order component.  Other popular libraries that use HoC as part of their APIs include:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://formidable.com/open-source/radium/">Radium</a>: a library for inline styles in React that uses a higher order component to transform in-line styles added to a component into a more robust-css like system</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/ReactTraining/react-router">React Router</a>: a routing library for React that uses <code>withRouter</code> a HoC that injects access to the router into components that it wraps</li>
<li><a href="https://facebook.github.io/relay/">Relay</a>: Facebook’s library for connecting to GraphQL APIs includes Relay.Container, a HoC that allows developers to declare the data requirements for a component</li>
</ul>
<h3>More Resources</h3>
<ul>
<li>This was intentionally a very high level look at Higher Order Components.  If you want to go deeper, <a href="https://medium.com/@franleplant/react-higher-order-components-in-depth-cf9032ee6c3e#.yhbug3ohe">this medium article</a> is a great deep dive into all the use cases they allow.</li>
<li>If you’re interested in using HoCs in your own code base, <a href="https://github.com/acdlite/recompose">recompose</a> is a utility library for making the syntax around defining and using them painless</li>
</ul>
<h3>Subscribe</h3>
<p>Thanks for taking the time to read this post!  JavaScript development is one of the main topics of this blog, so if you enjoyed the post, please consider subscribing by using the <a href="http://feedpress.me/benmccormick">feed</a>, <a href="http://twitter.com/benmccormickorg">Twitter</a> or my <a href="http://eepurl.com/WFYon">mailing list</a>. You also might want to check out the my post from earlier this year on <a href="http://benmccormick.org/2016/05/02/digging-into-react-choosing-component-styles/">choosing a React component syntax</a>.</p>
]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Ben McCormick</name>
            <email>ben@benmccormick.org</email>
            <uri>http://benmccormick.org</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Readable code: Know your audience ]]></title>
        <id>https://benmccormick.org/2016/12/11/readable-code-audience/</id>
        <link href="https://benmccormick.org/2016/12/11/readable-code-audience/">
        </link>
        <updated>2016-12-12T04:00:00Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A coworker asked me last week if there was a better way to write the following python code:</p>
<pre><code class="language-python">self.custom_attributes = {
  x.split(':')[0]: x.split(':')[1]
  for x in a.split(',')
}
</code></pre>
<p>I semi-jokingly replied that there were 3 better ways:</p>
<h5>For people who like comprehensions</h5>
<pre><code class="language-python">self.custom_attributes = {
  key: value
  for [key, value] in [entry.split(':') for entry in a.split(',')]
}
</code></pre>
<h5>For people who like functions</h5>
<pre><code class="language-python">def build_obj(acc, val):
   [key, value] = val.split(':')
   acc[key] = value
   return acc
self.custom_attributes = reduce(build_obj, a.split(','), {})
</code></pre>
<h4>For people who like other folks to be able to read their code</h4>
<pre><code class="language-python"># create a hash of custom attributes
self.custom_attributes = {}
# get the entries from splitting the input string
entries = a.split(',')
# for each entry split the key value pairs and add them to the hash
for entry in entries:
   [key, value] = entry.split(':')
   self.custom_attributes[key] = value
</code></pre>
<p>The joke of course is that it doesn’t really matter what the author of the code considers the best way to write it.  Like writing an essay or persuasive speech, it is much more important to consider the audience, and what style will work best for them.  Most code will eventually be read by other people, even if that is simply a future version of the original author who has been stripped of context by time [^1].</p>
<p>If my coworker is confident that his code will be read in the future by confident Python programmers who understand object comprehensions, then he could go with the first example, with its heavy use of python idioms.  If he thought it was more likely that somebody like me who is used to JavaScript idioms, he might consider the less idiomatic python from the second example that matched his teammates.  If he didn’t know who would read the code in the future, he might go with the more explicit and difficult to misinterpret version 3, and possibly tuck it away within a named function so that the main code flow could remain uninterrupted.</p>
<pre><code class="language-python">self.custom_attributes = parse_entry_string(a)

# ... elsewhere ...

def parse_entry_string (entry_string):
    attributes = {}
    # get the entries from splitting the input string
    entries = a.split(',')
    # for each entry split the key value pairs and add them to the hash
    for entry in entries:
       [key, value] = entry.split(':')[0:2]
       attributes[key] = value
    return attributes
</code></pre>
<p>Of course once the functionality is separated out into a function, it matters a lot less how it is implemented since the only time somebody will need to read it is when they are interested in that specific functionality and can invest the time to understand the code.  The well named function replaces the need for understanding everything when people browse through the code.  This is extremely important in larger code bases, since data often flows through many lines of code.  The more of it that can be usefully (and accurately) abstracted away for a reader, the easier the code base is to debug.</p>
<p>So quick tip version:</p>
<ol>
<li>Think about the audience of the code you’re writing</li>
<li>Naming functions well limits the needs to make implementation details readable for everybody. It can also make your program flow easier to follow.</li>
</ol>
<h3>Subscribe</h3>
<p>Thanks for taking the time to read this post!  Software development is one of the main topics of this blog, so if you enjoyed the post, please consider subscribing by using the <a href="http://feedpress.me/benmccormick">feed</a>, <a href="http://twitter.com/benmccormickorg">Twitter</a> or my <a href="http://eepurl.com/WFYon">mailing list</a>. You also might want to check out the my post from last year on <a href="http://benmccormick.org/2016/01/25/staying-productive/">staying productive</a>.</p>
<p>[^1]: In my experience, it usually only takes about a week for me to look back at my old code and wonder what maniac wrote it and what he could have possibly been thinking</p>
]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Ben McCormick</name>
            <email>ben@benmccormick.org</email>
            <uri>http://benmccormick.org</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Saving Time With Jest: Meetup Summary]]></title>
        <id>https://benmccormick.org/2016/12/10/saving-time-with-jest/</id>
        <link href="https://benmccormick.org/2016/12/10/saving-time-with-jest/">
        </link>
        <updated>2016-12-10T05:15:00Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This week I gave a talk at the brand new Triangle ReactJS meetup group on how <a href="https://facebook.github.io/jest/">Jest</a> can save developers time.  I was asked afterwards to share the content online for those who missed it.  My talk was mostly demos and wasn’t recorded, so there unfortunately isn’t much to share, but I thought I could write out the basic ideas behind the talk, and share them here.</p>
<h3>What is Jest</h3>
<p>Jest is a JavaScript testing framework built by Facebook to address their internal problems testing JavaScript code.  It was open-sourced in 2014, but unlike Facebook’s other recent high profile JavaScript OSS projects like React, Flux, Relay and GraphQL, it failed to develop much traction in the community and mostly stagnated for 2 years.  That changed in early 2016 when 2 Facebook developers, <a href="https://twitter.com/cpojer">Christoph Pojer</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/abramov_dmitrii">Dmitrii Abramov</a> began working on improving the project. Over the past year they’ve brought massive improvements to the developer experience of using Jest.</p>
<p>At a more practical level Jest is a test runner with a built in assertion library and support for code coverage, babel transpilation, and module mocking.  It began as a wrapper around <a href="https://jasmine.github.io/">Jasmine</a>, an older JavaScript testing library, but has since replaced parts of Jasmine with replacement functionality, while retaining backwards compatibility.</p>
<h3>How Can Jest Save Me Time?</h3>
<p>Jest saves developers  time in 4 main ways:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Setup</strong> - Jest is simple to configure</li>
<li><strong>Writing Tests</strong> - Jest provides a method for writing simple UI tests, and makes it easy to port over existing tests</li>
<li><strong>Running Tests</strong> - Jest runs tests in parallel, doesn’t require a browser, and only runs the tests that are affected by the current code changes</li>
<li><strong>Fixing Tests</strong> - Jest gives great error messages, helps you find the failing code, and has other smaller UX features that make it easy to debug your failing tests quickly.</li>
</ol>
<div>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Tonight <a href="https://twitter.com/ben336">@ben336</a> speaks about using <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/jest?src=hash">#jest</a> with <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/reactjs?src=hash">#reactjs</a> for your testing needs <a href="https://twitter.com/nestraleigh">@nestraleigh</a> <a href="https://t.co/CAV8wZUwFw">pic.twitter.com/CAV8wZUwFw</a></p>&mdash; Tracy Lee | ladyleet (@ladyleet) <a href="https://twitter.com/ladyleet/status/806655476515618822">December 8, 2016</a></blockquote>
</div>
<h3>Setup</h3>
<p>Setting up Jest is extremely straightforward. Here’s a <code>Hello World</code> React Project</p>
<pre><code class="language-json">//package.json
{
  &quot;name&quot;: &quot;simple_example&quot;,
  &quot;version&quot;: &quot;1.0.0&quot;,
  &quot;description&quot;: &quot;A minimal jest testing example&quot;,
  &quot;scripts&quot;: {
    &quot;test&quot;: &quot;jest&quot;
  },
  &quot;dependencies&quot;: {
    &quot;react&quot;: &quot;^15.4.1&quot;
  },
  &quot;devDependencies&quot;: {
    &quot;babel-jest&quot;: &quot;^17.0.2&quot;,
    &quot;babel-preset-es2015&quot;: &quot;^6.18.0&quot;,
    &quot;babel-preset-react&quot;: &quot;^6.16.0&quot;,
    &quot;jest&quot;: &quot;^17.0.3&quot;,
    &quot;react-test-renderer&quot;: &quot;^15.4.1&quot;
  }
}
</code></pre>
<p>In package.json we have 4 dependencies that are part of a normal React project setup, <code>react</code>, the 2 babel presets for using <a href="http://benmccormick.org/2015/09/14/es5-es6-es2016-es-next-whats-going-on-with-javascript-versioning/">es2015</a> syntax, and <code>react-test-renderer</code>, which is a react addon for rendering react for testing, similar to how <code>react-dom</code> renders components for the browser.  We then add <code>jest</code> and <code>babel-jest</code>.  <code>jest</code> provides the test runner, assertions API, mocking capabilities, and cli.  <code>babel-jest</code> is a drop-in dependency that lets Jest integrate with Babel.  Neither require any additional configuration in the normal case. Lets say the rest of our project looks like this:</p>
<pre><code class="language-txt">├── __tests__
│   └── simple-component.spec.js
├── package.json
└── simple-component.js
</code></pre>
<pre><code class="language-javascript">// simple-component.js
import React from 'react';

export const SimpleComponent = () =&gt; &lt;div&gt;
    Hello World
&lt;/div&gt;;
</code></pre>
<pre><code class="language-javascript">// __tests__/simple-component.spec.js
import React from 'react';
import renderer from 'react-test-renderer';
import {SimpleComponent} from '../simple-component';

it('shows Hello World', () =&gt; {
  const component = renderer.create( &lt;SimpleComponent/&gt;);
  let componentJSON = component.toJSON();
  expect(componentJSON.children[0]).toBe('Hello World');
});
</code></pre>
<p>Given this project, we only have to run</p>
<pre><code>yarn # or npm install
jest
</code></pre>
<p>and jest will automatically find our test file and run the test.</p>
<img src="http://benmccormick.org/posts/images/jest-hello-world.gif" class="full-width" alt ="gif of running jest">
<h3>Writing Tests</h3>
<p>Jest provides Snapshot Tests, which are a quick way of writing tests to catch changes in the rendered output of a UI component (or any other serializable content).  <a href="http://benmccormick.org/2016/09/19/testing-with-jest-snapshots-first-impressions/">I’ve written about Snapshot testing before</a>, so I won’t go into depth here.  But snapshot tests are significantly faster to write than traditional assertion based tests, and for the write type of code can provide greater or equal benefit.  This is one area where technically Jest may not save you time.  Instead it may take your team to a place where you’re actually willing to write tests for your UI components for the first time.</p>
<p>There are also a great set of codemods for Jest. <a href="https://github.com/skovhus/jest-codemods">jest-codemods</a> can help you take your existing suite of tests from Mocha, Ava, or tape and translate it over to Jest automatically.  Of course if you were using Jasmine previously, your tests can be migrated without changes. So Jest saves you time by not requiring you to rewrite any tests.</p>
<h3>Running Tests</h3>
<p>Jest runs tests fast by default.  While I’ve seen from comments on my last Jest post and elsewhere that some people may have been able to optimize mocha or AVA to be fast enough that switching to Jest was a downgrade, for most people Jest is going to be faster than whatever they may have been using before.  This is true because of performance reasons (tests run in parallel, and mock out timers to avoid unnecessary waiting), but also because of UX decisions.  Jest is able to use git and node’s modules system to detect what files have changed since the last commit, and which tests are affected by that.  Because of that, it is able to optionally run only the tests that might have changed on each run (<code>jest -o</code>).  Since it is usually able to run tests fast as a result (since it only runs a few at a time), Jest also is able to have an awesome watch mode (<code>jest --watch</code>).  In watch mode, tests rerun as files change, and there are options to target specific tests, run all tests, or fix snapshots as you go.</p>
<img src="http://benmccormick.org/posts/images/jest-watch.gif" class="full-width" alt ="gif of running jest --watch">
<h3>Fixing Tests</h3>
<p>Jest provides 4 main conveniences for fixing tests</p>
<ol>
<li>Error messages have clear formatted diffs, making it easy to know the difference between what was received and expected</li>
<li>Error messages have a clear traceback to the line that failed, either the assertion in the test file, or the exception in the source file</li>
<li>Even though tests run in parallel, Jest makes sure that any console output from the test is placed in line with the test output, making it easy to debug with quick console messages</li>
<li>When running Jest multiple times, Jest runs the tests that failed in the previous run prior to other tests, leading to a faster feedback loop even when not using watch mode</li>
</ol>
<img src="http://benmccormick.org/posts/images/jest-error.png" class="full-width" alt ="gif of running jest --watch">
<h3>More Resources</h3>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Another speakup at Wednesday’s meetup has a Jest related blog post out this week.  Nate Hunzaker blogged about <a href="https://www.viget.com/articles/acceptance-testing-react-apps-with-jest-and-nightmare">using Jest with Nightmare.js for acceptance tests</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>If you live in the Triangle area (thats Raleigh/Durham, North Carolina to the rest of the world) make sure to check out the <a href="http://www.meetup.com/trianglereact/">Triangle React meetup</a>.  The plan as I understand it is to do events once a month, alternating project nights and talks.  I believe <a href="https://twitter.com/ladyleet">Tracy</a> is looking for more speakers too, so hit her up if you’re interested.  This time 4 of us spoke for 15-20 minutes, so it isn’t as much preparation as other events where you’re the only speaker.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3>Subscribe</h3>
<p>Thanks for taking the time to read this post!  JavaScript development is one of the main topics of this blog, so if you enjoyed the post, please consider subscribing by using the <a href="http://feedpress.me/benmccormick">feed</a>, <a href="http://twitter.com/benmccormickorg">Twitter</a> or my <a href="http://eepurl.com/WFYon">mailing list</a>. If you’re excited about Jest, you also might want to check out my <a href="http://benmccormick.org/2016/09/19/testing-with-jest-snapshots-first-impressions/">post on Jest Snapshots</a>.</p>
]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Ben McCormick</name>
            <email>ben@benmccormick.org</email>
            <uri>http://benmccormick.org</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[A whole new site]]></title>
        <id>https://benmccormick.org/2016/12/02/whole-new-site/</id>
        <link href="https://benmccormick.org/2016/12/02/whole-new-site/">
        </link>
        <updated>2016-12-02T16:00:00Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After 2.5 years of stability, this week I moved <a href="http://benmccormick.org">benmccormick.org</a> to a new platform and overhauled the look and feel. Although most readers have seen the site remain relatively stable, this is actually the 5th major revision of the site since it was first created, so this seems like a good time for a quick trip down memory lane.</p>
<p>I first started it as a Django app, wanting to challenge myself to build a blog.  That was so short-lived that the way-back machine never even registered it, and I don’t have any evidence that it ever existed (thankfully).  In December 2012, I moved the blog over to <a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</a> a static site generator based on Ruby.  I started out using a very nice stock template:</p>
<img src="http://benmccormick.org/posts/images/oldsite1.png" class="full-width">
<p>and then shortly switched to a version that I mostly did myself based off of the default octopress theme.  This was one of my first attempts to design anything from scratch, and was not particularly pretty:</p>
<img src="http://benmccormick.org/posts/images/oldsite2.png" class="full-width">
<p>I enjoyed Octopress, but spent a lot of time messing around with it (and struggling through the unfamiliar ruby ecosystem), and not a lot of time writing.  So in the spring of 2014 I decided I wanted to switch to a blogging platform where I could write, rather than messing with code.  So I moved my blog to <a href="https://ghost.org/">Ghost</a>, lightly modified a public theme, and began writing about Vim.  It was around this time (2 years and 40 articles in) that I began to attract more readers, and also began to focus more on higher quality technical articles:</p>
<img src="http://benmccormick.org/posts/images/oldsite3.png" class="full-width">
<p>About a year after that I re-introduced some color to the blog after a prolonged absence. The black and white sidebar was traded for a colorful green, and a I began using a mix of blue and red for text emphasis. I also began to focus on making it more clear how to subscribe to the blog, and highlighted the more popular content:</p>
<img src="http://benmccormick.org/posts/images/oldsite4.png" class="full-width">
<p>Ghost was a great blogging platform, but this fall I decided it was time to move off of it.  I was interested in trying some things that didn’t fit into the platform’s more structured approach, and wanted to move the blog to a place where it was no longer losing me money to run.  So I decided to take another look at the static site generator landscape. I looked through the top 12 or so options on <a href="https://www.staticgen.com/">StaticGen</a> and <a href="https://github.com/gatsbyjs/gatsby">Gatsby</a> quickly stood out.  It uses concepts I’m extremely comfortable with (built with React and Webpack!), produces fast server-rendered SPA style sites, and dictates almost nothing about how the site is built.</p>
<p>The site is now built with Gatsby and hosted on Github pages.  I’ve ditched the noisy green sidebar in favor of a simpler text-focused experience and added a small ad at the top of the page to offset some of the costs associated with the blog.  I’m planning on iterating on the design (better organizing and exposing older content, making it simpler to subscribe to the blog, and making it easier for me to add rich content/code examples to posts without relying on 3rd party services), but for right now I’m excited to get back to focusing on writing.</p>
<img src="http://benmccormick.org/posts/images/current_site.png" class="full-width">
<p>Like all software, as this blog has evolved, I’m sure not all of the progress has been forward.  If you see any issues with the new site, feedback and bugfixes are welcome.  Feel free to hit me up on <a href="https://twitter.com/ben336">twitter</a>, comment on this post, or open an issue on the site’s <a href="https://github.com/benmccormick/benmccormickorg/issues">github repo</a>.  Thank you to everyone who has read and supported this site over the past several years.</p>
<h3>More Resources</h3>
<ul>
<li>If you’re interested in <a href="https://github.com/gatsbyjs/gatsby">Gatsby</a> this post on <a href="https://blog.scottnonnenberg.com/practical-gatsby-js/">Practical Gatsby.js</a> by Scott Nonnenberg is excellent.  Its not a how-to, but more of a series of examples of how he deviated from the base Gatsby blog (and why).  I found it really helpful when brainstorming ideas for this site.</li>
</ul>
<h3>Subscribe</h3>
<p>Thanks for taking the time to read this post!  I’m going to be ramping up posts again this winter, so if you have enjoyed my posts, please consider subscribing by using the <a href="http://benmccormick.org/rss/">feed</a>, <a href="http://twitter.com/benmccormickorg">Twitter</a> or my <a href="http://eepurl.com/WFYon">mailing list</a>. You also might want to check out my <a href="http://benmccormick.org/2016/05/02/digging-into-react-choosing-component-styles/">post on choosing which component styles to use in React</a>.</p>
]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Ben McCormick</name>
            <email>ben@benmccormick.org</email>
            <uri>http://benmccormick.org</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Testing with Jest Snapshots: First Impressions]]></title>
        <id>https://benmccormick.org/2016/09/19/testing-with-jest-snapshots-first-impressions/</id>
        <link href="https://benmccormick.org/2016/09/19/testing-with-jest-snapshots-first-impressions/">
        </link>
        <updated>2016-09-19T12:41:00Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Over the past 6 months my team at work has been slowly transitioning a large Backbone application to React.  One of the main goals of the transition has been to build out unit tests as we transition components.  As part of that we switched from using Karma to using Jest for managing our tests.</p>
<p>Our new setup with Jest has several advantages over our previous setup. All Jest tests run through node using a fake DOM implementation.  We don’t need to start up a browser so tests are faster and less flaky [^1].  Jest makes it possible to mock all modules by default [^2], which works well for us since our code base currently contains a large amount of code that is difficult to test for one reason or another.  Jest provides great integration with Babel, which is helpful since all of our Backbone and React code uses ES6 that we transpile for the browser.  Finally Jest provides a wonderful watch mode that runs only the tests that are relevant to the changes you’ve made and makes it easy to see the result.</p>
<p>About a month ago, Jest debuted a new feature: Snapshot testing.  It works a bit differently than a normal unit test.  Instead of executing some code and comparing the output against a value provided by a developer, the first time a test is run, the output passed into the test is saved to a “snapshot file”.  Then when the test is run in the future, the output is compared to the snapshot file.  If the output matches the file, the test passes, if the output is different then the file, the test fails and Jest prints a diff.  We’ve been using Jest snapshots for a few weeks now and I wanted to share my initial impressions.</p>
<h3>What is it like to use a snapshot test ?</h3>
<p>The process for snapshot testing is a bit different than normal tests.  Most snapshot tests look fairly simple.  Something like this example from the <a href="https://github.com/facebook/jest/tree/master/examples/snapshot">Jest repository</a>:</p>
<pre><code class="language-javascript">// Link.react.js
// Copyright 2004-present Facebook. All Rights Reserved.

import React from 'react';

const STATUS = {
  NORMAL: 'normal',
  HOVERED: 'hovered',
};

export default class Link extends React.Component {

  constructor() {
    super();

    this._onMouseEnter = this._onMouseEnter.bind(this);
    this._onMouseLeave = this._onMouseLeave.bind(this);

    this.state = {
      class: STATUS.NORMAL,
    };
  }

  _onMouseEnter() {
    this.setState({class: STATUS.HOVERED});
  }

  _onMouseLeave() {
    this.setState({class: STATUS.NORMAL});
  }

  render() {
    return (
      &lt;a
        className={this.state.class}
        href={this.props.page || '#'}
        onMouseEnter={this._onMouseEnter}
        onMouseLeave={this._onMouseLeave}&gt;
        {this.props.children}
      &lt;/a&gt;
    );
  }

}

// Link.react-test.js  (partial)
// Copyright 2004-present Facebook. All Rights Reserved.
/* eslint-disable no-unused-vars */

'use strict'

import React from 'react';
import Link from '../Link.react';
import renderer from 'react-test-renderer';

it('renders correctly', () =&gt; {
  const tree = renderer.create(
    &lt;Link page=&quot;http://www.facebook.com&quot;&gt;Facebook&lt;/Link&gt;
  ).toJSON();
  expect(tree).toMatchSnapshot();
});

</code></pre>
<p>The first time the test is run, a snapshot file is produced.  In this case, running the previous test produces a snapshot file that looks like this:</p>
<pre><code class="language-javascript">// Link.react-test.js.snap  (partial)
exports[`test renders correctly 1`] = `
&lt;a
  className=&quot;normal&quot;
  href=&quot;http://www.facebook.com&quot;
  onMouseEnter={[Function bound _onMouseEnter]}
  onMouseLeave={[Function bound _onMouseLeave]}&gt;
  Facebook
&lt;/a&gt;
`;
</code></pre>
<p>This gives us a baseline for what we expect the UI to look like.  The snapshot is generated in a folder in your <code>__tests__</code> directory, so that it can be checked into source control.</p>
<p>The next time a test is run, if nothing has changed, the test passes.  However, if we change something (let’s say we add a class), the test fails and shows us a diff.</p>
<pre><code class="language-javascript">// updated link render method

render() {
  return (
    &lt;a
      className={`link-item ${this.state.class}`}
      href={this.props.page || '#'}
      onMouseEnter={this._onMouseEnter}
      onMouseLeave={this._onMouseLeave}&gt;
      {this.props.children}
    &lt;/a&gt;
  );
}
</code></pre>
<pre><code class="language-diff">
# jest output

FAIL  __tests__/Link.react-test.js
 ✕ renders correctly (16ms)

● renders correctly

    Received value does not match the stored snapshot 1.

    - Snapshot
    + Received

      &lt;a
-       className=&quot;normal&quot;
+       className=&quot;link-item normal&quot;
        href=&quot;http://www.facebook.com&quot;
        onMouseEnter={[Function bound _onMouseEnter]}
        onMouseLeave={[Function bound _onMouseLeave]}&gt;
        Facebook
      &lt;/a&gt;

      at Object.&lt;anonymous&gt; (__tests__/Link.react-test.js:14:16)
</code></pre>
<p>We can then choose to accept this change by running <code>jest -u</code> to update the snapshot, or update our code to fix the regression.  If we update the snapshot file, the test will start passing again.</p>
<h3>Snapshot tests are a complement for conventional tests not a replacement</h3>
<p>The first thing that became clear to me while using snapshot testing is that they’re not for everything.  They are optimized for a different case than normal assertion-based tests.</p>
<p>Classic assertion based tests are perfect for testing clearly defined behavior that is expected to remain relatively stable.</p>
<p>Snapshot tests are great for testing less clearly defined behavior that may change often.</p>
<p>Snapshot testing is perfect for things that in the past would have raised concern for “overly brittle” tests that slow development teams down.  The classic example of this (and the main focus of discussion around Jest snapshots so far) is UI testing.</p>
<p>UI components often change in small and trivial ways.  Copy is changed, whitespace is added, a border color is modified. Generally this means that developers have to choose between detailed tests that catch any regression but require constant updates, or less detailed tests that focus on core behaviors but miss smaller regressions.</p>
<p>Snapshot tests provide a new way of approaching these problems in unit tests.  Because they are easy to write and effortless to update, and provide a clear view of what changed after each update, whether it is major or minor.</p>
<p>This isn’t without any disadvantage. Snapshot tests preserve a starting point, but don’t give any indication of developer intent to future developers.  Like any other test, if the initial snapshot passes with bugs, or doesn’t capture the full range of cases, the test won’t adequately cover those behaviors.  But unlike traditional tests, snapshot tests don’t provide specific guidance for what the original developer expected beyond the “actual behavior”.  If there are multiple sub-behaviors that interact to produce output, its not clear which of those are essential, and which are incidental.  That’s not something you want for your critical application logic, especially complicated logic with many subtle cases.  But for UI components and other application elements that are likely to change a lot over time, this is a good set of tradeoffs.</p>
<h3>Snapshot tests are more useful with a healthy code review process</h3>
<p>I’ve pointed out several times now that snapshot tests are easy to update.  One of the downsides of the current design is that they can be almost too easy to update.  When a snapshot test fails, you have the option of modifying the output so that the test passes again, or updating the snapshot to reflect the new output.  Unfortunately, Jest currently provides no granularity for this updating.  Running <code>jest -u</code> to update the snapshots will update all snapshots.  So if  a single change causes many snapshots to break, it can be easy to accidentally update all of them, and possibly difficult to work through the whole diff to find changes.</p>
<p>A robust code review process minimizes these problems.  Because snapshots are checked into source, the diffs in the snapshots are checked into source control.  Viewing diffs in a dedicated code review tool like Github, Bitbucket or Gitlab, it’s easier to see exactly what changed over many files than it might be when updating snapshots from the command line, and if you update a snapshot multiple times in a single branch, you can see the net effect on the snapshot through source control diffs better than you can through Jest.</p>
<h3>Snapshot tests work well with auto-mocking</h3>
<p>Auto-mocking has been one of Jest’s more controversial features.  Prior to version 15, Jest mocked every module used in tests by default.  To run the actual module code, it was necessary to manually unmock each module used or change Jest configurations.  Though it is now disabled by default, auto-mocking actually works very well with snapshot tests.  One problem with tests that rely on generating DOM in React is the fact that most components of any complexity are actually made up of smaller components, that often use external functions with complex logic to determine what to show.  If we fully render everything, changing any of those pieces can break tests for many components, moving us away from the concept of a “unit test”.  If we mock child components and helper functions and then test them individually though, we can focus our tests to only change based on the logic of the individual component being tested.  This is incredibly easy with Jest, and especially helpful in large code bases that don’t have complete test coverage.  Auto-mocking is considered an “advanced feature” of Jest, but it’s not hard to use.  Most mocked modules produce something non-harmful by default, and when its necessary to override, its not difficult to produce something meaningful without getting too involved.  Just add a file with the same name as the file to be mocked into a <code>__mocks__</code> folder in that directory, and give the mocked module the same interface as the mocked component.  You can either write it from scratch or use <a href="http://facebook.github.io/jest/docs/api.html#jest-genmockfrommodule-modulename">jest.genMockFromModule</a> as a starting place.</p>
<h3>Summary</h3>
<p>I’m impressed by Jest snapshots.  When combined with React, they’re providing my first non-frustrating experience unit testing UI components.  I’m excited to use them more going forward, and will be interested to see how they evolve from here.</p>
<hr>
<h3>Extra: A few miscellaneous Jest Thoughts</h3>
<ul>
<li>The UI output from Jest 15 tests is the best I’ve ever seen from a testing framework.  Aside from the nice diffs on snapshots, they do a good job explaining how output differed from expectations in assertion based tests, and communicating context for test failures, warnings and logging messages.  They also give great guidance when making configuration changes:</li>
</ul>
<div style="display:flex; justify-content:center">
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr"><a href="https://twitter.com/cpojer">@cpojer</a> This is lovely, thank you! <a href="https://t.co/CX1v11CAVc">pic.twitter.com/CX1v11CAVc</a></p>&mdash; Ben McCormick (@ben336) <a href="https://twitter.com/ben336/status/772906536154894336">September 5, 2016</a></blockquote>
</div>
<ul>
<li>
<p>I’ve also been super impressed with Jest’s watch mode in Jest 15.  <code>--watch</code> makes it easy to focus on a few files or run tests on all files, and stays up to date as you change code.  If you haven’t worked with Jest in a while, the developer experience alone makes it worth trying out.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>One potential future annoyance with snapshot tests:  The snapshot format can’t be iterated on without breaking all current tests.  Make sure not to mix functional changes with Jest updates!</p>
</li>
</ul>
<div style="display:flex; justify-content:center">
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-cards="hidden" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">We&#39;ll update the snapshot format sometimes in minor/major releases. When updating Jest, please update snapshots<br><br>See <a href="https://t.co/gPE63dMz8P">https://t.co/gPE63dMz8P</a></p>&mdash; Christoph Pojer (@cpojer) <a href="https://twitter.com/cpojer/status/776623521069805568">September 16, 2016</a></blockquote>
</div>
<h3>More Resources</h3>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Randy Coulman has a <a href="http://randycoulman.com/blog/2016/09/06/snapshot-testing-use-with-care/">nice article</a> on some of the reasons to be careful about embracing snapshot testing.  He makes good points about the requirement of human involvement in verifying a change in time-crunched situations and also the potential value of snapshot tests for legacy code.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>My team uses a mix of <a href="https://github.com/airbnb/enzyme">enzyme</a> and snapshot tests for unit testing React Components.  <a href="https://github.com/trayio/enzyme-to-json?utm_content=buffer6b78b&amp;utm_medium=social&amp;utm_source=twitter.com&amp;utm_campaign=buffer">This repo</a> combines them, allowing you to use enzyme to generate the snapshot output to diff against rather than the renderer provided by Jest. I personally haven’t felt the need to integrate these two tools, but if your team uses enzyme and wants consistency/fewer (used) dependencies, this could be a cool option.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Finally here’s <a href="https://blog.grommet.io/post/2016/09/01/how-we-landed-on-jest-snapshot-testing-for-javascript">another article</a> on how Snapshot testing convinced one team to migrate to Jest from Tape</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3>Subscribe</h3>
<p>Thanks for taking the time to read this post!  JavaScript development is one of the main topics of this blog, so if you enjoyed the post, please consider subscribing by using the <a href="http://feedpress.me/benmccormick">feed</a>, <a href="http://twitter.com/benmccormickorg">Twitter</a> or my <a href="http://eepurl.com/WFYon">mailing list</a>. You also might want to check out my <a href="http://benmccormick.org/2016/05/02/digging-into-react-choosing-component-styles/">post on choosing which component styles to use in React</a>.</p>
<p>[^1]: PhantomJS was a tremendous source of pain in our Karma setup.
[^2]: This used to be the default setting, with Jest 15 it can be configured to work that way.</p>
]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Ben McCormick</name>
            <email>ben@benmccormick.org</email>
            <uri>http://benmccormick.org</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Quick Tip: Take advantage of lodash collections]]></title>
        <id>https://benmccormick.org/2016/06/26/quick-tip-take-advantage-of-lodash-collections-2/</id>
        <link href="https://benmccormick.org/2016/06/26/quick-tip-take-advantage-of-lodash-collections-2/">
        </link>
        <updated>2016-06-26T21:27:55Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the more frustrating things about using JavaScript in the browser is the number of different collection types that you need to deal with.  When using native APIs and 3rd party libraries, it’s easy to encounter 3 or more different types of collections, including <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/NodeList">NodeLists</a>, <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/HTMLCollection">HTMLCollections</a>, <a href="https://learn.jquery.com/using-jquery-core/jquery-object/">jQuery Objects</a>, and plain arrays.</p>
<pre><code class="language-javascript">let a = document.querySelectorAll('div')
a instanceOf NodeList //true

let b = document.getElementsByTagName('div')
b instanceOf HTMLCollection //true

let c = $('div')
c instanceOf jQuery // true

let d = ['button1', 'button2', 'button3'].map(id =&gt; document.getElementById(id));
d instance of Array //true
</code></pre>
<p>This ends up mattering in practice because not every function that is available on Array is available on NodeList, HTMLCollections, and jQuery objects.</p>
<pre><code class="language-javascript">let ids = document.querySelectorAll('div').map(el =&gt; el.id)
// Uncaught TypeError: document.querySelectorAll(...).map is not a function

ids = document.getElementsByTagName('div').map(el =&gt; el.id)
// Uncaught TypeError: document.getElementsByTagName(...).map is not a function

let numDivs = $('div').reduce((count, el) =&gt; count + 1, 0);
// Uncaught TypeError: $(...).reduce is not a function
</code></pre>
<p>Since we can’t use native array methods on these alternate collections, we end up having to be very careful about knowing where we’ve retrieved data from, and how to convert those collections or how to work around their limitations.</p>
<p>It’s useful to know about these distinctions, but in practice dealing with them is a pain.  One of the nice properties of <a href="https://lodash.com/docs">lodash</a> is that it abstracts over these incompatibilities.</p>
<pre><code class="language-javascript">let ids = _.map(document.querySelectorAll('div'), el =&gt; el.id);
// ['container', 'left-box', 'right-box']

ids = _.map(document.getElementssByTagName('div'), el =&gt; el.id);
// ['container', 'left-box', 'right-box']

let numDivs = _.reduce($('div'), (count, el) =&gt; count + 1, 0));
// 3
</code></pre>
<p>For methods that iterate over a collection lodash treats all array-like objects (essentially anything with a length property) the same and iterates over their numerical properties from 0 to length-1.  This provides a nice consistency when working with DOM APIs and removes the mental overhead from managing their inconsistencies.</p>
<h3>Subscribe</h3>
<p>Thanks for taking the time to read this post!   JavaScript development is one of the main topics of this blog, so if you enjoyed the post, please consider subscribing by using the <a href="http://feedpress.me/benmccormick">feed</a>, <a href="http://twitter.com/benmccormickorg">Twitter</a> or my <a href="http://eepurl.com/WFYon">mailing list</a>. You also might want to check out my post <a href="http://benmccormick.org/2014/11/12/underscore-vs-lodash/">comparing lodash and underscore</a>.  I’m also going to be starting a new series of posts soon diving into lodash more in depth.</p>
]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Ben McCormick</name>
            <email>ben@benmccormick.org</email>
            <uri>http://benmccormick.org</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
</feed>