<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>benmccormick.org</title>
        <link>http://benmccormick.org</link>
        <description>A blog by Ben McCormick</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2019 16:58:33 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs>
        <generator>Feed for Node.js</generator>
        <image>
            <title>benmccormick.org</title>
            <url>https://benmccormick.org/logo.png</url>
            <link>http://benmccormick.org</link>
        </image>
        <copyright>All rights reserved 2016, Ben McCormick</copyright>
        <atom:link href="http://benmccormick.org/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Ten Soft Skills That Will Shape Your Career]]></title>
            <link>https://benmccormick.org/2019/04/15/soft-skills</link>
            <guid>https://benmccormick.org/2019/04/15/soft-skills</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 15 Apr 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>One of the most popular posts in the history of my blog was a list with the click-baity name <a href="https://benmccormick.org/2017/07/19/ten-things-javascript/">Ten Things A Serious JavaScript Developer Should Learn</a>.  It explicitly focused on the set of technical skills that you need to become a “senior” JavaScript developer.  While I’m happy with that post, I’ve always wanted to revisit the idea, because it is my strong belief that <em>once you’ve hit a minimum level of technical capability, only about 20% of career success is determined by your technical skills</em>.  The other 80% is composed of skills that can be loosely bundled under “soft skills”.</p>
<p>You may quibble with my choice of percentage, but I don’t think the underlying idea that things other than technical ability is particularly controversial.  Even if they bitterly dismiss such things as “politics” most developers are aware that their careers are impacted by things that go beyond their ability to write algorithms.  What I haven’t seen much of however, are attempts to catalogue what these soft skills are, and how somebody might get better at them.  The second part is outside of the scope of a single post, though I will attempt to list resources here.  But the first is achievable, and that is what I will attempt to do here.</p>
<p>The following is not an exhaustive list, but it covers 10 “soft skills” that I’ve seen have a clear impact on my career in software and those of others.  The best part? These are things you can grow in that will have an impact in your life outside of work, and in any career you might transition into in the future.</p>
<h3>The Skills</h3>
<h4>1. Clear Communication</h4>
<p>While I’m making bold statements: A developer’s ability to communicate clearly is the single most important skill in determining the trajectory of their career.  Poor communicators are forced to rely on others to interpret their work, even when it is brilliant.  They will often create problems for others through miscommunications or lead teams to make suboptimal decisions because they were not able to explain the technical considerations involved in a situation.</p>
<p>Great communicators on the other hand, enlighten.  They help teams understand what is really going on so that non-technical team members can make good decisions, and technical folk can work with confidence.  Great communicators cut through misunderstandings, expose ambiguity and poor assumptions, and can translate for team members who are having trouble making themselves heard.</p>
<p>Communication skills are important for those on a management track, but they are just as important for those on a technical trajectory. Architects, Principal Engineers and Tech Leads must coordinate with many teams, teach less experienced developers, explain technical tradeoffs and document decisions and code.  Those are core parts of a senior technical employee’s job, and all of them come down to communication.</p>
<p><strong>Resources</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://benmccormick.org/2019/03/02/the-importance-of-writing">The Importance Of Writing For Software Developers</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.codingame.com/blog/10-tips-to-improve-your-communication-skills-as-a-software-developer/">10 Tips to Improve your Communication Skills as a Software Developer</a></li>
</ul>
<h4>2. Attention Management</h4>
<p>This one is more commonly referred to as “time management”, but I agree with <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/03/28/smarter-living/productivity-isnt-about-time-management-its-about-attention-management.html">this recent NYT Op-Ed</a>: the mechanics of how we organize our time is less important than whether we end up spending it on the most important things.  This broadly encompasses the ability to prioritize, to prevent distractions from wreaking havoc on productivity, and the ability to find ways to get back on track when things go wrong or priorities change.</p>
<p>This was a weakness for me early in my career: I got things done but often did them haphazardly or inefficiently.  One of my biggest sources of growth in the last few years has been finding ways to structure and prioritize my time better, while cutting out distractions.  This has been necessary due to life changes: I’m now a parent and have people reporting to me at work.  I wouldn’t be able to meet my current responsibilities with the habits I had as a 25 year old.  For me this has been largely about focusing in on a small amount of essential things and actively removing less important things from my life.  For others it may be more about establishing patterns and limits.  Either way, this requires planning and introspection first to be effective.</p>
<p><strong>Resources</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://amzn.to/2TqwDeR">Deep Work - Cal Newport</a></li>
<li><a href="http://bradfrost.com/blog/post/scheduling-every-minute-of-my-day/">Scheduling Every Minute of My Day - Brad Frost</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/03/28/smarter-living/productivity-isnt-about-time-management-its-about-attention-management.html">Productivity Isn’t About Time Management, It’s about Attention Management - Adam Grant</a></li>
</ul>
<h4>3. Initiative</h4>
<p>If you see an opportunity or a problem, do you do something about it?  I’ve been reading a good amount of “manager books” recently, and in many of them a surprising amount of focus is dedicated to the question of how we create conditions when people are “empowered” to act.  And there certainly is an environmental factor here.  People are more likely to take initiative and risks when they’re not afraid of being punished for it.  But the individual also controls a lot here.  Developers who are willing to step up and take initiative in a situation can make an outsize impact.</p>
<p>Do you have a piece of code or process on your team that everybody acknowledges is a bit wonky, but nobody has ever taken the time to fix even though it is slowly taking a toll on the team over time?  Are there simple things that you know could make your product better, but nobody has quite taken the time to get to them?  Those are the opportunities that initiative can turn into value.</p>
<p><strong>Resources</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://overreacted.io/fix-like-no-ones-watching/">Fix Like No One’s Watching</a></li>
</ul>
<h4>4. Empathy</h4>
<p>There is no meaningful software product that has been created in isolation.  One person may have written the code (though that is quite rare for software with any scale of impact), and maybe even didn’t collaborate with anyone to handle distribution / hosting etc, but if that software is used by others there is always support, training and marketing to consider.  You can create a todo app for yourself without talking to anyone.  But nobody makes a career in this business without talking to other humans.</p>
<p>The thing about us humans; we work well with people who we trust, and who we perceive as caring about us.  We also are for the most part exceptionally good at discerning when somebody is faking it.  So if we can’t get away from humans, and we can’t be fake, what can we do?  We are left with, in the words of Dale Carnegie “becoming genuinely interested in other people”.  If you’re currently filled with red-faced frustration at your annoying co-worker or manipulative boss, this may seem like asking for a miracle. And arguably any time we look outside ourselves it is a miracle. But regardless of your philosophical outlook on such things, there are definitely ways we can improve in how we work with and care for the people around us.  And it starts with trying to empathize and seeing the people around us as human beings and not obstacles or tools.</p>
<p><strong>Resources</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://amzn.to/2Iiooe4">How To Win Friends And Influence People - Dale Carnegie</a></li>
<li><a href="https://amzn.to/2YSZasy">Radical Candor - Kimball Scott</a></li>
<li><a href="https://amzn.to/2WVkqfv">I Hear You - Michael Sorenson</a></li>
</ul>
<h4>5. Negotiation &#x26; Persuasion</h4>
<p>You may not think that Software Engineering involves much negotiation.  But that is only true if you use a shallow definition of negotiation.  Every time a team debates implementation strategies for a feature, which tickets should end up in a sprint, and how much time to spend chasing a difficult to reproduce bug, they are engaging in negotiation, and team members are attempting to persuade.  And there is a wealth of knowledge out there describing how to improve on these skills.</p>
<p>A word of caution here; unlike some of the other things on this list, these skills can often be dangerous when they’re improved in isolation.  When developers complain about politics trumping technical ability, they’re often experiencing decisions being made based on the ability of some employees to persuade and negotiate.  When those employees are not actually providing the best ideas this is suboptimal.  For the technically skilled employees, the answer is to learn to persuade better.  But for those who can negotiate we always need to make sure that we’re <strong>persuading for good</strong>.  Just like the loudest voices shouldn’t always win, when you can communicate well, make sure to stay humble and  boost other’s good ideas when you see them.</p>
<p><strong>Resources</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://amzn.to/2OUBnnl">Negotiation Genius - Deepak Malhotra and Max Bazerman</a></li>
</ul>
<h4>6. Continual Learning</h4>
<p>Were you paying attention in high school physics when they taught about the difference between distance, velocity, and acceleration?  Distance is the amount an object has traveled.  Velocity is the speed at which it is currently moving in a given direction.  Acceleration is the rate at which the object’s velocity is changing.  If you want to know where an object is <em>right now</em>, distance is the only thing that matters.  But as time progresses, velocity starts to matter more, and in the very long term any difference in acceleration will be the only thing that matters.</p>
<p>The same ideas play out when acquiring skills.  If you need to evaluate your career potential for the next few months, the skills and accomplishments you’ve acquired so far (distance) are the only things that matter.  But if you want to think about your career potential over the next 30 years, the new skills you’re acquiring (velocity) and even more importantly your ability to get better at learning new things (acceleration) will matter much much more. Learning is a skill unto itself, and the earlier you invest in it the more dividends it will pay over time.</p>
<p><strong>Resources</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://css-tricks.com/learning-to-learn/">Learning To Learn - Sarah Drasner</a></li>
<li><a href="http://benmccormick.org/2019/02/18/how-to-keep-learning-js">How To Keep Learning JavaScript</a></li>
</ul>
<h4>7. Self Care</h4>
<p>Another lesson that I’ve learned the hard way in my career is the reality of my own mortality.  None of us are indestructible, and our bodies are not perpetual energy machines.  They require care and maintenance.  Our souls too are not meant to run on work alone, and we can burn out hard without sufficient rest.  This is all aside from deeper issues of disease and mental health that can change our lives in even more profound and difficult ways.</p>
<p>Self care is a career skill because frankly we are great at deluding ourselves into thinking we’re functioning normally while we’ve compromised ourselves.  <a href="https://www.thecut.com/2014/07/you-might-not-know-if-youre-sleep-deprived.html">Research</a> shows that we are horrible judges of whether our judgement and creativity are compromised by lack of sleep.  Because we can’t run controlled studies on ourselves, we don’t really know whether our lack of exercise or 60 hour workweek induced burnout are hurting our creativity.  But research suggests it is for pretty much everybody.</p>
<p>Healthy socialization, sleeping, eating and exercise ultimately lead to better emotional stability, ability to focus, and creativity.  But even aside from the career benefits, when we’re devouring our bodies and minds for work, it leads to a question of what we’re doing this for in the first place.</p>
<p><strong>Resources</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://amzn.to/2OVBpvx">Why We Sleep - Matthew Walker</a></li>
<li><a href="https://benmccormick.org/2019/03/09/book-review-deep-work-common-rule">Deep Work &#x26; The Common Rule</a></li>
</ul>
<h4>8. Business Awareness</h4>
<p>Do you know what your company actually does?  Do you understand why the features you’re building are important, and the relative priority of them?  Can you explain the business tradeoffs involved when you’re making an software architecture decision between performance and security?</p>
<p>In companies larger than a few people it’s not ultimately developers’ jobs to make business decisions.  But understanding the context for those decisions helps us better prioritize our time, make good tradeoffs, and call attention to inefficiencies or counterproductive behavior in our products. In addition, nobody wants to spend time working on things that don’t matter. But when we try to innovate without understanding the broader business, we often end up doing just that.</p>
<p><strong>Resources</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://mcfunley.com/choose-boring-technology">Choose Boring Technology - Dan McKinley</a></li>
</ul>
<h4>9. Marketing and Branding</h4>
<p>Marketing is a dirty word in engineering circles.  Many take the attitude of the Dilbert comics that <a href="https://dilbert.com/strip/1997-05-02">marketing is a synonym for exaggeration lying, and fraud</a>.  But at it’s core marketing is just making sure that the people who could benefit from your services are aware of those services.  This has several applications to developers.  In the job market, finding ways to let employers know who you are and what you’re capable of is important.  But in medium to large companies it also is important to do some level of internal marketing; to make sure you’re credited for the work you’ve done and that people understand it’s values.  Developers who consider themselves above this or dismiss it as politics do so at their own peril.</p>
<p><strong>Resources</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.stephaniemorillo.co/single-post/2019/02/17/7-Common-Content-Marketing-Mistakes-Developers-Make-and-How-to-Avoid-Them">7 Common Content Marketing Mistakes Developers Make and How to Avoid Them - Stephanie Morillo</a></li>
</ul>
<h4>10. Character</h4>
<p>The final item here is in some ways an oddball.  While the other 9 things on this list are skills that you can work on, character is something deeper.  Questions of what good character is and how you develop it are way outside the scope of this post.  And I would personally consider any attempt to improve your character for solely utilitarian career reasons to be ultimately hollow.  But character is undeniably important in your career.</p>
<p>Do the people around you trust you?  Do they believe that you’re trying to do the right thing?  If the answers are no, you may find obstacles in the most unexpected places.  If the answers are yes, you will eventually find help from people you would never have looked to.</p>
<p>In addition, as an industry, technology has the power to shape the world, and as practitioners we all get the chance to impact our little corners of the world.  It’s worth considering not just whether we’re “succeeding in our career”, but what impact we’re having on the world around us.</p>
<p><strong>Resources</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://amzn.to/2I5jP7K">Future Ethics - Cennydd Bowles</a></li>
</ul>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>ben@benmccormick.org (Ben McCormick)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Consistency]]></title>
            <link>https://benmccormick.org/2019/04/01/consistency</link>
            <guid>https://benmccormick.org/2019/04/01/consistency</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The last few weeks I’ve had several conversations with a coworker about consistency in code: why do we do things one way here, and a different way there?  Some of this is macro level; Where do we split chunks of related functionality into different files?  Some of it is micro level; what should the rules be for when we use an inline function instead of pulling it out into its own named method?  Some of it is trivial; Do we use <code class="language-text">_</code> or <code class="language-text">-</code> to separate words in file names?  In our current codebase we’re not always consistent on many of these issues.  As we’ve discussed the various issues, I realized that some of them bothered me more than others, and (more interestingly to me) my ideas have changed here over time.</p>
<h3>The Platonic Ideal</h3>
<blockquote>
<p> In a perfectly consistent system, 3 developers writing the same module would produce line by line identical code</p>
</blockquote>
<p>There’s an extreme point of view out there that says “while a perfectly consistent system might not be possible, the closer we can get to that the better”.  The benefits of consistency are many: consistent naming helps with code search and connecting different parts of a system.  Consistent code structure makes code easier to scan once a developer is familiar with the system, and it makes exceptions stand out as something intentional and interesting.  Consistent formatting removes potential distractions.   So what’s not to love?  Shouldn’t we always try to add more consistency?  I see 2 primary reasons why it might not be worth trying to enforce every single rule we can come up with.</p>
<h4>We’re only human</h4>
<p>The first reason not to enforce “everything” is that our human attention spans can only internalize so many rules at once.  When we’re trying to remember a large number of rules, its easy to miss one.  But more importantly, when we’re writing code or reviewing it, focusing too much on human enforced consistency rules can distract from the actual purpose of the code, making it harder to notice the substance of code because we’re so focused on the form.</p>
<h4>Standards too soon</h4>
<p>The other thing that can happen when you try to standardize everything is a loss of creativity.  Sometimes it’s helpful to experiment for a while to find the right pattern in a codebase.  In an ideal situation experiments like that will happen on the side, or be explored in branches, but for small teams or new codebases, it will likely happen at least partially in production.</p>
<h3>User Friendly Consistency</h3>
<p>So what <strong>can</strong> we do to get the benefits of consistency? The 4 ways I like to see this happen are:</p>
<h4>Automation</h4>
<p>The best way to enforce stylistic consistency and other straightforward things like naming conventions is to use automation.  Linters like <a href="https://eslint.org/">eslint</a> and auto-formatters like <a href="https://prettier.io/">Prettier</a>.  My rule here is that any linter rule that is about stylistic consistency should be auto-fixable, if not it isn’t clear enough or isn’t worth it.  For “correctness rules” it can be ok to flag errors without auto-fixing, if human judgement is needed.</p>
<h4>Code Review Checklists</h4>
<p>Code reviews can be a good way to limitedly enforce consistency; but its good to limit scope to avoid <a href="https://samsaccone.com/posts/code-reviews-not-nits.html">developers trying to become human compilers</a>.  If you try to enforce too many things in code reviews, its easy for people to get caught up in going through a list and forget to apply human judgement to the context of the current code. But <a href="https://benmccormick.org/2019/01/14/value-from-code-reviews">code review checklists</a> are a good way to make a coordinated push on high value items that are either new or often neglected.  This checklist should consist of a few important things to check during every review. The list should be re-examined on a regular basis and ideally kept to 5 or less items.</p>
<h4>Focused Refactoring</h4>
<p>Sometimes its appropriate to have “refactoring initiatives” to standardize on a particular pattern over time.  This can be good for standardizing on a particular library for a task, or removing an older pattern that persists in the codebase after a better way has been found.  My advice here is to <a href="https://benmccormick.org/2018/01/07/large-improvements-small-team/">only do one of these at a time, and complete them before starting a new one</a>.  One of the biggest causes of inconsistency is when a team attempts to ”<a href="https://xkcd.com/927/">standardize</a>” on a solution, then abandons that for a new solution without finish the migration, resulting in a <a href="http://mikehadlow.blogspot.com/2014/12/the-lava-layer-anti-pattern.html">lava layer architecture</a>.</p>
<h4>Focus on the high level</h4>
<p>If there is one place to apply human consistency checks its at the structural level.  If your high level patterns are consistent, the code base will be easy to navigate, and modular code written in a standardized high level structure will be <a href="https://programmingisterrible.com/post/139222674273/write-code-that-is-easy-to-delete-not-easy-to">easy to delete</a>.  Overall low level code that is inconsistent or poorly written is easier to overcome than high level code as long as you’re taking advantage of code reviews and the other methods suggested here to improve new code, because most low level code is only read occasionally.  So high traffic “messy code” can be a focus of refactoring efforts, and the rest can continue working without disturbing anything.</p>
<p>Messy code is much more problematic at a structural level though, because when different areas of the code are arranged in different ways, it becomes much harder to find functionality when debugging.  This type of inconsistency also tends to make bulk improvements harder, as you have to have a much greater understanding of all the ways a codebase is put together.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>ben@benmccormick.org (Ben McCormick)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Lessons from Six Months As A Manager/Developer Hybrid]]></title>
            <link>https://benmccormick.org/2019/03/25/manager-and-developer</link>
            <guid>https://benmccormick.org/2019/03/25/manager-and-developer</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 25 Mar 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>For the last 6 months I’ve been serving as a hybrid developer/engineering manager.  It’s been an interesting experience, and because this is a fairly common way to transition into engineering management<sup id="fnref-1"><a href="#fn-1" class="footnote-ref">1</a></sup>, I thought it might be worthwhile to share some lessons I’ve learned so far.</p>
<h4>1. Time discipline is key</h4>
<p>The biggest challenge of this transition was learning to be a manager.  It’s a whole new job!  But the biggest challenge specific to the management/developer split has been managing my time.</p>
<p>I’ve always been a bit loose with my time management.  I do a lot based on my mental state at a particular time; if I’m tired or uninspired I may lean more into grunt work like documentation, code reviews, or more “scripted” code work.  If I’m in the zone I’ll dive into big tasks, and if someone comes to me with a problem I tend to context shift into it and go from there.</p>
<p>This “time management strategy” hasn’t held up at all while trying to balance manager and development strategies.  Basically because of the blend of <a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/makersschedule.html">maker and manager schedules</a>.  Developers need long uninterrupted periods of time to be productive, while managers tend to operate on a much more social and interrupt driven schedule.  They’re naturally opposed.</p>
<p>Working with this tension requires discipline and planning.  For me personally I’ve started planning my schedule for the next day at the end of the previous day, batching my checking of Slack/email and being more thoughtful when somebody asks for my time.</p>
<p><strong>Planning my schedule for the next day</strong> is a tip I picked up from <a href="https://benmccormick.org/2019/03/09/book-review-deep-work-common-rule">Deep Work</a>.  To close out the day, I review the things I’ll need to handle the next day, and block out my calendar with time for different tasks for the next day.  This does mean that my calendar <em>always looks completely booked for the current day</em>.  So far this has served as a feature not a bug; I can still move things if something urgent comes up and it has a way of encouraging people to schedule less urgent things in advance.  Note that scheduling like this doesn’t mean you can’t change plans; I do all the time.  It just means that you start with a plan and can be thoughtful about how you vary off of it.</p>
<p><strong>Batching Slack and email</strong> has been something I’ve known would be good for me forever.  It feels good in the moment to be the guy who is constantly available, but the cost of distraction is higher than you think.  So far, management has been a catalyst for me buckling down here.</p>
<p>Finally, I get a lot more unexpected requests for my time now than I did previously.  I’ve found that batching my email and Slack reading combined with <strong>a willingness to suggest a meeting later in the day or the next morning rather than <em>right now</em></strong> has helped me protect blocks of productivity and focus, without making me an unresponsive manager.  Most things can sit for 2 hours without blowing up anyone’s day.  The key is to ask enough to identify the 5% of things that can’t wait.</p>
<p>Those 3 tactics have worked for me, but overall it comes down to being intentional about your time.  If you let yourself be blown by the wind while splitting dual responsibilities, one of them will almost always receive the short end of the stick.</p>
<h4>2. Team success metrics are the only ones that matter</h4>
<p>When you’re acting as both a developer and a manager, it can be tempting to hold yourselves to 2 sets of metrics: management metrics and development metrics.  This is a mistake.  It will cause you to over-prioritize your own tasks and hurt your team’s long term growth.</p>
<p>Focusing on personal development metrics and goals can lead to over-prioritizing them for a few reasons. First, development goals tend to be much “cleaner” than management goals; it’s easier to tell what you’ve achieved.  Second, if you’re transitioning into this role from a dev role, you probably are much more comfortable with these tasks, and so they can act as a safe place where you avoid having to stretch yourself.  And finally, if you moved into this role from a senior dev position, it can be easy to tell yourself that this is actually the best way to get stuff done.  And you may be right… in the short term.</p>
<p>So what’s the antidote?  Focus on team productivity and view your own work as just an extra card you have to play in your hand.  It’s an advantage you have over less technical managers, but if you don’t set to working developing other strengths, you’re not going to be able to grow, and if you’re monopolizing the important work your team won’t be able to step up into new roles.  So play that card, but do it with caution, and always as a means rather than an end.</p>
<h4>3. This isn’t long term sustainable; have a plan</h4>
<p>Hybrid Management / Developer roles aren’t a long term game.  Aside from the scheduling tension I mentioned above, once you move into this role you’re either going to be slowly giving up responsibilities and watching your tech skills slowly move off the cutting edge as you focus on learning how to manager your team and developing others to fill the roles you once did, or you’re going to be failing as a manager as you try to cling too tightly to your senior individual contributor responsibilities.  So if you want to avoid that, it’s important to be evaluating how you want your career to evolve.  A role like this can be a first step up a chain, or part of a <a href="https://charity.wtf/2017/05/11/the-engineer-manager-pendulum/">dev to manager pendulum</a>.  You also might discover that management isn’t for you and decide to move back.  I’m committed to this for a set period of time, and that’s helped me to work through the days when I wonder what I actually accomplished, and think strategically about what I need to get better at.</p>
<h4>4. Best Management resources</h4>
<p>So this isn’t a learning so much, but as a newbie manager, probably the best thing I can do is point you to the resources I’ve found helpful.  So here are some of the best.</p>
<p><strong>On Engineering Management</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://randsinrepose.com/">Rands In Repose</a> by Michael Lopp and <a href="https://amzn.to/2Clyjvy">the book he pulled out of the blog</a> are great little snippets of engineering management gold</li>
<li><a href="https://us2.campaign-archive.com/home/?u=1f50ce22f02ed0ffc80c10aff&#x26;id=8c0f947e69">Lara Hogan’s Newsletter</a> is full of useful advice, and she’s really good about including exercises to help practice what she’s describing.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>On Management Generally</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://amzn.to/2F4i0ni">Radical Candor</a> is the single most helpful thing I’ve read while trying to figure out this whole management thing</li>
<li>Patrick Lencioni’s books are all told as “leadership fables” which can seem a bit weird, but in the squishy imprecise world of management, stories can be very effective ways to teach.  I’ve read <a href="https://amzn.to/2UCPpvT">The Five Dysfunctions of a Team</a>, <a href="https://amzn.to/2UIaxkr">Death By Meeting</a> and <a href="https://amzn.to/2CqYalR">Silos, Politics, and Turf Wars</a>.  They’ve all been great and I plan to read more of his stuff.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>On Structuring My Time</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>I reviewed it last week, but <a href="https://amzn.to/2UBcIGy">Deep Work</a> was super helpful in thinking through how to balance my time.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>On Career Path</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>I linked this one above, but if you didn’t click through then Charity Major’s post on the <a href="https://charity.wtf/2017/05/11/the-engineer-manager-pendulum/">Engineer/Manager Pendulum</a> has been really helpful for pushing me to think through where I want to go next.</li>
</ul>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn-1">
<p>I’m aware that lots of folks would say that this is a very <em>bad</em> way to start management and that you should stop coding when you become a manager, but it isn’t always possible to fully control what opportunities are available.</p>
<a href="#fnref-1" class="footnote-backref">↩</a>
</li>
</ol>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>ben@benmccormick.org (Ben McCormick)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Utility Functions]]></title>
            <link>https://benmccormick.org/2019/03/11/utility-functions</link>
            <guid>https://benmccormick.org/2019/03/11/utility-functions</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 11 Mar 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As I’ve gone through projects over time, I’ve found a few functions that I end up creating for every significant project that I’ve worked on.  Some of the details differ from project to project, but the basic function remains the same.  I thought it would be helpful to do a rundown:</p>
<h3>React/JSX</h3>
<p>Some of my utils are focused on making JSX nicer to deal with.  2 situations that I’ve run into a lot in JSX are conditionally showing an item in JSX, and determining which of several classes to add to an element based on logic.  Scenarios like these:</p>
<div class="gatsby-highlight" data-language="js">
      <pre class="language-js"><code class="language-js"><span class="token operator">&lt;</span>div<span class="token operator">></span>
    <span class="token punctuation">{</span>shouldShowCreateButton <span class="token operator">?</span> <span class="token operator">&lt;</span>Button
            onClick<span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token punctuation">{</span>createWidget<span class="token punctuation">}</span>
            type <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token string">'primary'</span>
            size <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token string">'Large'</span>
            disabled <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span><span class="token operator">!</span>createEnabled<span class="token punctuation">}</span>
            className<span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token string">'create-button'</span>
        <span class="token operator">></span>
            Create Widget
        <span class="token operator">&lt;</span><span class="token operator">/</span>Button<span class="token operator">></span> <span class="token punctuation">:</span> <span class="token keyword">null</span><span class="token punctuation">}</span>
<span class="token operator">&lt;</span><span class="token operator">/</span>div<span class="token operator">></span></code></pre>
      </div>
<div class="gatsby-highlight" data-language="js">
      <pre class="language-js"><code class="language-js"><span class="token keyword">let</span> classNames <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token string">'create-button'</span>
<span class="token keyword">if</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span>extraClass<span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
    classNames <span class="token operator">+=</span> <span class="token string">' '</span> <span class="token operator">+</span> extraClass<span class="token punctuation">;</span>
<span class="token punctuation">}</span>
<span class="token keyword">if</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span>createEnabled<span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
    classNames <span class="token operator">+=</span> <span class="token string">' is-disabled'</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
<span class="token punctuation">}</span>
<span class="token keyword">if</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span>hasCreateError<span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
    classNames <span class="token operator">+=</span> <span class="token string">' has-error'</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
<span class="token punctuation">}</span>
<span class="token keyword">return</span> <span class="token operator">&lt;</span>Button
        onClick<span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token punctuation">{</span>createWidget<span class="token punctuation">}</span>
        type <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token string">'primary'</span>
        size <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token string">'Large'</span>
        disabled <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span><span class="token operator">!</span>createEnabled<span class="token punctuation">}</span>
        className<span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token punctuation">{</span>classNames<span class="token punctuation">}</span>
    <span class="token operator">></span>
        Create Widget
<span class="token operator">&lt;</span><span class="token operator">/</span>Button<span class="token operator">></span></code></pre>
      </div>
<p>These are both ok, and you’ll see plenty of examples of code like them out there, but the first puts a big chunk of code in a ternary, and it’s not always going to be clear to a reader where that <code class="language-text">: null</code> came from at the end, or why it’s there by the time they reach the end.</p>
<p>In the second example, we’re dealing with a lot of ugly string concatenation.  There are other ways to handle this, like using template strings + ternaries but generally they each provide their own messy pieces.</p>
<p>To solve these situations, I like to define these 2 small functions:</p>
<div class="gatsby-highlight" data-language="js">
      <pre class="language-js"><code class="language-js"><span class="token keyword">import</span> isString <span class="token keyword">from</span> <span class="token string">'lodash-es/isString'</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
<span class="token keyword">import</span> filter <span class="token keyword">from</span> <span class="token string">'lodash-es/filter'</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
<span class="token comment">// A helper for React Components to reduce ternary use</span>
<span class="token keyword">export</span> <span class="token keyword">const</span> <span class="token function-variable function">showIf</span> <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span>condition<span class="token punctuation">,</span> element<span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token operator">=></span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span>condition <span class="token operator">?</span> element <span class="token punctuation">:</span> <span class="token keyword">null</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>

<span class="token comment">// A helper for handling class lists where some values may be undefined</span>
<span class="token comment">// filters out anything that isn't a string and then adds spaces</span>
<span class="token keyword">export</span> <span class="token keyword">const</span> <span class="token function-variable function">classes</span> <span class="token operator">=</span> classList <span class="token operator">=></span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
    <span class="token keyword">return</span> <span class="token function">filter</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>classList<span class="token punctuation">,</span> c <span class="token operator">=></span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
        <span class="token keyword">return</span> <span class="token function">isString</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>c<span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token operator">&amp;&amp;</span> c<span class="token punctuation">.</span>length <span class="token operator">></span> <span class="token number">0</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
    <span class="token punctuation">}</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">join</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token string">' '</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
<span class="token punctuation">}</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span></code></pre>
      </div>
<p>The first just formalizes the most common use of ternaries in JSX (conditionally showing an item) and adds an easy to understand name to it.</p>
<p>The second lets us work with an array of classNames instead of handling string concat ourselves, and will automatically filter out undefined or empty classNames.  This implementation does silently swallow errors on anything that is not a string, which may not be your preference.  Usage looks like this:</p>
<div class="gatsby-highlight" data-language="js">
      <pre class="language-js"><code class="language-js"><span class="token operator">&lt;</span>div<span class="token operator">></span>
    <span class="token punctuation">{</span><span class="token function">showIf</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>shouldShowCreateButton<span class="token punctuation">,</span> <span class="token operator">&lt;</span>Button
            onClick<span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token punctuation">{</span>createWidget<span class="token punctuation">}</span>
            type <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token string">'primary'</span>
            size <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token string">'Large'</span>
            disabled <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span><span class="token operator">!</span>createEnabled<span class="token punctuation">}</span>
            className<span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token string">'create-button'</span>
        <span class="token operator">></span>
            Create Widget
        <span class="token operator">&lt;</span><span class="token operator">/</span>Button<span class="token operator">></span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">}</span>
<span class="token operator">&lt;</span><span class="token operator">/</span>div<span class="token operator">></span></code></pre>
      </div>
<p>the showIf reads much more clearly than the previous ternary, especially for language newbies who might not be used to ternaries.</p>
<div class="gatsby-highlight" data-language="js">
      <pre class="language-js"><code class="language-js"><span class="token keyword">let</span> classNames <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token punctuation">[</span><span class="token string">'create-button'</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span> extraClass<span class="token punctuation">]</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
<span class="token keyword">if</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span>createEnabled<span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
    classNames<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">push</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token string">'is-disabled'</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
<span class="token punctuation">}</span>
<span class="token keyword">if</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span>hasCreateError<span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
    classNames<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">push</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token string">'has-error'</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
<span class="token punctuation">}</span>
<span class="token keyword">return</span> <span class="token operator">&lt;</span>Button
        onClick<span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token punctuation">{</span>createWidget<span class="token punctuation">}</span>
        type <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token string">'primary'</span>
        size <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token string">'Large'</span>
        disabled <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span><span class="token operator">!</span>createEnabled<span class="token punctuation">}</span>
        className<span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token punctuation">{</span><span class="token function">classes</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>classNames<span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">}</span>
    <span class="token operator">></span>
        Create Widget
<span class="token operator">&lt;</span><span class="token operator">/</span>Button<span class="token operator">></span></code></pre>
      </div>
<p>Here we’ve gotten rid of the extra string code and are working on arrays, which is a nicer data structure for dealing with lists of stuff. Also since we’re auto-filtering falsy stuff, we don’t have to worry about whether extraClass was defined if it was passed as a prop to our component or something.</p>
<h3>Formatting</h3>
<p>So the next few may be different for everyone.  The details here aren’t important, the important thing is that you centralize your formatting of numbers and dates.  For instance, here are functions for formatting dates, normal numbers and percentages from a current project:</p>
<div class="gatsby-highlight" data-language="js">
      <pre class="language-js"><code class="language-js"><span class="token keyword">import</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span> format <span class="token punctuation">}</span> <span class="token keyword">from</span> <span class="token string">'date-fns'</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
<span class="token keyword">import</span> isNumber <span class="token keyword">from</span> <span class="token string">'lodash-es/isNumber'</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>

<span class="token comment">// takes either a string or a date object and formats it as a standard date with time</span>
<span class="token keyword">export</span> <span class="token keyword">const</span> <span class="token function-variable function">stdFormat</span> <span class="token operator">=</span> dateStr <span class="token operator">=></span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
    <span class="token keyword">if</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token operator">!</span>dateStr<span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
        <span class="token keyword">return</span> dateStr<span class="token punctuation">;</span>
    <span class="token punctuation">}</span>
    <span class="token keyword">let</span> date <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token keyword">new</span> <span class="token class-name">Date</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>dateStr<span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
    <span class="token keyword">return</span> <span class="token function">format</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>date<span class="token punctuation">,</span> <span class="token string">'MM/DD/YY hh:mm A'</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
<span class="token punctuation">}</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>

<span class="token keyword">export</span> <span class="token keyword">const</span> <span class="token function-variable function">commafy</span> <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span>num<span class="token punctuation">,</span> minDecimals <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token number">0</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token operator">=></span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
    <span class="token keyword">if</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token function">isNumber</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>num<span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
        <span class="token keyword">return</span> num<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">toLocaleString</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token string">'en-US'</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
            minimumFractionDigits<span class="token punctuation">:</span> minDecimals<span class="token punctuation">,</span>
        <span class="token punctuation">}</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
    <span class="token punctuation">}</span> <span class="token keyword">else</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
        <span class="token keyword">return</span> num<span class="token punctuation">;</span>
    <span class="token punctuation">}</span>
<span class="token punctuation">}</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>

<span class="token keyword">export</span> <span class="token keyword">const</span> <span class="token function-variable function">percentify</span> <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span>num<span class="token punctuation">,</span> minDecimals <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token number">0</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token operator">=></span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
    <span class="token keyword">if</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token function">isNumber</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>num<span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
        <span class="token keyword">return</span> num<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">toLocaleString</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token string">'en-US'</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
            style<span class="token punctuation">:</span> <span class="token string">'percent'</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span>
            minimumFractionDigits<span class="token punctuation">:</span> minDecimals<span class="token punctuation">,</span>
        <span class="token punctuation">}</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
    <span class="token punctuation">}</span> <span class="token keyword">else</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
        <span class="token keyword">return</span> num<span class="token punctuation">;</span>
    <span class="token punctuation">}</span>
<span class="token punctuation">}</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span></code></pre>
      </div>
<p>The first one will take a date object and format it to something like <code class="language-text">05/30/17 01:16 PM</code>.  The second will take a number and return a string formatted with appropriate commas: <code class="language-text">1234567 -&gt; &#39;1,234,567&#39;</code>.  The last one will convert a decimal to a percentage string: <code class="language-text">0.5 -&gt; &#39;50%&#39;</code>.</p>
<p>Note that none of these functions are very long.  I’m relying on a date library for the first piece and <code class="language-text">toLocaleString</code> for the other 2.  So I could inline this in most places and not have it get much longer.  The benefit of these types of functions is not in saving typing.  It’s in standardizing how you format or don’t format things throughout an application.  This has 2 benefits:</p>
<ol>
<li>It’s easy to fix bugs, add features or switch between libraries for these common tasks across your application because all of the logic is centralized.  If I needed to start supporting more locales than just the US for percentage formatting, or use moment for my date formatting library I could easily do so with edits to only one file.  That file is also well unit tested, so those transitions would be safe.</li>
<li>It lets us control which formats are allowed.  For instance we’re allowing the function caller to specify how many decimal points to show for the numeric functions, but not giving options to change the date format for the formatting function, because we want that to be the same everywhere.  If we need to support multiple formats for different scenarios, like a date-only format or a format for communicating with the API, we can add options for that which don’t open up all formats, or expose them as separate functions.  With dates in particular, I want imports of libraries like moment or date-fns to be limited to 2 or 3 files at the most, and not used ad-hoc throughout the codebase.</li>
</ol>
<p>Note that all my examples so far have utilized other utility libraries like lodash and date-fns.  The best utility functions are those that you don’t have to maintain yourself.  I do recommend looking for libraries that you can tree-shake and only take what you need though.  Other ones like moment.js can make a big difference on your JavaScript bundle size if you let them.</p>
<h3>Timing</h3>
<p>Timeout functions are useful, but the browsers built in functions are callback based and don’t play well with promises or async await.  We can fix that:</p>
<div class="gatsby-highlight" data-language="js">
      <pre class="language-js"><code class="language-js"><span class="token keyword">export</span> <span class="token keyword">const</span> <span class="token function-variable function">sleep</span> <span class="token operator">=</span> secs <span class="token operator">=></span> <span class="token keyword">new</span> <span class="token class-name">Promise</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>res <span class="token operator">=></span> <span class="token function">setTimeout</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>res<span class="token punctuation">,</span> secs <span class="token operator">*</span> <span class="token number">1000</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
<span class="token keyword">export</span> <span class="token keyword">const</span> <span class="token function-variable function">pause</span> <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token operator">=></span> <span class="token function">sleep</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token number">0</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span></code></pre>
      </div>
<p>I now have a promisified version of setTimeout (<code class="language-text">sleep</code>) and a special case version with a 0 timeout (useful for things that should happen as soon as possible after the current event loop executes. I prefer dealing with things in seconds over milliseconds, so I changed the API to use that.  That is probably not everyone’s cup of tea, so feel free to copy and modify.</p>
<p>Usage looks like this:</p>
<div class="gatsby-highlight" data-language="js">
      <pre class="language-js"><code class="language-js"><span class="token comment">// function to kick off a "job" of some type and then</span>
<span class="token comment">// check every 30 seconds to see if the job is complete</span>
<span class="token keyword">const</span> createJobAndShowResults <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token keyword">async</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token operator">=></span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
    <span class="token function">createJob</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
    <span class="token comment">// don't do this without a timeout/failure</span>
    <span class="token comment">// condition in real life!</span>
    <span class="token keyword">while</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token boolean">true</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
        <span class="token keyword">await</span> <span class="token function">sleep</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token number">30</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
        <span class="token keyword">let</span> jobStatus <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token function">checkIfJobIsCompleted</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
        <span class="token keyword">if</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span>jobStatus<span class="token punctuation">.</span>complete<span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
            <span class="token keyword">return</span> jobStatus<span class="token punctuation">;</span>
        <span class="token punctuation">}</span>
    <span class="token punctuation">}</span>
<span class="token punctuation">}</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span></code></pre>
      </div>
<h3>And Even More!</h3>
<p>This is just a sample of the small functions I usually create in projects.  Pretty much all of them exist for one or more of the reasons that were already discussed:</p>
<ol>
<li>Smoothing over awkward library syntax like multiple classes in JSX or HTML templates</li>
<li>Making user intention clear with a well named function, like showIf or stdDateFormat</li>
<li>Ensuring consistent application-specific behavior across common low-level operations like formatting or logging</li>
<li>Making it easy to replace 3rd party utility libraries  like date-fns by wrapping them in an application specific function</li>
<li>Improving browser level APIs, or shaping them to have useful defaults for the current application, like we did with toLocaleString and setTimeout.</li>
</ol>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>ben@benmccormick.org (Ben McCormick)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Book Review: Deep Work & The Common Rule]]></title>
            <link>https://benmccormick.org/2019/03/09/book-review-deep-work-common-rule</link>
            <guid>https://benmccormick.org/2019/03/09/book-review-deep-work-common-rule</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I’m trying something different today.  This is a review of 2 books I’ve read recently; I’m combining them because their similarities and differences are just as interesting to me as the practical steps they encourage.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2TqwDeR">Deep Work</a> is a 3 year old book from Cal Newport focused on encouraging readers to spend more time on their most important work.  It starts out with sections defining and motivating “Deep Work”: focusing without distraction on cognitively demanding tasks.  Then it goes on to give a series of recommended strategies for creating more and better deep work time in your life.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2F0AIgV">The Common Rule</a> is a new book by Justin Earley focused on building habits that allow living life with purpose.  It is a “Christian book”, and recommends practices like daily prayer and fasting.  But it is mainly focused on encouraging habits to combat some universal challenges of modern American life: distracting technologies, all consuming work environments, and increasing isolation.</p>
<h3>A Shared Diagnosis</h3>
<p>Deep Work and The Common Rule share a common view on the challenges facing many American adults today: they each tackle tech distractions, work expectations of constant availability, and time spent on shallow activities disconnected from our core goals and desires.</p>
<p>Both authors are skeptical of modern “networking tools” like social networks, chat tools, news sites and email without dismissing them.  The primary issue both authors identify as the problem with technology is our non-critical acceptance of new tools into our lives as progress, the addictive nature of these services, and how they then impact our brains. Because we turn to technology for distraction and easy comfort whenever we’re bored, we lose our capacity for deeper engagement with the world and can lose sight of more important things.</p>
<p>Each book also decries the problems with “constant connectivity culture”.  Deep Work comes at it from a pure productivity standpoint: expectations of constant availability create distractions that prevent us from getting into the flow of meaningful work, and when we’re answering emails at all hours of the day, we don’t get the context shifts where our brains can rest and help us be more productive later.  The Common Rule shares these concerns but is more interested in how these distractions can shape our thinking and emotions: when we get sucked into the world of social media news for instance, is the anger we feel about issues a reflection of our true priorities or a path that we’ve fallen down.  It also asks us to consider how long term media-consumption may shape these believes and not just distract from them.</p>
<p>Finally, both authors touch on the amount of time we spend on meaningless activities.  Whether it is busy work, meetings, social media usage we feel we “have to do” or “real work” that just isn’t the most important work, both books encourage readers to value their time and be strategic about how to spend it.  They share a rare humble view of the human condition: we really do need to work with only 24 hours a day.  How to “make the most of them” is a core focus of each book.</p>
<h3>A Suprisingly Similar Recommendation</h3>
<p>In addition to a shared view of the problems people face, both books share a fairly similar approach to solving them.  Both books recommend ritualized structuring of life to reduce time spent on shallow, distracting activities and enable time for “the good life”.</p>
<p>So… what is “ritualized structuring”?  Both books spend significant time outlying a series of recommended habits/rituals that combine to help make us more aware of how our time is spent, and also serve as enabling spaces for “the good life”.  Deep work recommends (among other things) structured work hours, work-free evenings, social media avoidance and end of the day “shutdown rituals” where you clean up todos and make a schedule for the next day.  The Common Rule advocates for taking an hour away from your phone each day, a meal with others each day, curating media to 4 hours each week as well as more obviously religious habits like daily prayer and a sabbath day.</p>
<p>Each book offers these habits as “focusing tools”, ways to spend time on what is important and focus on the “good life”.  So what is the “good life”? Well…</p>
<h3>A Subtly Different Motivation</h3>
<p>The biggest difference between Deep Work and The Common Rule is what they’re aiming to enable.  What is the “good life” that we want to unlock as we wade out of the shallows?</p>
<p>Deep Work sees “Deep Work” as both a good in itself and a means to career success.  Deep Work allows for craftsmanship and an impact on the world greater than we’re normally able to achieve.  And because it is both important and implicitly discouraged by the modern office environment, clearing space for it is a tremendous competitive advantage when it comes to career success.</p>
<p>The Common Rule is explicitly focused on habits that turn us outward from ourselves; habits like a daily meal with others and a weekly hour of conversation with a friend are about connecting with the people around us, while daily prayer and weekly fasting are about connecting with God.  And ultimately they’re about health: when we connect well with God and others, we’re able to live in a way where we can accept our limitations and thrive where we are.</p>
<p>I don’t think the 2 philosophies are incompatible per say: you can work efficiently at work while valuing your relationships, as long as you’re willing to accept the inherent limitations of the 24 hour day.  But reading these 2 books back to back reminded me that “efficiency” is never an end to itself.  It’s always important to make sure you’re heading efficiently in the right direction.</p>
<h3>Recommendation</h3>
<p>I highly recommend both of these books.  They are full of fantastic suggestions that I plan on implementing over time (I’m trying to avoid my classic blunder of trying to change everything about my life at once and look for bits and pieces to attempt first). But as you take in the ideas, make sure to reflect on what the “good life” looks like to you.</p>
<h4>Amazon Links</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://amzn.to/2TqwDeR">Deep Work by Cal Newport</a></li>
<li><a href="https://amzn.to/2F0AIgV">The Common Rule by Justin Earley</a></li>
</ul>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>ben@benmccormick.org (Ben McCormick)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Importance of Writing For Software Developers]]></title>
            <link>https://benmccormick.org/2019/03/02/the-importance-of-writing</link>
            <guid>https://benmccormick.org/2019/03/02/the-importance-of-writing</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 02 Mar 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>Once somebody hits a minimum threshold of technical skill to hold a job in the industry, about 80% of their ability to succeed in Software Development is determined by their communication and people skills, not their technical abilities</p>
<p>- <em>Me, Christmas 2018</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>I think I caught my sister in law by surprise a bit when I answered her questions about the importance of writing in my job that way.  She’s an assistant professor who teaches writing to college students, and has found that her students pursuing technical degrees generally fail to see the value in learning to write.  The contrast between their expectations and my perspective after a decade working in software was strong.  I promised her at the time that I’d write down some thoughts on why writing skills are valuable for software engineers.  So here it is, 6 reasons that writing skills are crucial for working in the tech industry<sup id="fnref-1"><a href="#fn-1" class="footnote-ref">1</a></sup>.</p>
<h4>1. You will write every day</h4>
<p>Every industry has truths that are obvious to those who have spent time working in the industry, but may be surprising to those on the outside.  One such truth for software engineers: our jobs involve an awful lot of writing.  Here are a few types of writing that I’ve done daily or weekly for the last decade:</p>
<ol>
<li>Discussing technical implementations through chat apps like slack</li>
<li>Writing Bug Reports</li>
<li>Writing comments in my code and technical documentation to help others and my future self understand what was done</li>
<li>Writing reviews of other developers code to help our team improve and coordinate on best practices</li>
<li>Answering questions from less technical employees or clients, often through email or slack.</li>
<li>Creating design documents for complex work during planning times</li>
</ol>
<p>That list is illustrative but not exhaustive.  Any software engineer who wishes to build software that is used by others will end up doing plenty of writing.</p>
<h4>2. The ability to explain complex topics will set you apart</h4>
<p>The ability to take a complex topic and explain it in terms that somebody who doesn’t have all the background you do can understand is a critical one for software engineers.  This can help negate two of the most frustrating experiences for a developer:</p>
<ol>
<li>A business asking for work that doesn’t make sense because the business folks don’t understand how the product works</li>
<li>Less experienced members of the the team routinely making mistakes and breaking things because they don’t understand how the product works</li>
</ol>
<p>Senior engineers who can explain and document complex pieces of software save everyone frustration by helping junior members of the team understand how things work and be more productive, and by aligning business expectations and plans to the reality of how their software systems actually work.  These are hugely valuable activities that can make a big difference in your career.</p>
<h4>3. Writing will help you find a (better) job</h4>
<p>When I’ve interviewed software engineers, I see a variety of problems: they fail to present their strengths, don’t manage to show a sincere interest in the job, and get caught flat-footed on fairly standard questions.  Most of these mistakes come down to a lack of preparation, not tailoring their message to their audience, and not knowing how to structure the information they know about themselves in a compelling way.  These are the skills that you’ll learn from a good class on writing, and develop through practice writing.</p>
<p>Interviews are important, especially early on in your career.  Your compensation as you go throughout your career tends to be anchored to where you started, especially if you stay one place for a long time.  An increase of $5,000 in salary on a job you take today would mean an additional $92,000 of accumulated income over the next 15 years assuming a salary increase rate of 3% a year<sup id="fnref-2"><a href="#fn-2" class="footnote-ref">2</a></sup>.</p>
<p>In addition if you write publicly on a blog like this, it can help you show proof of your knowledge in a way that a resume never will.  Not everybody needs to be publicly blogging, but if that appeals to you it can be a great career booster.</p>
<h4>4. Remote work increases the importance of writing</h4>
<p>One of the biggest trends in the tech industry these days is the <a href="https://www.zenefits.com/blog/remote-workforce-rise/">rise of remote work</a>. More teams are embracing partial remote work, and there are major companies like Buffer, Invision and GitLab that are entirely remote.  Remote work is partially enabled by video chat technology, but written communication is the lifeblood of a successful remote team. Collaborating via tools like Slack, Github, Trello and Jira is part of most teams’ workflows, but when everybody is remote, being able to express yourself clearly on these platforms is critical.</p>
<h4>5. Your career trajectory will depend on your ability to influence and persuade</h4>
<p>Most developers when they begin their first software job will be given a set of tasks to do and the expectation is that they will create work to the spec that somebody else has designed.  They are implementors.  But as a developers career progresses there is an opportunity to be more than an implementor.  Since developers understand the system best, they often have ideas that can help shape product designs.  Developers also often need to work with other teams whose goals may not be completely aligned with their team.  These are not situations where even a senior engineer is likely to have direct authority.  Instead the developers who continue to grow in their careers are those who are able to influence and persuade without authority.</p>
<p>This is again a skill that writing classes can cultivate.  Persuasive writing practice can help give you the clarity of thought and intuition for structuring arguments that will help both when you’re trying to make a point through writing or doing it verbally.</p>
<h4>6. Writing skills translate to writing code</h4>
<p>This last one is really specific to software engineering, but I’ve found that applying writing principles to code has helped me write more maintainable code.  Most code written in a professional context will be read many times by other people (or by the original author after they have long lost track of their original context).  Being able to write code that can be understood by both a computer and by human beings is a skill developed over time, but many of the same “brain muscles” that you develop in writing prose can be applied to code: it’s important to know your audience, structure your information in a logical manner, and use judgement when finding just the right phrase (or code structure) for a situation.  That could be a whole post in itself.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn-1">
<p>I write based on the tech industry and software development specifically because that is what I have lived, but most of these points should be equally applicable to any engineering career and would likely require very little modification for science and research as well.</p>
<a href="#fnref-1" class="footnote-backref">↩</a>
</li>
<li id="fn-2">
<p>Ok real world promotion rates in the tech industry are likely to be choppier than that, but the example holds.</p>
<a href="#fnref-2" class="footnote-backref">↩</a>
</li>
</ol>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>ben@benmccormick.org (Ben McCormick)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How To Keep Learning JavaScript]]></title>
            <link>https://benmccormick.org/2019/02/18/how-to-keep-learning-js</link>
            <guid>https://benmccormick.org/2019/02/18/how-to-keep-learning-js</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 18 Feb 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>A member of my team at work asked me last week how I continue to learn things about JavaScript.  This is my answer. Note that it is focused on leveling up for folks with existing programming experience, not giving the best pathway into the field.</em></p>
<p>I’m going to break this up into 3 parts.</p>
<ol>
<li>The different ways people tackle learning new programming things</li>
<li>An inventory of the different types of resources out there for learning programming</li>
<li>My specific recommendations for JavaScript and React resources</li>
</ol>
<p>The first 3 are going to be generalizable to any type of learning about programming you want to pursue (and probably other fields as well).  The last one is necessarily more specific.</p>
<h4>Learning Strategies</h4>
<p>It’s helpful to start by talking about the different ways that people learn programming concepts.  We can break things up into 3 categories:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Practical</strong>:  This is where you work on projects and pursue goals, and learn the things you need as you need them.</li>
<li><strong>Topical</strong>: This is when you commit to learning something about a certain set of topics that you think will be valuable.  This may be related to work you’re doing, but your goal is a deep understanding of the topic moreso than trying to solve a specific problem.</li>
<li><strong>Serendipitous</strong>: This type of learning isn’t directed at all.  You’re just diving into learning as you encounter new terms or concepts, trying to absorb and understand everything.</li>
</ul>
<p>So which one is best?  You’ll hear arguments for all three, but personally I see learning like investing; it’s a long term game that you can’t win in a day, the gains accumulate slowly until suddenly you’re a long way from where you started, and one of the keys is diversifying.</p>
<p>Practical knowledge is safe; when you focus on learning things you need, you’ll rarely waste your time, will likely get more done, and will put yourself in a position to learn more interesting things as you develop a reputation for doing good work.  However focusing solely on learning the things you need to do your current job may blind you to trends and eventually leave you with an out of date skill set. In addition, while you may be looking for answers to practical problems, if your knowledge base is narrow to start you may miss out on innovative ideas because you don’t have exposure to solutions that might not “google well” for the way you think of your current needs.</p>
<p>Topical knowledge can be very useful when jumping into a new area of work: sometimes you just need a level of exposure to the syntax, concepts and tools behind a language, framework or project before you can effectively work with it.  But learning about a topic divorced from a project can sometimes feel more productive in the moment than it actually ends up being: without practical experience of the pain points that the topic is solving for and/or causing, it can be hard to know what is important and make the connections that you really need. Topical learning can also devolve into a purely academic exercise where you never really learn to apply what you know.</p>
<p>Serendipitous learning on the face of it is the most easily wasted; trying to learn everything can be overwhelming in programming, a field based on layers of abstractions, with a plethora of different subfields that can be explored for years without learning everything. However sometimes it is the dash of inspiration that comes from bringing previously disconnected ideas together that leads to the creation of something novel and great.  And those types of connection only come from somebody who is learning broadly as well as deeply.  Being curious also prevents the pitfalls of purely practical learning: dead-ends and blind spots. So there is a place for serendipitous learning too.</p>
<p>The best approach is a mix of the 3: have real problems that you’re trying to solve, but make sure to keep an eye out for interesting things, and don’t be afraid of the occasional deep dive into a useful sounding topic.</p>
<h3>Resource Types</h3>
<p>There are so many ways to learn things in the programming world.  Below is a brief roundup of resource types, ordered roughly in terms of stability and how rapidly they produce new material.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Academic Courses</strong> - College, bootcamps, Coursera, etc:  These are the ultimate in topical learning.  Not something that most people are doing every day, but can be great for rebooting a career if you want to head in a new direction or refresh after being away from the field for a while.</li>
<li><strong>Books</strong> - People are still writing programming books.  These tend to fall into 2 categories: books about a specific framework or technique and more “timeless” books about some fundamental part of how we write software. The first group tends. to age fast but can be great for topical learning, the second are an essential resource for “higher level” thinking about our field.</li>
<li><strong>Video Courses</strong> - In recent years, video courses seem to have grown in popularity as a way of teaching programming.  They’ve never been my cup of tea, but they can be great topical guides to new subjects for visual learners who don’t want to commit to a full academic course.</li>
<li><strong>Wikis</strong> - There are several places online where developers aggregate documentation in an open way.  <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/">Stack Overflow</a> and <a href="https://www.wikipedia.org/">Wikipedia</a> are the most prominent.  These can be an excellent authoritative source to start looking for answers that still are able to remain relevant as best practices and trends change.</li>
<li><strong>Blogs</strong> -  Blogs come in a variety of flavors.  They can be focused profitable publishing platforms with multiple authors like <a href="https://css-tricks.com/">CSS Tricks</a> or occasionally updates on a variety of topics from an individual developer.  They tend to be the best source for in depth “how tos” on niche topics that might not justify a book or be fully covered by a wiki.</li>
<li><strong>Podcasts</strong> - There are lots of developer podcasts out there.  Due to the audio nature of the medium, they tend to be more focused on high level ideas and less likely to drift into the nitty gritty of code.</li>
<li><strong>Newsletters</strong> - Newsletters like this one can be a great way to get regular updates from knowledgeable developers or receive aggregations of interesting links. I’ve personally found them more and more valuable in recent years as a way of bringing the best content to the surface.</li>
<li><strong>Github/Looking at code</strong> - Sometimes the best way to learn is to go straight to the source.  We live in a golden age of open source software, where billions of lines of code are available for anyone to look at online.  Code is ultimately the source of truth.</li>
<li><strong>Forums, Mailing Lists &#x26; Chat Groups</strong> - Many technologies, geographic areas and interest groups have vibrant online communities that can be a great source of learning.  In the past these groups tended to exist as mailing groups, IRC channels or forum sites.  But nowadays the most popular form of community seems to be chat groups implemented with Slack or Discord.</li>
<li><strong>Conferences</strong> - These aren’t something that most of us can do regularly, but conferences are a great place to be introduced to new ideas and make connections with people in a tech community.</li>
<li><strong>Meetup Groups</strong> - A more accessible option than conferences for many people, most mid-sized and larger cities have multiple tech meetup groups that can be a good place to grow a tech community and be introduced to new concepts</li>
<li><strong>Aggregators</strong> - Aggregator sites like <a href="https://www.reddit.com/">Reddit</a> and <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/">Hacker News</a> are useful places to encounter new ideas.  Compared to the options above, they’re much noisier; you’ll encounter a mix of content quality and topics.  But it can be a great way to find serendipitous ideas and find new blogs, podcasts and communities to follow.</li>
<li><strong>Social Media</strong> - Social Media sites (especially Twitter) can be a great way to get a sense of whats on a tech communities collective mind, and encounter concepts and ideas while they’re still being formed.  But it also can be a distracting mess of noise.  So consider moderating your intake.</li>
</ul>
<p>I’d generally recommend a mix of the resources above, though you’ll find some are more helpful to you than others I personally have found that books, blogs, newsletters, wikis and aggregators have been the most useful for me personally, as well as finding ways to teach others through meetup groups, conferences and my own blog.  There is real truth in the idea that the best way to learn something well is to teach it.</p>
<h3>Specific Resources</h3>
<p>So the above stuff is all pretty generic.  I’ll end by listing some resources that I’ve found personally helpful in learning and keeping up with the JavaScript and React world.  This isn’t exhaustive, and I know there are a lot of great resources out there that I haven’t personally used.  But this is my list:</p>
<h4>Books</h4>
<ul>
<li>
<p><a href="https://leanpub.com/javascriptallongesix">JavaScript Allongé</a> is a great ebook about functional JavaScript.  It was very influential for me in terms of how I structure my code.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2TTXlZt">Effective JavaScript</a> is a bit dated now; it was written pre-ES6.  But it’s the best non-beginner book I’ve read about the JavaScript language.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2GNviXY">Clean Architecture</a> is my favorite book on Software Architecture.  If you want to think about how we structure programs at a higher level, it is worth a read</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2GPi6ll">A Philosophy of Software Design</a> is a book I’ve mentioned a few times recently here; Its my new recommendation for a first “writing better code” book because its so concise.  <a href="https://amzn.to/2TRAPAl">The Pragmatic Programmer</a> played that role for me personally though, and I’d still recommend it as well for any developer who hasn’t read it.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="http://atomicdesign.bradfrost.com/">Atomic Design</a> is a great book on building modern design systems, and has been useful for me as I think about how to break down UIs in my development work.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h4>Video Courses</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://egghead.io/">Egghead.io</a> is the best source for dev video content I’ve found.  Video has never really been my jam, I prefer text content where I can go through it at my pace and easily reference back and forth between it and code.  But it can be great to get a focused intro to a topic, and Egghead seems to have nailed the format with its collection of short focused snippets. It’s mostly a paid service, but there is a bunch of great free content on there, especially beginner React stuff.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Wikis</h4>
<p>These are maybe stupid obvious, but I’ve learned more from these 3 sites than probably anything else listed here:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://stackoverflow.com/">Stack Overflow</a> is the single best source for software development information on the internet.  Note that I would advise most people to use it as more of a googleable resource than a place to ask questions; they’re focused on documenting canonical answers to common problems moreso than chasing down situational issues, and for popular technologies they are fairly comprehensive.</li>
<li><a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/">MDN</a> is my site of choice for learning about browser APIs and JavaScript/CSS/HTML language features.  It’s extremely reliable, and generally very readable (although some articles are much more detailed than others).</li>
<li><a href="https://www.wikipedia.org/">Wikipedia</a> is a surprisingly great place to learn about general computer science concepts.  I wouldn’t use it for front end specific stuff, there are better resources there, but if I want to learn about a classical computer science concept like a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Priority_queue">priority queue</a> or <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dijkstra%27s_algorithm">Dijkstra’s algorithm</a> wikipedia usually has a pretty robust article giving the basic background.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Blogs</h4>
<p>For blogs, I highly recommend getting a good RSS reader so you can keep up with posts as they come.  My tool of choice here is <a href="https://feedbin.com/">Feedbin</a> for which I pay a very small monthly fee, but there are good free alternatives like <a href="/https://feedly.com/">Feedly</a> as well.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://2ality.com/">2ality</a> is a blog focused on new JavaScript features as they work their way through the TC39 development process.  It’s the best resource I know of for understanding what is coming down the language pipeline, and also learning about new features when they are released.</li>
<li><a href="https://overreacted.io/">Overreacted</a> is Dan Abramov’s “Advanced React” blog.  It’s the best single source of knowledge on React that I’ve seen.</li>
<li><a href="https://css-tricks.com/">CSS Tricks</a> is more of a mega-blog, with multiple articles published a day by a variety of authors.  It’s consistently high quality content, and even though it leans more towards “web site development” than “web app development” there is stuff here that anyone will find interesting.  It’s also been around a long time and has great historical resources for learning newish CSS standards like CSS Grid and Flexbox.</li>
<li><a href="https://reactjs.org/blog/">The official React Blog</a> is excellent and a great place to get “official news” about React.  The same applies for other frameworks like Ember, Vue, and Angular; you always want to be following the official source and not just getting your news from the community.  It greatly reduces the chances of misunderstanding and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cargo_cult_programming">cargo culting</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://benmccormick.org">benmccormick.org</a>.  Ok I’m sort of kidding here, but the truth is that having my own blog has been one of the best ways for me to learn; I learn when I write, I can reference back to older posts when I’m re-engaging with a topic, and things stick better when you write them down.  Plus when I write posts like this where I’m linking other resources, its easier for me to find those resources later. (but uh… feel free to tell everyone to <a href="https://benmccormick.org/subscribe">subscribe</a> to my blog anyway)</li>
</ul>
<h4>Newsletter</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://javascriptweekly.com/">JavaScript Weekly</a> is a great “list of links” style newsletter every week.  If you just want a pulse of the weekly news in the JS community, I think this is the best place to find it.</li>
<li><a href="https://kentcdodds.com/subscribe/">Kent C Dodds’ Newsletter</a> is a great resource for React and JavaScript testing.</li>
<li><a href="https://hackernewsletter.com/">Hacker Newsletter</a> is a roundup of the top <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/">Hacker News</a> posts each week.  Hacker News can be a bit of a mess (the comments are often written from deep within the startup bubble and the quality of links at any given time on the site is mixed) but it’s an amazing source of interesting content if you’re willing to wade through it.  This newsletter lets somebody else do that for you.</li>
<li><a href="https://this-week-in-react.org/">This week in React</a> is another source of advanced React content.  It’s actually just a summary of the interesting things going on in the React repo itself.  So if you’re interested in contributing to React or want to see how they’re progressing against their roadmap, it’s an interesting and quick read each week.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Aggregators &#x26; Social Media</h4>
<p>Honestly, 2 years ago I probably would have led with this section; Twitter and Hacker News were a huge part of how I have found interesting content and built my skills over the past 5 years.  But I’ve gotten disenchanted with them over time as they became part of a broader issue of my increasing inability to focus on things because of the abundance of technology related distractions in my life.  So… caveat emptor.  That said here are some people I’d recommend following on Twitter if you’re interested in React and JavaScript.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>React</strong> - <a href="https://twitter.com/dan_abramov">Dan Abramov</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/kentcdodds">Kent C Dodds</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/ryanflorence">Ryan Florence</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/acemarke">Mark Erikson</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/swyx">Shawn Wang</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/rauchg">Guillermo Rauch</a></li>
<li><strong>JavaScript</strong> - <a href="https://twitter.com/ladyleet">Tracy Lee</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/_developit">Jason Miller</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/slicknet">Nicholas Zakas</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/sarah_edo">Sarah Drasner</a></li>
</ul>
<h3>A final note</h3>
<p>I just want to end where I started, and encourage you to not rush out and try to absorb all of these things at once, but instead work on projects and find the resources that give you what you need.  And then explore a bit on the side to help yourself grow.  Your resources will probably be different than mine.  The internet is huge, the world is even bigger. Explore and have fun!</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>ben@benmccormick.org (Ben McCormick)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Strategic Coding]]></title>
            <link>https://benmccormick.org/2019/02/18/strategic-coding</link>
            <guid>https://benmccormick.org/2019/02/18/strategic-coding</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 18 Feb 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I recently read <a href="https://amzn.to/2Elk5g8">A Philosophy Of Software Design</a> by John Ousterhout.  In an early chapter he paints a picture of a “tactical tornado” programmer, a programmer who is always focused on solving the current problem by the most expedient method possible, with no thought to the long term implications.  I suspect anyone with even a few years in the programming has seen programmers like this, and has also from time to time written “tactical” code like this themselves.  Ousterhout’s recommendation is instead to write code strategically rather than tactically, taking more up front time to plan the structure for the benefit of longer term productivity.</p>
<p>Ousterhout focuses his examination of tactical vs strategic coding on the issue of complexity.  Complexity as he defines it is anything that makes the system difficult to work with.  It is the root issue behind much of the <em>ease of change</em> concern I identified in my <a href="https://benmccormick.org/2019/01/07/the-concerns-of-fe-architecture/">recent post</a>.  But we can expand this to encompass all of the front end concerns.  We can easily impact reliability, performance, ease of change, accessibility, security and capability when we make short hand tradeoffs.</p>
<p>Let’s consider the problem of getting a new sign up page set up for a site.  There are several different approaches we could take.  By far the simplest is a basic HTML page using normal CSS and little or no JavaScript, that posts to a backend service after the signup and then redirects to a different static page.  We could set this up on S3 or any other service that will host static files.  On the other extreme, we could set up a new server side rendered Typescript-based React application that uses Next.js to give us server side rendering, which we deploy using Docker and a fully automated CI build system with chatbot ops.  Which one of these approaches is better?</p>
<p>A tactical tornado would likely prefer the first solution.  They could get the whole thing up and running in an hour, stamp it and call it done.  Other developers might be attracted to the <em>cool</em> approach and want to avoid the “outdated” approach.  But we can only really answer the question by stepping back and asking some questions:</p>
<ul>
<li>What is the future of this application?  Is this a standalone page, or the first page in a larger application?</li>
<li>What feature requests are we likely to get for the page?  Is it probable that we’ll eventually need form validation, dynamic success and failure states, complex behavior that depends on the use case?</li>
<li>What browsers are we supporting</li>
<li>What are our performance benchmarks?</li>
</ul>
<p>Questions like that can tell us when we’ll benefit from an up front investment in certain areas, and when it’s wiser to be quick and dirty.  They also allow us to evaluate whether any options we’re considering might cut us off from achieving long term goals.  For instance, if we know that we’ll eventually need to scale this site into a large application with responsive interactions, personalized content and information maintained between page loads, building this out as a series of static pages which POST to a backend would eventually limit our capabilities or require a refactor.  But if this is only a one-off landing page for an event happening next week that won’t be maintained beyond that point, developing a long-term maintenance strategy would be wasted effort.  This is <em>strategic coding</em>, and it doesn’t stop at the beginning of a project, it’s an ongoing mindset that you can take as you add each new feature to an application.</p>
<p>Ousterhout makes a case that aligns with my experience, that strategic programming is a long term winner.  I’ve seen that over time improvements to ease of change will often help a team save time lost, significant hits to performance, security, reliability may hurt them more than a fast solution saves them, and solutions that unreasonably limit us in terms of system capability or accessibility will ultimately get rejected.  The weasel words there exist for a reason… sometimes it really is the best idea to just get something working.  But a strategic programmer will understand the context of their project, and make wise choices about where and how to invest in the codebase.</p>
<p><strong>TL;DR</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>It is possible to program either tactically or strategically</strong></li>
<li><strong>Tactical programming is focused on solving the immediate problem as quickly as possible</strong></li>
<li><strong>Strategic coding considers the context of the problem, and any architectural concerns involved in a change</strong></li>
<li><strong>Strategic coding doesn’t mean never hacking and always investing, it means letting context inform the amount and direction of investment in a codebase</strong></li>
</ul>
<p>PS: I put a <a href="https://benmccormick.org/2018/12/31/book-review-philosophy-of-software-design/">full review of A Philosophy of Software Design</a> up on the site a few weeks ago.  Check it out :)</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>ben@benmccormick.org (Ben McCormick)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Reusable Code In React: Inheritance, Composition, Decorators and Mixins]]></title>
            <link>https://benmccormick.org/2019/02/11/reusable-react</link>
            <guid>https://benmccormick.org/2019/02/11/reusable-react</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 11 Feb 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Once you get past the initial complexity it creates by bucking conventions, React is the most developer friendly UI library I have ever used.  A big reason for that is the way it uses and encourages a variety of patterns to share codes and concepts across a code base. Let’s look at how 4 traditional code re-use patterns are used by React and in the React ecosystem, using a simple counter example to explore why each pattern is used.</p>
<h4>Inheritance</h4>
<p>Inheritance is a code-reuse technique associated with object oriented programming.  If you’re like me and learned to program in school using Java, it probably is one of the very first Computer Science concepts you learned.  For self-taught JavaScript devs it may be much less familiar.  Inheritance is a pattern for extending an existing class or object with additional methods or data, possibly overriding the implementations of other methods in the process.  A classic example of inheritance looks like this in JS:</p>
<div class="gatsby-highlight" data-language="javascript">
      <pre class="language-javascript"><code class="language-javascript"><span class="token keyword">class</span> <span class="token class-name">Automobile</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
    <span class="token function">constructor</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
        <span class="token keyword">this</span><span class="token punctuation">.</span>vehicleName <span class="token operator">=</span> automobile<span class="token punctuation">;</span>
        <span class="token keyword">this</span><span class="token punctuation">.</span>numWheels <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token keyword">null</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
    <span class="token punctuation">}</span>
    <span class="token function">printNumWheels</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
        console<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">log</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token template-string"><span class="token string">`This </span><span class="token interpolation"><span class="token interpolation-punctuation punctuation">${</span><span class="token keyword">this</span><span class="token punctuation">.</span>vehicleName<span class="token interpolation-punctuation punctuation">}</span></span><span class="token string"> has </span><span class="token interpolation"><span class="token interpolation-punctuation punctuation">${</span><span class="token keyword">this</span><span class="token punctuation">.</span>numWheels<span class="token interpolation-punctuation punctuation">}</span></span><span class="token string"> wheels`</span></span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
    <span class="token punctuation">}</span>
<span class="token punctuation">}</span>

<span class="token keyword">class</span> <span class="token class-name">Car</span> <span class="token keyword">extends</span> <span class="token class-name">Automobile</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
    <span class="token function">constructor</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
        <span class="token keyword">super</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token keyword">this</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
        <span class="token keyword">this</span><span class="token punctuation">.</span>vehicleName <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token string">'car'</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
        <span class="token keyword">this</span><span class="token punctuation">.</span>numWheels <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token number">4</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
    <span class="token punctuation">}</span>
<span class="token punctuation">}</span>

<span class="token keyword">class</span> <span class="token class-name">Bicycle</span> <span class="token keyword">extends</span> <span class="token class-name">Automobile</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
    <span class="token function">constructor</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
        <span class="token keyword">super</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token keyword">this</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
        <span class="token keyword">this</span><span class="token punctuation">.</span>vehicleName <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token string">'bike'</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
        <span class="token keyword">this</span><span class="token punctuation">.</span>numWheels <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token number">2</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
    <span class="token punctuation">}</span>
<span class="token punctuation">}</span>

<span class="token keyword">const</span> car <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token keyword">new</span> <span class="token class-name">Car</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
<span class="token keyword">const</span> bike <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token keyword">new</span> <span class="token class-name">Bicycle</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
car<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">printNumWheels</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token comment">// This car has 4 wheels</span>
bike<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">printNumWheels</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token comment">// This bike has 2 wheels</span></code></pre>
      </div>
<p>Inheritance is useful for highly structured objects where you have a lot of shared behavior across similar but slightly different objects and you want to be able to treat all of the objects as interchangeable from an API perspective. This is especially valuable when that interchangeable API is well defined and unlikely to change too much.  However it tends to lead to brittle structures when nested across multiple levels, and is a poor fit when dealing with dissimilar objects that need to share a few behaviors.</p>
<p>React Components are objects that we want to treat as interchangeable from an outside API perspective, and they have well defined points where behavior may need to be different between components but don’t always need to differ: the lifecycle methods like render, componentDidMount, componentWillUnmount, etc.  Thus React relies on a single level of inheritance as the foundation of its class components.  Class components inherit from React.Component, and only implement the life cycle methods that they’re interested in.  But all of them inherit useable setState and forceUpdate functions, and React can verify that by checking the <code class="language-text">isReactComponent</code> property on the object.</p>
<p>Here is a basic counter component.  Notice how we don’t have to define <code class="language-text">setState</code> on our <code class="language-text">Counter</code> class.  Instead it inherits it from React.Component.</p>
<div class="gatsby-highlight" data-language="javascript">
      <pre class="language-javascript"><code class="language-javascript"><span class="token comment">//counter.js</span>
<span class="token keyword">class</span> <span class="token class-name">Counter</span> <span class="token keyword">extends</span> <span class="token class-name">React<span class="token punctuation">.</span>Component</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
    <span class="token function">constructor</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>props<span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
        <span class="token keyword">super</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>props<span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
        <span class="token keyword">this</span><span class="token punctuation">.</span>state <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
            count<span class="token punctuation">:</span> <span class="token number">0</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span>
        <span class="token punctuation">}</span>
    <span class="token punctuation">}</span>
    <span class="token function">render</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
        <span class="token keyword">let</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>count<span class="token punctuation">}</span> <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token keyword">this</span><span class="token punctuation">.</span>state<span class="token punctuation">;</span>
        <span class="token keyword">let</span> <span class="token function-variable function">increment</span> <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token operator">=></span> <span class="token keyword">this</span><span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">setState</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>state <span class="token operator">=></span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
            <span class="token keyword">return</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
               count<span class="token punctuation">:</span> state<span class="token punctuation">.</span>count <span class="token operator">+</span> <span class="token number">1</span>
            <span class="token punctuation">}</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
        <span class="token punctuation">}</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
        <span class="token keyword">return</span> <span class="token operator">&lt;</span>div className<span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token string">"fancy-layout"</span><span class="token operator">></span>
            <span class="token operator">&lt;</span>div className<span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token string">"fancy-display"</span><span class="token operator">></span>
                Current Count<span class="token punctuation">:</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>count<span class="token punctuation">}</span>
            <span class="token operator">&lt;</span><span class="token operator">/</span>div<span class="token operator">></span>
            <span class="token operator">&lt;</span>button
                className<span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token string">"incrementCounterBtn fancy-btn"</span>
                onClick<span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token punctuation">{</span>increment<span class="token punctuation">}</span>
            <span class="token operator">></span>Increment<span class="token operator">&lt;</span><span class="token operator">/</span>button<span class="token operator">></span>
        <span class="token operator">&lt;</span><span class="token operator">/</span>div<span class="token operator">></span>
    <span class="token punctuation">}</span>
<span class="token punctuation">}</span></code></pre>
      </div>
<p>Outside of this single layer of inheritance for defining Class components, inheritance isn’t used much in React development.  It turns out that better patterns have emerged for sharing application code.</p>
<p><strong>Inheritance Pattern</strong>: Used sparingly to share common code across React class components.</p>
<h4>Composition</h4>
<p>Composition is a code reuse technique where a larger object is created by combining multiple smaller objects.  Composition is in some ways the natural pattern of the browser, as HTML uses it.  We build a table in html, not by adding a bunch of configuration to a single table object, but by combining a <code class="language-text">table</code> tag with <code class="language-text">tr</code>s, <code class="language-text">td</code>s, and <code class="language-text">th</code>s like this:</p>
<div class="gatsby-highlight" data-language="html">
      <pre class="language-html"><code class="language-html"><span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;</span>table</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span>
    <span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;</span>thead</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span>
        <span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;</span>tr</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span><span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;</span>th</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span>Web Framework<span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;/</span>th</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span><span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;</span>th</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span>Language<span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;/</span>th</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span><span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;/</span>tr</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span>
    <span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;/</span>thead</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span>
    <span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;</span>tbody</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span>
        <span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;</span>tr</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span><span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;</span>th</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span>Rails<span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;/</span>th</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span><span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;</span>th</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span>Ruby<span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;/</span>th</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span><span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;/</span>tr</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span>
        <span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;</span>tr</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span><span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;</span>th</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span>Django<span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;/</span>th</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span><span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;</span>th</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span>Python<span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;/</span>th</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span><span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;/</span>tr</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span>
        <span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;</span>tr</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span><span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;</span>th</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span>Flask<span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;/</span>th</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span><span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;</span>th</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span>Python<span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;/</span>th</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span><span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;/</span>tr</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span>
        <span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;</span>tr</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span><span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;</span>th</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span>Play<span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;/</span>th</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span><span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;</span>th</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span>Scala<span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;/</span>th</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span><span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;/</span>tr</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span>
        <span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;</span>tr</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span><span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;</span>th</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span>Play<span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;/</span>th</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span><span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;</span>th</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span>Java<span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;/</span>th</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span><span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;/</span>tr</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span>
        <span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;</span>tr</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span><span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;</span>th</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span>Express<span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;/</span>th</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span><span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;</span>th</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span>JavaScript<span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;/</span>th</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span><span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;/</span>tr</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span>
    <span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;/</span>tbody</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span>
<span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;/</span>table</span><span class="token punctuation">></span></span></code></pre>
      </div>
<p>React has fully embraced the HTML style of composing UI components, and it takes thing to the next level by allowing components to be stateful and pass values down into children.  For instance, if we wanted to split the counter component above into a separate control and display, perhaps using a standard set of UI components we could do it by extracting <code class="language-text">FancyLayout</code>, <code class="language-text">FancyButton</code> and <code class="language-text">FancyDisplay</code> elements out into their own components and then composing them back into a single counter component.  This type of thing is useful for creating and reusing standard UI elements, and might look something like the following:</p>
<div class="gatsby-highlight" data-language="javascript">
      <pre class="language-javascript"><code class="language-javascript"><span class="token comment">// UI components defined elsewhere</span>
<span class="token keyword">const</span> <span class="token function-variable function">FancyLayout</span> <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">{</span>children<span class="token punctuation">}</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token operator">=></span> <span class="token operator">&lt;</span>div className<span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token string">"fancy-layout"</span><span class="token operator">></span><span class="token punctuation">{</span>children<span class="token punctuation">}</span><span class="token operator">&lt;</span><span class="token operator">/</span>div<span class="token operator">></span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
<span class="token keyword">const</span> <span class="token function-variable function">FancyDisplay</span> <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">{</span>children<span class="token punctuation">}</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token operator">=></span> <span class="token operator">&lt;</span>div className<span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token string">"fancy-display"</span><span class="token operator">></span><span class="token punctuation">{</span>children<span class="token punctuation">}</span><span class="token operator">&lt;</span><span class="token operator">/</span>div<span class="token operator">></span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
<span class="token keyword">const</span> <span class="token function-variable function">FancyButton</span> <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">{</span>children<span class="token punctuation">,</span> className<span class="token punctuation">,</span> onClick<span class="token punctuation">}</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token operator">=></span> <span class="token operator">&lt;</span>button
    className<span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token punctuation">{</span><span class="token template-string"><span class="token string">`fancy-layout </span><span class="token interpolation"><span class="token interpolation-punctuation punctuation">${</span>className<span class="token interpolation-punctuation punctuation">}</span></span><span class="token string">`</span></span><span class="token punctuation">}</span>
    onClick<span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token punctuation">{</span>onClick<span class="token punctuation">}</span>
    <span class="token operator">></span>
        <span class="token punctuation">{</span>children<span class="token punctuation">}</span>
    <span class="token operator">&lt;</span><span class="token operator">/</span>button<span class="token operator">></span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>


<span class="token comment">// counter.js</span>
<span class="token keyword">class</span> <span class="token class-name">Counter</span> <span class="token keyword">extends</span> <span class="token class-name">React<span class="token punctuation">.</span>Component</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
    <span class="token function">constructor</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>props<span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
        <span class="token keyword">super</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>props<span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
        <span class="token keyword">this</span><span class="token punctuation">.</span>state <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
            count<span class="token punctuation">:</span> <span class="token number">0</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span>
        <span class="token punctuation">}</span>
    <span class="token punctuation">}</span>
    <span class="token function">render</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
        <span class="token keyword">let</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>count<span class="token punctuation">}</span> <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token keyword">this</span><span class="token punctuation">.</span>state<span class="token punctuation">;</span>
         <span class="token keyword">let</span> <span class="token function-variable function">increment</span> <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token operator">=></span> <span class="token keyword">this</span><span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">setState</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>state <span class="token operator">=></span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
            <span class="token keyword">return</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
               count<span class="token punctuation">:</span> state<span class="token punctuation">.</span>count <span class="token operator">+</span> <span class="token number">1</span>
            <span class="token punctuation">}</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
        <span class="token punctuation">}</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
        <span class="token keyword">return</span> <span class="token operator">&lt;</span>FancyLayout<span class="token operator">></span>
            <span class="token operator">&lt;</span>FancyDisplay<span class="token operator">></span>
                Current Count<span class="token punctuation">:</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>count<span class="token punctuation">}</span>
            <span class="token operator">&lt;</span><span class="token operator">/</span>FancyDisplay<span class="token operator">></span>
            <span class="token operator">&lt;</span>FancyButton
                className<span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token string">"incrementCounterBtn"</span>
                onClick<span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token punctuation">{</span>increment<span class="token punctuation">}</span>
            <span class="token operator">></span>Increment<span class="token operator">&lt;</span><span class="token operator">/</span>FancyButton<span class="token operator">></span>
        <span class="token operator">&lt;</span><span class="token operator">/</span>FancyLayout<span class="token operator">></span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
    <span class="token punctuation">}</span>
<span class="token punctuation">}</span></code></pre>
      </div>
<p>In this example we now have 4 components instead of one.  Three of them are laser-focused on defining a specific element type, and are “display only” with no logic of their own.  The 4th contains all of our logic and defines how the display pieces come together.</p>
<p>In the seminal 1994 book <a href="https://amzn.to/2WDhncv">Design Patterns</a> the authors argue that composition should be strictly preferred over inheritance where possible because it creates less tightly coupled objects, and encourages designs where objects are small, focused and readable.  Composition also lets us hide complexity inside of child objects, because parent components only have to concern themselves with the APIs exposed by those child objects.  One of the keys to React’s success has been making this type of composition clean and painless by encouraging strong component interfaces and utilizing JSX to provide a comfortable syntax for describing composed UIs while keeping all component concerns in the same place<sup id="fnref-1"><a href="#fn-1" class="footnote-ref">1</a></sup>.</p>
<p>It is worth noting that after this refactor, our counting logic is still tightly tied to the layout of our counter component.  Let’s explore 2 more patterns that can help us extract our logic from the display completely.</p>
<p><strong>Composition Pattern</strong>: The core pattern for separating concerns while creating complex UIs with React.</p>
<h4>Decorators</h4>
<p>Decorators are a pattern for editing an instance of a class to give it additional behaviors than it had previously.  In contrast to inheritance, decorators are not part of the class definition, but are modifications to the class at run time to allow a subset of objects to have additional data or behavior <sup id="fnref-2"><a href="#fn-2" class="footnote-ref">2</a></sup>.  In classic object oriented programming, this was implemented by having a decorator class that shared an interface with the class to be decorated, and called its methods through to that class, with additional behavior before or after the pass-through.  The React community has generally implemented this pattern slightly differently, by writing functions that take a component class and return a new component class that calls through to the original component, possibly with additional props passed in, extra components rendered around it, or conditional logic that causes it not to render in some cases.  The React community generally refers to this pattern as <a href="https://reactjs.org/docs/higher-order-components.html">Higher Order Components</a>.</p>
<p>Here’s an example of using a higher order component called <code class="language-text">withCounter</code> to separate out the display and logic portions of our Counter component.</p>
<div class="gatsby-highlight" data-language="javascript">
      <pre class="language-javascript"><code class="language-javascript"><span class="token keyword">const</span> <span class="token function-variable function">withCounter</span> <span class="token operator">=</span> WrappedComponent <span class="token operator">=></span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
   <span class="token keyword">class</span> <span class="token class-name">ComponentWithCounter</span> <span class="token keyword">extends</span> <span class="token class-name">React<span class="token punctuation">.</span>Component</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
      <span class="token function">constructor</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>props<span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
         <span class="token keyword">super</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>props<span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
         <span class="token keyword">this</span><span class="token punctuation">.</span>state <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
            count<span class="token punctuation">:</span> <span class="token number">0</span>
         <span class="token punctuation">}</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
         <span class="token keyword">this</span><span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function-variable function">increment</span> <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token operator">=></span> <span class="token keyword">this</span><span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">setState</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>state <span class="token operator">=></span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
            <span class="token keyword">return</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
               count<span class="token punctuation">:</span> state<span class="token punctuation">.</span>count <span class="token operator">+</span> <span class="token number">1</span>
            <span class="token punctuation">}</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
         <span class="token punctuation">}</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
      <span class="token punctuation">}</span>

      <span class="token function">render</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
         <span class="token keyword">let</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>count<span class="token punctuation">}</span> <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token keyword">this</span><span class="token punctuation">.</span>state<span class="token punctuation">;</span>
         <span class="token keyword">return</span> <span class="token operator">&lt;</span>WrappedComponent count<span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token punctuation">{</span>count<span class="token punctuation">}</span> increment<span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token punctuation">{</span><span class="token keyword">this</span><span class="token punctuation">.</span>increment<span class="token punctuation">}</span> <span class="token operator">/</span><span class="token operator">></span>
      <span class="token punctuation">}</span>
  <span class="token punctuation">}</span>
  <span class="token keyword">return</span> ComponentWithCounter<span class="token punctuation">;</span>
<span class="token punctuation">}</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>

<span class="token comment">// counter.js</span>

<span class="token comment">// this is a display only version of the component with no logic</span>
<span class="token comment">// very easy to test and simple to change</span>
<span class="token keyword">class</span> <span class="token class-name">CounterDisplay</span> <span class="token keyword">extends</span> <span class="token class-name">React<span class="token punctuation">.</span>Component</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
    <span class="token function">render</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
        <span class="token keyword">let</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>count<span class="token punctuation">,</span> increment<span class="token punctuation">}</span> <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token keyword">this</span><span class="token punctuation">.</span>props<span class="token punctuation">;</span>
        <span class="token keyword">return</span> <span class="token operator">&lt;</span>FancyLayout<span class="token operator">></span>
            <span class="token operator">&lt;</span>FancyDisplay<span class="token operator">></span>
                Current Count<span class="token punctuation">:</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>count<span class="token punctuation">}</span>
            <span class="token operator">&lt;</span><span class="token operator">/</span>FancyDisplay<span class="token operator">></span>
            <span class="token operator">&lt;</span>FancyButton
                className<span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token string">"incrementCounterBtn"</span>
                onClick<span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token punctuation">{</span>increment<span class="token punctuation">}</span>
            <span class="token operator">></span>Increment<span class="token operator">&lt;</span><span class="token operator">/</span>FancyButton<span class="token operator">></span>
        <span class="token operator">&lt;</span><span class="token operator">/</span>FancyLayout<span class="token operator">></span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
    <span class="token punctuation">}</span>
<span class="token punctuation">}</span>

<span class="token comment">// this adds the logic back to the display only version</span>
<span class="token keyword">const</span> Counter <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token function">withCounter</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>CounterDisplay<span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span></code></pre>
      </div>
<p>Now we’ve taken our refactored <code class="language-text">Counter</code> and split it into 2 more pieces.  The display logic remains in a simplified <code class="language-text">CounterDisplay</code> component that doesn’t have any state or business logic of its own.  <code class="language-text">CounterDisplay</code> takes 2 new props, <code class="language-text">count</code> and <code class="language-text">increment</code> that allow it to implement the counting logic without having to know how it is implemented.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, we split the counting logic out into a Higher Order Component.  <code class="language-text">withCounter</code> takes a React component and wraps it with another component that is solely responsible for keeping track of counts and providing the increment function.  In this case that is our CounterDisplay component, but if we decided we wanted to also have fancy counters that incremented when the user clicked a checkbox or hovered over a box or typed the word increment, it would be easy to reuse this logic.</p>
<p>Higher Order Components helped many React libraries like Redux and React Router define elegant APIs when they first came on the scene, but they’ve always been a power user technique.  There are many ways to screw them up, and although they allow for theoretical loose coupling, they still require a certain level of shared understanding between the decorator and decoratee, including knowing what props to make available, whether any methods have to be proxied through to the decorated component, and more.  The community as a whole has tended to favor render props over the past year<sup id="fnref-3"><a href="#fn-3" class="footnote-ref">3</a></sup>, and now looks poised to move towards our 4th pattern: mixins.</p>
<p><strong>Decorator Pattern</strong>: Used to provide a nice interface for separating out logic shared by multiple components and centralizing it.</p>
<h4>Mixins</h4>
<p>The newest pattern that React has added to its bag of code reuse tricks is also one of the oldest.  In older versions of React there was a feature called “mixins” that was <a href="https://reactjs.org/blog/2016/07/13/mixins-considered-harmful.html">later deprecated due to its ease of mis-use</a>.  “Mixins” are gone now, but the “Mixin pattern” is back!  React is in the process of introducing <a href="https://reactjs.org/docs/hooks-intro.html">hooks</a>, a new way of doing mixins.</p>
<p>So first, what is a mixin?  It is yet another way of defining shared behavior onto a class, in this case providing methods and/or data that are “mixed in” to one or more classes.  It differs from inheritance because a class using a mixin doesn’t have to use the mixin as a parent class, and the class may use several mixins at once.  Mixins that are used together in one class may not be used together in another.  Mixins also different from the decorator pattern, because the mixin is part of the class definition, not something that is applied dynamically later.</p>
<p>Mixins are useful when you have classes with different purposes that shouldn’t share an inheritance tree but do have some shared behavior.  In practice though they have historically been tricky to use because it is easy to tightly bind mixin code to the implementation of the code that it is mixed into.  Poorly implemented Mixins can result in naming collisions, inflexible code, and hard to trace errors.</p>
<p>React Hooks may not look like mixins, since they are used in a function, not a class.  But they fill the exact same role as traditional mixins, while avoiding some of the footguns (no naming collisions!).  Let’s look at an example from Dan Abramov’s blog post <a href="https://medium.com/@dan_abramov/making-sense-of-react-hooks-fdbde8803889">introducing hooks</a>.</p>
<div class="gatsby-highlight" data-language="javascript">
      <pre class="language-javascript"><code class="language-javascript"><span class="token keyword">function</span> <span class="token function">useWindowWidth</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
  <span class="token keyword">const</span> <span class="token punctuation">[</span>width<span class="token punctuation">,</span> setWidth<span class="token punctuation">]</span> <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token function">useState</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>window<span class="token punctuation">.</span>innerWidth<span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>

  <span class="token function">useEffect</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token operator">=></span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
    <span class="token keyword">const</span> <span class="token function-variable function">handleResize</span> <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token operator">=></span> <span class="token function">setWidth</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>window<span class="token punctuation">.</span>innerWidth<span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
    window<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">addEventListener</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token string">'resize'</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span> handleResize<span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
    <span class="token keyword">return</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token operator">=></span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
      window<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">removeEventListener</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token string">'resize'</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span> handleResize<span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
    <span class="token punctuation">}</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
  <span class="token punctuation">}</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>

  <span class="token keyword">return</span> width<span class="token punctuation">;</span>
<span class="token punctuation">}</span></code></pre>
      </div>
<p>This is a hook that provides the width of the current window to a React component, updating each time the window is resized.  You would use it in practice like this example of a header bar that replaces its menu items with a hamburger menu on smaller screens:</p>
<div class="gatsby-highlight" data-language="javascript">
      <pre class="language-javascript"><code class="language-javascript"><span class="token keyword">const</span> <span class="token function-variable function">Header</span> <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token operator">=></span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
    <span class="token keyword">let</span> windowWidth <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token function">useWindowWidth</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
    <span class="token keyword">let</span> showHamburgerMenu <span class="token operator">=</span> windowWidth <span class="token operator">&lt;</span> <span class="token number">800</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>

    <span class="token keyword">return</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token operator">&lt;</span>div<span class="token operator">></span>
        <span class="token operator">&lt;</span>Logo<span class="token operator">></span>
        <span class="token punctuation">{</span>showHamburgerMenu <span class="token operator">?</span> <span class="token operator">&lt;</span>HamburgerMenu<span class="token operator">/</span><span class="token operator">></span> <span class="token punctuation">:</span> <span class="token operator">&lt;</span>MenuItems<span class="token operator">/</span><span class="token operator">></span><span class="token punctuation">}</span>
    <span class="token operator">&lt;</span><span class="token operator">/</span>div<span class="token operator">></span><span class="token punctuation">)</span>
<span class="token punctuation">}</span></code></pre>
      </div>
<p>This usage is different from a normal helper function, because it enhances the component; because this is using React’s state code within the hook, this component will automatically update when needed.  So it is a way of reusing component behavior like Higher Order Components.  But we lose a lot of the disadvantages of HOCs.   <code class="language-text">useWindowWidth</code> and <code class="language-text">Header</code> are extremely loosely coupled.  <code class="language-text">useWindowWidth</code> doesn’t know anything about the header bar structure or logic, or the rules for when things should show.  It is only providing information.  At the same time, if we refactored it to get the window size in some other way, or to throttle updates, we wouldn’t have to change anything about <code class="language-text">Header</code>, since all it knows is that <code class="language-text">useWindowWidth</code> will occasionally provide it an updated windowWidth.</p>
<p>The functional style makes this look different than a traditional object oriented “mixin pattern” example, but it is using the same concepts and solving the same problems.  This way of doing things has advantages; because it is “just a function” that gets called, we never need to worry about it having a naming collision with a different class method, or having to be aware of the structure of the outer component.  If it needs component specific information, we can just pass it an argument.</p>
<p>With Hooks, we can create a much cleaner version of our Higher Order Component example from the decorators section.</p>
<div class="gatsby-highlight" data-language="javascript">
      <pre class="language-javascript"><code class="language-javascript"><span class="token comment">// defined in a library file</span>
<span class="token keyword">const</span> <span class="token function-variable function">useIncrement</span> <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span>initial <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token number">0</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token operator">=></span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
   <span class="token keyword">const</span> <span class="token punctuation">[</span>count<span class="token punctuation">,</span> increment<span class="token punctuation">]</span> <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token function">useReducer</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>val <span class="token operator">=></span> val <span class="token operator">+</span> <span class="token number">1</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span> initial<span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
   <span class="token keyword">return</span> <span class="token punctuation">[</span>count<span class="token punctuation">,</span> increment<span class="token punctuation">]</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
<span class="token punctuation">}</span>

<span class="token comment">// counter.js</span>
<span class="token keyword">const</span> <span class="token function-variable function">Counter</span> <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token operator">=></span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
    <span class="token keyword">let</span> <span class="token punctuation">[</span>count<span class="token punctuation">,</span> increment<span class="token punctuation">]</span> <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token function">useIncrement</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
    <span class="token keyword">return</span> <span class="token operator">&lt;</span>FancyLayout<span class="token operator">></span>
        <span class="token operator">&lt;</span>FancyDisplay<span class="token operator">></span>
            Current Count<span class="token punctuation">:</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>count<span class="token punctuation">}</span>
        <span class="token operator">&lt;</span><span class="token operator">/</span>FancyDisplay<span class="token operator">></span>
        <span class="token operator">&lt;</span>FancyButton
            className<span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token string">"incrementCounterBtn"</span>
            onClick<span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token punctuation">{</span>increment<span class="token punctuation">}</span>
        <span class="token operator">></span>Increment<span class="token operator">&lt;</span><span class="token operator">/</span>FancyButton<span class="token operator">></span>
    <span class="token operator">&lt;</span><span class="token operator">/</span>FancyLayout<span class="token operator">></span>
<span class="token punctuation">}</span></code></pre>
      </div>
<p>As with decorators we’ve extracted the logic in a reusable form, but we’ve done so with much less boilerplate.  I’ve removed the intermediate <code class="language-text">CounterDisplay</code> here, because if we’re not using it for anything else, it is easy enough to just include the hook directly in the definition.  But if we wanted, we could easily use that <code class="language-text">CounterDisplay</code> component with a hooks enabled wrapper component:</p>
<div class="gatsby-highlight" data-language="javascript">
      <pre class="language-javascript"><code class="language-javascript"><span class="token keyword">const</span> <span class="token function-variable function">Counter</span> <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token operator">=></span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>
    <span class="token keyword">let</span> <span class="token punctuation">[</span>count<span class="token punctuation">,</span> increment<span class="token punctuation">]</span> <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token function">useIncrement</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
    <span class="token keyword">return</span> <span class="token operator">&lt;</span>CounterDisplay count<span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token punctuation">{</span>count<span class="token punctuation">}</span> increment<span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token punctuation">{</span>increment<span class="token punctuation">}</span><span class="token operator">/</span><span class="token operator">></span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>
<span class="token punctuation">}</span></code></pre>
      </div>
<p><strong>Mixin Pattern</strong>: Hooks use a variation on the Mixin pattern to allow sharing related behavior and data between unrelated function components easily.</p>
<h3>Summary</h3>
<p>If I took one thing out of this analysis personally, it was a renewed appreciation for considering the needs of a situation and finding the right approach for the job, rather than trying to fit every problem to my favorite solution.  I’m over 2000 words and I haven’t even addressed all the different strategies React and the React community use for code re-use. <em>Sorry render props</em> 😢.   So next time you run into an architecture problem, consider a few different solutions and their tradeoffs.</p>
<p><strong>TL;DR</strong></p>
<p>React uses a variety of patterns for code reuse.
<strong>Inheritance Pattern</strong>: Used sparingly to share common code across React class components.
<strong>Composition Pattern</strong>: The core pattern for separating concerns while creating complex UIs with React.
<strong>Decorator Pattern</strong>: Used to provide a nice interface for separating out logic shared by multiple components and centralizing it.
<strong>Mixin Pattern</strong>: Hooks use a variation on the Mixin pattern to allow sharing related behavior and data between unrelated function components easily.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn-1">
<p>Clunky JS based interfaces for specifying child components are visually difficult to scan and understand, while solutions that use external template files spread logic about a single component to multiple files, making it harder to keep everything in the developers head.</p>
<a href="#fnref-1" class="footnote-backref">↩</a>
</li>
<li id="fn-2">
<p>Note that the decorator pattern is not the same thing as the TC39 proposal to <a href="https://github.com/tc39/proposal-decorators">add a decorator syntax to JavaScript</a>, or the TypeScript feature of the same name.  Both are related to modifying class behavior, but the mechanisms are not the same.</p>
<a href="#fnref-2" class="footnote-backref">↩</a>
</li>
<li id="fn-3">
<p>Render props ultimately qualify as an advanced composition technique and so didn’t get their own heading here, but they’re definitely worth understanding.</p>
<a href="#fnref-3" class="footnote-backref">↩</a>
</li>
</ol>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>ben@benmccormick.org (Ben McCormick)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Book Review: Info We Trust]]></title>
            <link>https://benmccormick.org/2019/01/30/book-review-info-we-trust</link>
            <guid>https://benmccormick.org/2019/01/30/book-review-info-we-trust</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jan 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Sometimes surprises are good.  I bought RJ Andrews new book <a href="https://amzn.to/2Ww9BBl">Info We Trust</a> expecting to get some practical tips on how to create better data visualizations.  But frankly there’s very little in the way of “how to” in this book.  Instead I was treated to a deeply engaging book that’s part history of data visualization, part exploration of human psychology, and 100% a love letter to “data storytelling”, with brief detours into linguistics, museum curation sentence diagramming and propaganda posters. If you’re looking to know when to use a bar chart vs a pie chart in your powerpoint slides, this book will be a disappointment.  But if you want to learn how to think deeply about telling stories with data, or just enjoy seeing somebody who loves their topic nerd out about it for 200 pages in a beautiful formatted book, this may be for you.</p>
<p>Let’s start with that beautiful book.  This is not a read that you want to pick up on Kindle.  The book is littered with fascinating illustrations, all <a href="https://infowetrust.com/illustrations/">hand drawn by the author (!!!)</a>, and almost every page has interesting quotes, examples and tangents in the marginalia.  Here are a few random pages that I snapped with my phone while writing this;  it turns out that every single page is this beautiful.</p>
<p><a
    class="gatsby-resp-image-link"
    href="/static/a84e2d937fc60341661ef1066f2f838e/0cf58/page1.jpg"
    style="display: block"
    target="_blank"
    rel="noopener"
  >
    <span
    class="gatsby-resp-image-wrapper"
    style="position: relative; display: block;  max-width: 570px; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"
  >
    <span
      class="gatsby-resp-image-background-image"
      style="padding-bottom: 74.90234375%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url('data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAAPABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAFgABAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAwQA/8QAFgEBAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEC/9oADAMBAAIQAxAAAAFqImyow5f/xAAbEAACAQUAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEiEBAgMRIv/aAAgBAQABBQKyCHTHU3LdMf/EABQRAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABD/2gAIAQMBAT8BP//EABQRAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABD/2gAIAQIBAT8BP//EABkQAQACAwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEAAiAhkf/aAAgBAQAGPwIIzdDmH//EABkQAAMBAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABMSERsf/aAAgBAQABPyGZiSEoFtylDLC2p4j4Z//aAAwDAQACAAMAAAAQ/O//xAAVEQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEf/aAAgBAwEBPxBX/8QAFREBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABH/2gAIAQIBAT8QR//EABsQAQADAQADAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEAESFRMXGR/9oACAEBAAE/EGENEUL4i2rSKpft2LHolJVQ4+QxemZGz//Z'); background-size: cover; display: block;"
    ></span>
    <img
        class="gatsby-resp-image-image"
        style="width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;box-shadow:inset 0px 0px 0px 400px white;"
        alt="Page 1"
        title=""
        src="/static/a84e2d937fc60341661ef1066f2f838e/6fbc3/page1.jpg"
        srcset="/static/a84e2d937fc60341661ef1066f2f838e/da4c7/page1.jpg 143w,
/static/a84e2d937fc60341661ef1066f2f838e/1d39e/page1.jpg 285w,
/static/a84e2d937fc60341661ef1066f2f838e/6fbc3/page1.jpg 570w,
/static/a84e2d937fc60341661ef1066f2f838e/9d77e/page1.jpg 855w,
/static/a84e2d937fc60341661ef1066f2f838e/e356a/page1.jpg 1140w,
/static/a84e2d937fc60341661ef1066f2f838e/4208b/page1.jpg 1710w,
/static/a84e2d937fc60341661ef1066f2f838e/0cf58/page1.jpg 2048w"
        sizes="(max-width: 570px) 100vw, 570px"
      />
  </span>
  </a>
<a
    class="gatsby-resp-image-link"
    href="/static/9cbe611fd78dc6684980f96b90447a9c/0cf58/page2.jpg"
    style="display: block"
    target="_blank"
    rel="noopener"
  >
    <span
    class="gatsby-resp-image-wrapper"
    style="position: relative; display: block;  max-width: 570px; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"
  >
    <span
      class="gatsby-resp-image-background-image"
      style="padding-bottom: 74.90234375%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url('data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAAPABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAFgABAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAwQA/8QAFQEBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAH/2gAMAwEAAhADEAAAAaXiWH0OP//EABoQAAICAwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAECAAMEESL/2gAIAQEAAQUCrgPTKrFTC2icmsT/xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAEDAQE/AT//xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAECAQE/AT//xAAZEAEAAgMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAASEQMqH/2gAIAQEABj8CSuMW24//xAAZEAADAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAREhMZH/2gAIAQEAAT8haMwCio+GgvdMGUr0f//aAAwDAQACAAMAAAAQZx//xAAVEQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEf/aAAgBAwEBPxBX/8QAFREBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABH/2gAIAQIBAT8QR//EABsQAQADAAMBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEAESFRYZHR/9oACAEBAAE/EGEXL8JVY7IAMBpJWYXdVnGOVYcfCf/Z'); background-size: cover; display: block;"
    ></span>
    <img
        class="gatsby-resp-image-image"
        style="width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;box-shadow:inset 0px 0px 0px 400px white;"
        alt="Page 2"
        title=""
        src="/static/9cbe611fd78dc6684980f96b90447a9c/6fbc3/page2.jpg"
        srcset="/static/9cbe611fd78dc6684980f96b90447a9c/da4c7/page2.jpg 143w,
/static/9cbe611fd78dc6684980f96b90447a9c/1d39e/page2.jpg 285w,
/static/9cbe611fd78dc6684980f96b90447a9c/6fbc3/page2.jpg 570w,
/static/9cbe611fd78dc6684980f96b90447a9c/9d77e/page2.jpg 855w,
/static/9cbe611fd78dc6684980f96b90447a9c/e356a/page2.jpg 1140w,
/static/9cbe611fd78dc6684980f96b90447a9c/4208b/page2.jpg 1710w,
/static/9cbe611fd78dc6684980f96b90447a9c/0cf58/page2.jpg 2048w"
        sizes="(max-width: 570px) 100vw, 570px"
      />
  </span>
  </a>
<a
    class="gatsby-resp-image-link"
    href="/static/cb1d42855dc02f90a8197db101881b61/6964c/page3.jpg"
    style="display: block"
    target="_blank"
    rel="noopener"
  >
    <span
    class="gatsby-resp-image-wrapper"
    style="position: relative; display: block;  max-width: 570px; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"
  >
    <span
      class="gatsby-resp-image-background-image"
      style="padding-bottom: 75%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url('data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAAPABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAGAAAAwEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAMEAQL/xAAVAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABAP/aAAwDAQACEAMQAAAB2uJxcDQf/8QAGhABAAMBAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAgEDEgATIf/aAAgBAQABBQKkmDgatpOio6X99T3/xAAVEQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEf/aAAgBAwEBPwFX/8QAFBEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEP/aAAgBAgEBPwE//8QAGxAAAgMAAwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAERISICcZH/2gAIAQEABj8CVIeePhmuhQxwy2f/xAAbEAACAwEBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAREhMXFBYf/aAAgBAQABPyGBVSpw+jW6DqtEsYhiFCfQg6nD/9oADAMBAAIAAwAAABDn/wD/xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAEDAQE/EB//xAAWEQEBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAARH/2gAIAQIBAT8QZH//xAAcEAEAAwACAwAAAAAAAAAAAAABABEhMWFxkdH/2gAIAQEAAT8QfXAShd3WDluRFrfUUCDdEu3Y5NAA2PFeIKqqDR5lGFTt8n//2Q=='); background-size: cover; display: block;"
    ></span>
    <img
        class="gatsby-resp-image-image"
        style="width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;box-shadow:inset 0px 0px 0px 400px white;"
        alt="Page 3"
        title=""
        src="/static/cb1d42855dc02f90a8197db101881b61/6fbc3/page3.jpg"
        srcset="/static/cb1d42855dc02f90a8197db101881b61/da4c7/page3.jpg 143w,
/static/cb1d42855dc02f90a8197db101881b61/1d39e/page3.jpg 285w,
/static/cb1d42855dc02f90a8197db101881b61/6fbc3/page3.jpg 570w,
/static/cb1d42855dc02f90a8197db101881b61/9d77e/page3.jpg 855w,
/static/cb1d42855dc02f90a8197db101881b61/6964c/page3.jpg 1024w"
        sizes="(max-width: 570px) 100vw, 570px"
      />
  </span>
  </a>
<a
    class="gatsby-resp-image-link"
    href="/static/273d364db3287a8954088f89815e0c9c/6964c/page4.jpg"
    style="display: block"
    target="_blank"
    rel="noopener"
  >
    <span
    class="gatsby-resp-image-wrapper"
    style="position: relative; display: block;  max-width: 570px; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"
  >
    <span
      class="gatsby-resp-image-background-image"
      style="padding-bottom: 75%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url('data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAAPABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAFwABAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAMCBP/EABUBAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAC/9oADAMBAAIQAxAAAAFaWiLvRX//xAAZEAADAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABAgMAESH/2gAIAQEAAQUClKeSMs8QrLVcHPQfP//EABURAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAR/9oACAEDAQE/AVf/xAAVEQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEf/aAAgBAgEBPwFH/8QAGxAAAgMAAwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAECITEREiL/2gAIAQEABj8CXMFZJdFp5w0bhdlqz//EABsQAQADAAMBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEAESExYXHR/9oACAEBAAE/IUli60nPelK1l6XCvxKqbfUZPsn/2gAMAwEAAgADAAAAECjf/8QAFREBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQD/2gAIAQMBAT8Qhhf/xAAWEQEBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABABH/2gAIAQIBAT8QRk7f/8QAHBABAQADAQADAAAAAAAAAAAAAREAIUExUYGR/9oACAEBAAE/EOAAqQXR+YhYgqioX59xmaABLPvC9JJN+ecxg0UC7D3ePZEaaY5//9k='); background-size: cover; display: block;"
    ></span>
    <img
        class="gatsby-resp-image-image"
        style="width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;box-shadow:inset 0px 0px 0px 400px white;"
        alt="Page 4"
        title=""
        src="/static/273d364db3287a8954088f89815e0c9c/6fbc3/page4.jpg"
        srcset="/static/273d364db3287a8954088f89815e0c9c/da4c7/page4.jpg 143w,
/static/273d364db3287a8954088f89815e0c9c/1d39e/page4.jpg 285w,
/static/273d364db3287a8954088f89815e0c9c/6fbc3/page4.jpg 570w,
/static/273d364db3287a8954088f89815e0c9c/9d77e/page4.jpg 855w,
/static/273d364db3287a8954088f89815e0c9c/6964c/page4.jpg 1024w"
        sizes="(max-width: 570px) 100vw, 570px"
      />
  </span>
  </a></p>
<p>In addition to the eye candy, Andrews mostly avoids giving readers rules, but instead dives deep into the whys of data storytelling.  Things I was left thinking about:</p>
<ol>
<li>The way I think about bars vs columns differently based on my different assumptions about distance vs stacks of items</li>
<li>How the plethora of data available in the world today has a cost: our attention.  That has left me thinking both about designing interfaces that manage attention, but also how to reclaim my own distracted attention.</li>
<li>The difference between data and information, and how each can be useful.  How in the product I work on we can help users get access to enough raw data to explore on their own, but also give them meaningful “information” derived from that data.</li>
<li>I was motivated to get better at drawing, and explaining things with images in my day to day work.  I don’t do this enough.</li>
</ol>
<p>If all of that sounds too high level and impractical for you, this is probably not the book for you.  But anyone who is already a data viz geek will find something to love, and as somebody who is tangential to the field it certainly expanded my mind and gave me a lot to think about.  All in all, this one is easy to recommend. <a href="https://amzn.to/2Ww9BBl">Check it out!</a></p>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>ben@benmccormick.org (Ben McCormick)</author>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>